[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "Load torques can be classified into how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Three",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Four",
            "d) Five"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Load torques can have two types. They are active and passive load torques. Active load torques are able to run the motor under equilibrium conditions and their sign remains the same even if the motor rotation changes but passive load torques always opposes the motion by changing their sign with the change in rotation of the motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "Rolling mills exhibit what type of load torque characteristics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant torque characteristics",
            "b) Linearly rising torque characteristics",
            "c) Non-Linearly rising torque characteristics",
            "d) Non-Linearly decreasing torque characteristics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rolling mills are an example of non-linearly decreasing torque characteristics because torque and speed exhibits inversely proportional relationships and power are constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "What is the relationship between torque and speed in constant type loads?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Torque is independent of speed",
            "b) Torque linearly increases with increase in speed",
            "c) Torque non-linearly increases with an increase in speed",
            "d) Torque non-linearly decreases with an increase in speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Speed hoist is a perfect example of constant type loads in which torque variation is independent of speed. The speed-torque characteristics of this type of load are given by T=K where K is a constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "What type of force handles for active torques?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strong nuclear forces",
            "b) Weak nuclear forces",
            "c) Gravitational forces",
            "d) Electrostatic forces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Torque varies with a square of speed in the windage load torque component whereas in coulomb torque component torque is constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "Among the following which one exhibits linearly rising load torque characteristics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elevators",
            "b) Rolling Mills",
            "c) Fan load",
            "d) Separately excited dc generator connected to the resistive load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gravitational forces are responsible for active torques. Active torques due to gravitational forces can be obtained in the case of hoists, lifts or elevators and railway locomotives operating on gradients.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "What is the condition for the steady-state operation of the motor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Load torque > Motor torque",
            "b) Load torque <<<< Motor torque",
            "c) Load torque = Motor torque",
            "d) Load torque < Motor torque"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Passive torques are due to friction or shear and deformation in elastic bodies. They always oppose the motion, restricting the motion of the machine. "
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "Choose the correct one. (* stands for multiplication, J represents the moment of inertia, w represents angular speed).",
        "Options": [
            "a) J*d(w)/dt = Load torque – Motor torque",
            "b) J*d(w)/dt = Load torque + Motor torque",
            "c) J*d(w)/dt = Motor torque – Load torque",
            "d) J*d(w)/dt = Load torque * Motor torque"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Separately excited dc generator connected to the resistive load is an example of linearly rising load torque characteristics as the torque increases linearly with an increase in speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "Regenerative braking mode can be achieved in which quadrant (V-I curve)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Third",
            "b) Second",
            "c) Fourth",
            "d) First"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Regenerative braking is only available in second quadrant as power from motor is fed back to source. Back emf generated (Eb) is more than armature terminal (Vt) so it works as a generator."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Fan type of loads exhibits which type of load torque characteristics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant torque characteristics",
            "b) Linearly rising torque characteristics",
            "c) Non-Linearly rising torque characteristics",
            "d) Non-Linearly decreasing torque characteristics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Torque produced by the fan is directly proportional to square of speed throughout the range of usable fan speeds. This type of loads exhibits non-linearly rising torque characteristics."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "Type-A chopper is used for obtaining which type of mode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Motoring mode",
            "b) Regenerative braking mode",
            "c) Reverse motoring mode",
            "d) Reverse regenerative braking mode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Only motoring mode is available in case of step-down chopper (Type-A chopper). Value of output voltage (Vo) is less than the input voltage (Vin) in case of step-down chopper."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of angular acceleration of motor using the given data: J = 20 kg-m2, load torque = 20 N-m, motor torque = 60 N-m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 rad/s2",
            "b) 2 rad/s2",
            "c) 3 rad/s2",
            "d) 4 rad/s2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Using the dynamic equation of motor J*(angular acceleration) = Motor torque – Load torque: 20*(angular acceleration) = 60-20=40, angular acceleration=2 rad/s2."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "230V, 10A, 1500rpm DC separately excited motor having resistance of .2 ohm excited from external dc voltage source of 50V. Calculate the torque developed by the motor on full load.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 13.89 N-m",
            "b) 14.52 N-m",
            "c) 13.37 N-m",
            "d) 14.42 N-m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Back emf developed in the motor during full load can be calculated using equation Eb = Vt- I*Ra = 228 V and machine constant Km = Eb / Wm which is equal to 1.452. Torque can be calculated by using the relation T = Km* I = 1.452*10 = 14.52 N-m."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "Boost converter is used to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Step down the voltage",
            "b) Step up the voltage",
            "c) Equalize the voltage",
            "d) Step up and step down the voltage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Output voltage of boost converter is Vo = Vin / 1 – D. Value of duty cycle is less than 1 which makes the Vo > Vin as denominator value decreases and becomes less than 1. Boost converter is used to step up voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "Calculate the power developed by motor using the given data: Eb = 20V and I = 10 A. (Assume rotational losses are neglected)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400 W",
            "b) 200 W",
            "c) 300 W",
            "d) 500 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In reverse motoring mode motor rotates in opposite to original direction as direction of motor torque changes which makes the motor to run in opposite direction and load torque tries to oppose the motion of motor.\t"
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "Which one is an example of variable loss?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Windage loss",
            "b) Hysteresis loss",
            "c) Armature copper loss",
            "d) Friction loss"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Power developed by motor can be calculated using the formula P = Eb*I = 20*10 = 200 W. If rotational losses are neglected, power developed becomes equal to the shaft power of motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "What is the empirical formula for the tractive force required to overcome curve resistance? (W-the weight of the body, R – radius of curvature)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 710×W÷R",
            "b) 700×W÷R",
            "c) 720×W÷R",
            "d) 750×W÷R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fc= 700×W÷R is the tractive force required to overcome curve resistance where W is the weight of the body in Kg and R be the radius of curvature in meters."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "Force resisting the upward motion of a body on an inclined plane is given by (alpha – the angle of inclination, W- the weight of the body).",
        "Options": [
            "a) F = W×sin(alpha)",
            "b) F = W×cosec(alpha)",
            "c) F = W×sec(alpha)",
            "d) F = W×cos(alpha)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a body is moving upward on an inclined plane its weight can be resolved in two perpendicular components that are W×sin(alpha) and W×cos(alpha). W×cos(alpha) is the component that is opposite to normal of the inclined plane and W×sin(alpha) is the component that opposes the upward motion of the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "The unit of the torque is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) N-m",
            "b) N-m2",
            "c) N-m/sec",
            "d) N-Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Torque is defined as the vector product of displacement and force. The unit of the force is Newton(N) and of the displacement is a meter (m) so the unit of torque in N-m."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the torque when 10 N force is applied perpendicular to a 10 m length of rod fixed at the center.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200 N-m",
            "b) 300 N-m",
            "c) 100 N-m",
            "d) 400 N-m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Torque can be calculated using the relation T = (length of rod) × (Force applied) = r×F×sin90. F is given as 10 N and r is 10 m then torque is 10×10 = 100 N-m. (the angle between F and r is 90 degrees)"
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "What is the dimensional formula for torque?",
        "Options": [
            "a) [ML2T-2] ",
            "b) [MLT-2] ",
            "c) [M1L2T-3] ",
            "d) [LT-2]"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Torque is a vector product of force and displacement. Dimensional formula for force is [MLT-2] and displacement is [L] so dimensional formula for torque is [MLT-2] [L] = [ML2T-2]."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "Buck converter is used to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Step down the voltage",
            "b) Step up the voltage",
            "c) Equalize the voltage",
            "d) Step up and step down the voltage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The output voltage of the buck converter is Vo = D×Vin. The value of the duty cycle is less than one which makes the Vo < Vin. The buck converter is used to step down voltage. Vin is a fixed voltage and Vo is a variable voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "250V, 15A, 1100 rpm separately excited dc motor with armature resistance (Ra) equal to 2 ohms.  Calculate back emf developed in the motor when it operates on half of the full load. (Assume rotational losses are neglected)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 210V",
            "b) 240V",
            "c) 230V",
            "d) 235V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: J×d(w)÷d(t) = Motor torque – Load torque is the dynamic equation of motor. If starting torque (motor torque) is less than the load torque then d(w)÷d(t) <0, acceleration <0 so the motor will decelerate and fails to start."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "Duty cycle (D) is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ton÷Toff",
            "b) Ton÷(Ton+ Toff)",
            "c) Ton÷2×(Ton+ Toff)",
            "d) Ton÷2×Toff"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Duty cycle (D) is defined as the ratio of time for which system is active to the total time period. It is also known as the power cycle. It has no unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "A 220 V, 1000 rpm, 60 A separately-excited dc motor has an armature resistance of .5 ω. It is fed from single-phase full converter with an ac source voltage of 230 V, 50Hz. Assuming continuous conduction, the firing angle for rated motor torque at (-400) rpm is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 122.4°",
            "b) 117.6°",
            "c) 130.1°",
            "d) 102.8°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: During rated operating conditions of the motor, Eb = Vt-Ia×Ra = 220-60×.5=190 V. As Eb=Kmwm so Km=190×60÷(2×3.14×1000) = 1.8152 V-s/rad. Back emf at (-400 rpm) is Kmwm = 1.8152×(2×3.14×(-400))÷60 = -76 V. Now Vt = -76+60×.5 = -46 V. Average voltage of single-phase full converter is 2×Vm×cos(α)÷3.14. The output of the converter is connected to the input terminal of the motor so α = cos-1(-46×3.14÷2×230×1.414) = 102.8o."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the angular acceleration of the motor using the given data: J= 50 kg-m2, load torque = 40 N-m, motor torque = 10 N-m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) -.7 rad/s2",
            "b) -.6 rad/s2",
            "c) -.3 rad/s2",
            "d) -.4 rad/s2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Angular acceleration is defined as a derivate of angular velocity with respect to time. It is generally written as α. The unit of angular velocity is rad/sec and of time is second so the unit of angular acceleration is rad/s2."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "The principle of step-up chopper can be employed for the ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Motoring mode",
            "b) Regenerative mode",
            "c) Plugging",
            "d) Reverse motoring mode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Using the dynamic equation of motor J*(angular acceleration) = Motor torque – Load torque: 50*(angular acceleration) = 10-40 = -30, angular acceleration=-.6 rad/s2. The motor will decelerate and will fail to start."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "A Buck-Boost converter is used to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Step down the voltage",
            "b) Step up the voltage",
            "c) Equalize the voltage",
            "d) Step up and step down the voltage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The step-down chopper is used in motoring mode but a step-up chopper can operate only braking mode because the characteristics are in the second quadrant only."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "Which of the following converter circuit operations will be unstable for a large duty cycle ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Buck converter",
            "b) Boost converter",
            "c) Buck-Boost converter",
            "d) Boost converter and Buck-Boost converter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The output voltage of the buck-boost converter is Vo = D×Vin ÷ (1-D). It can step up and step down the voltage depending upon the value of the duty cycle. If the value of the duty cycle is less than .5 it will work as a buck converter and for duty cycle greater than .5 it will work as a boost converter."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Calculate the shaft power developed by a motor using the given data: Eb = 50V and I = 60 A. Assume frictional losses are 400 W and windage losses are 600 W.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4000 W",
            "b) 2000 W",
            "c) 1000 W",
            "d) 1500 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The output voltage of the buck converter and buck-boost converter are Vo=Vin ÷ (1-D) and Vo = D×Vin ÷ (1-D) respectively. When the value of the duty cycle tends to 1 output voltage tends to infinity."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Which one of the following devices have low power losses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MOSFET",
            "b) IGBT",
            "c) SCR",
            "d) BJT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Shaft power developed by the motor can be calculated using the formula P = Eb*I-(rotational losses) = 50*60 = 3000 – (600+400) = 2000 W. If rotational losses are neglected, the power developed becomes equal to the shaft power of the motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Servo motors are an example of which type of load?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulsating loads",
            "b) Short time loads",
            "c) Impact loads",
            "d) Short time intermittent loads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Servo motors are motors with control feedback. The motor can be AC or DC. This is an example of short time loads. They have a high torque to inertia ratio and high-speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Load torque of the crane is independent of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speed",
            "b) Seebeck effect",
            "c) Hall effect",
            "d) Thomson effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Load torque of the crane is independent of speed. They are short time intermittent types of loads. They require constant power for a short period of time."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "R.M.S value of the sinusoidal waveform V=Vmsin(ωt+α).",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vm÷2½",
            "b) Vm÷2¼",
            "c) Vm÷2¾",
            "d) Vm÷3½"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Angular velocity is defined as the rate of change of angular displacement with respect to time. Angular displacement is generally expressed in terms of a radian. The unit of angular velocity is rad/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "Calculate the time period of the waveform x(t)=24sin(24πt+π÷4).",
        "Options": [
            "a) .064 sec",
            "b) .047 sec",
            "c) .083 sec",
            "d) .015 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: R.M.S value of the sinusoidal waveform is Vm÷2½ and r.m.s value of the trapezoidal waveform is Vm÷3½. The peak value of the sinusoidal waveform is Vm."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "Which of the following devices should be used as a switch for high power and high voltage application?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GTO",
            "b) MOSFET",
            "c) TRIAC",
            "d) Thyristor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The fundamental time period of the sine wave is 2π. The time period of x(t) is 2π÷24π=.083 sec. The time period is independent of phase shifting and time shifting."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Calculate the useful power developed by a motor using the given data: Pin = 3000 W, Ia = 60 A, Ra = .4 Ω. Assume frictional losses are 200 W and windage losses are 400 W.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 970 W",
            "b) 960 W",
            "c) 980 W",
            "d) 990 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Increasing turn-off time implies decreasing speed and majority carrier devices do not have any minority charge carrier storage so they have less turn-off time and hence MOSFET has the least turn off time. So, the increasing order of turn-off time is, MOSFET < IGBT < BJT < Thyristor."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Calculate the phase angle of the sinusoidal waveform y(t)=55sin(4πt+π÷8).",
        "Options": [
            "a) π÷8",
            "b) π÷5",
            "c) π÷7",
            "d) π÷4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thyristor is used for high power applications but it has a limited frequency range and cannot be used at high frequencies. A thyristor is a unidirectional, bipolar and semi-controlled device."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "The axis along which no emf is produced in the armature conductors is called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Geometrical Neutral Axis (GNA)",
            "b) Magnetic Neutral Axis (MNA)",
            "c) Axis of rotation",
            "d) Axis of revolution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The coil undergoing commutation must lie along the magnetic neutral axis so that no emf is induced and there is no sparking at the time of commutation."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "The generated e.m.f from 25-pole armature having 200 conductors driven at 10 rev/sec having flux per pole as 20 mWb, with two parallel paths is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400 V",
            "b) 500 V",
            "c) 200 V",
            "d) 300 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The generated can be calculated using the formula Eb = Φ×Z×N×P÷60×A, Φ represent flux per pole, Z represents the total number of conductors, P represents the number of poles, A represents the number of parallel paths, N represents speed in rpm. Eb = .02×25×200×600÷60×2= 500 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Which of the following motor can be referred as a universal motor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DC shunt motor",
            "b) DC compound motor",
            "c) Permanent magnet motor",
            "d) DC series motor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flux is the total amount of magnetic field lines passing through a given area. Φ is a dot product of magnetic flux density and area. The unit of the flux is Weber (Wb)."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "The phase difference between voltage and current in the inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45°",
            "b) 90°",
            "c) 80°",
            "d) 55°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DC series motor can operate on DC and AC. It is a universal motor. Universal motors are those motors that can operate on both DC and AC. DC shunt motor can only operate on DC because of pulsating torque in AC."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "The phase difference between voltage and current in the resistor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 85°",
            "b) 90°",
            "c) 0°",
            "d) 5°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the case of an inductor, the voltage leads the current by 90° or the current lags the voltage by 90o. The phase difference between voltage and current is 90°."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "The phase difference between voltage and current in the capacitor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 90°",
            "b) 80°",
            "c) 95°",
            "d) 91°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the case of a resistor, the voltage and current are in the same phase. The phase difference between voltage and current is 0°. The voltage drop in the resistor is given as V=IR."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "The slope of the I-V curve is 30°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between I and V is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.732 Ω",
            "b) 2.235 Ω",
            "c) 1.625 Ω",
            "d) 1.524 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the case of a capacitor, the voltage lags the current by 90° or the current leads the voltage by 90o. The phase difference between voltage and current is 90°."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "What is a mark to space ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ton÷Toff",
            "b) Ton÷(Ton- Toff)",
            "c) Ton÷2×(Ton*Toff)",
            "d) Ton÷2×Toff"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance. The slope given is 30° so R=1÷tan(30°)=1.732 Ω. The slope of the V-I curve is resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "What is the formula for the moment of inertia? (m – a mass of the body, r – distance from the axis of the rotation)",
        "Options": [
            "a) ∑miri2",
            "b) ∑miri",
            "c) ∑miri4",
            "d) ∑miri3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moment of inertia is the property by the virtue of which the body withstand the effect of angular acceleration. It depends on the shape and mass distribution of the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "The generated e.m.f from 50-pole armature having 400 conductors driven at 20 rev/sec having flux per pole as 30 mWb, with lap winding is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 230 V",
            "b) 140 V",
            "c) 240 V",
            "d) 250 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The generated can be calculated using the formula Eb = Φ×Z×N×P÷60×A, Φ represent flux per pole, Z represents the total number of conductors, P represents the number of poles, A represents the number of parallel paths, N represents speed in rpm. In lap winding number of parallel paths are equal to the number of poles. Eb = .03×50×400×1200÷60×50= 240 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the egg having a mass of 7 kg and radius of 44 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .968 kgm2",
            "b) 1.454 kgm2",
            "c) 1.545 kgm2",
            "d) 1.552 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moment of inertia is taken as the sum of the product of the mass of each particle with the square of their distance from the axis of the rotation. The unit of the moment of inertia is kg×m2=kgm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Which of the theorems helps in the calculation of the moment of inertia?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The theorem of Parallel and Perpendicular axes",
            "b) The theorem of Horizontal and Perpendicular axes",
            "c) The theorem of Vertical and Perpendicular axes",
            "d) The theorem of Parallel and Tilted axes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the egg can be calculated using the formula I=∑miri2. The mass of egg and radius is given. I=(7)×(.44)2=1.552 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "What is the unit of resistance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ohm",
            "b) ohm-1",
            "c) ohm2",
            "d) ohm5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The theorem of Parallel and Perpendicular axes helps in the calculation of the moment of inertia. The moment of inertia of the complex bodies can be easily calculated with the help of these theorems. "
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the frequency if the time period of the signal is 20 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.05 Hz",
            "b) 0.04 Hz",
            "c) 0.02 Hz",
            "d) 0.03 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resistance is the opposition offered by the body to the flow of current. It is the ratio of voltage and current. It is given in ohms."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 60°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.732 Ω",
            "b) 1.608 Ω",
            "c) 1.543 Ω",
            "d) 1.648 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The frequency is defined as the number of oscillations per second. It is reciprocal of the time period. It is expressed in Hz. F = 1÷T=1÷20=.05 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Calculate mark to space ratio if the system is on for 5 sec and off for 10 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .5",
            "b) .4",
            "c) .2",
            "d) .6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 60° so R=tan(60°)=1.732 Ω. The slope of the V-I curve is resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "A 4-pole lap wound generator with 720 armature conductors and a flux per pole of .003 Wb has an armature current of 50 A. The developed torque is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 17.25 N-m",
            "b) 17.19 N-m",
            "c) 16.54 N-m",
            "d) 16.89 N-m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The developed torque in the motor is Km×I. The value of machine constant(Km) is Eb÷ωm = Φ×Z×P÷2×3.14×A = .003×720×4÷2×3.14×4 = .3438 Vs/rad. The developed torque is .3438×50 = 17.19 N-m."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "The generated e.m.f from 70-pole armature having 100 conductors driven at 10 rev/sec having flux per pole as 20 mWb, with wave winding is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 730 V",
            "b) 740 V",
            "c) 700 V",
            "d) 690 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The generated e.m.f can be calculated using the formula Eb = Φ×Z×N×P÷60×A, Φ represent flux per pole, Z represents the total number of conductors, P represents the number of poles, A represents the number of parallel paths, N represents speed in rpm. In wave winding number of parallel paths are 2. Eb = .02×70×100×600÷60×2 = 700 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the sphere having a mass of 12 kg and radius of 78 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7.888 kgm2",
            "b) 7.300 kgm2",
            "c) 7.545 kgm2",
            "d) 7.552 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The current is the amount of charge that can flow through an area in a given amount of time. It is mathematically represented as d(q)/d(t). It is expressed in terms of Ampere."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "The most suitable servo-motor application is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) AC series motor",
            "b) DC series motor",
            "c) AC two-phase induction motor",
            "d) DC shunt motor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the egg can be calculated using the formula I=Σmiri2. The mass of egg and radius is given. I=(12)×(.78)2=7.300 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "In a DC series motor, the electromagnetic torque developed is proportional to ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ia",
            "b) Ia2",
            "c) Ia3",
            "d) Ia.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DC shunt motor has definite no-load speed, so they don’t ‘run away’ when the load is suddenly thrown off provided the field circuit remains closed. The speed for any load within the operating range of the motor can be readily obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the time period if the frequency of the signal is 70 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.014 sec",
            "b) 0.013 sec",
            "c) 0.017 sec",
            "d) 0.079 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a DC series motor, the electromagnetic torque developed is equal to KmΦIa. In a DC series, the motor field winding is connected in series with the armature so the flux in the field winding is proportional to current. T = KmΦIa α Ia2."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 90°. Calculate the value of resistance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.732 Ω",
            "b) 1.608 Ω",
            "c) 1.543 Ω",
            "d) 1.648 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The time period is defined as the time after the signal repeats itself. It is expressed in second. T =  1÷F=1÷70=.014 sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "In a DC shunt motor, the electromagnetic torque developed is proportional to ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ia",
            "b) Ia2",
            "c) Ia3",
            "d) Ia.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 90° so R=tan(90°)=infinite Ω. It behaves as an open-circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "What is the formula for the active power in the cylindrical rotor synchronous machine? (Eb represents armature emf, Vt represents terminal voltage, δ represents rotor angle, X represents reactance)",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eb×Vt×sinδ÷X",
            "b) Eb×Vt2×sinδ÷X",
            "c) Eb2×Vt×sinδ÷X",
            "d) Eb×Vt×sinδ÷X2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The real power in the cylindrical rotor machine is Eb×Vt×sinδ÷X. It is inversely proportional to the reactance. The stability of the machine is decided by the maximum power transfer capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "Calculate the power factor during the resonance condition.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .58",
            "b) .42",
            "c) .65",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Salient pole machines are more stable than cylindrical rotor machines because of the high short circuit ratio and more real power transfer capability. The air gap length in salient pole machines is more as compare to cylindrical rotor machines."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "Calculate the reactive power in a 5 Ω resistor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7 VAR",
            "b) 0 VAR",
            "c) 2 VAR",
            "d) 1 VAR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The reactive power is the useless power in case of electric circuits. It is the energy trapped that keeps on oscillating between inductive and capacitive element. It plays a vital role in generating flux in electrical machines. It is expressed in Volt Ampere reactive."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "What is the unit of the apparent or complex power?",
        "Options": [
            "a) VAR",
            "b) VA",
            "c) ohm",
            "d) Volt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: During the resonance condition, the reactive power generated by the capacitor is completely absorbed by the inductor. Only active power flows in the circuit. Net reactive power is equal to zero and cosΦ=1."
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the frequency of the DC supply.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 Hz",
            "b) 50 Hz",
            "c) 20 Hz",
            "d) 10 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 90°. Q = VIsin0 = 0 VAR."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 0°. Calculate the value of resistance. The graph is parallel to the x-axis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 Ω",
            "b) 1.8 Ω",
            "c) 0 Ω",
            "d) 2.2 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The apparent power in AC circuits is VI*. It is expressed in volt-amperes (VA). It consists of both active and reactive power. It is the vector sum of the real power and reactive power."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the duty cycle if the system is on for 5 sec and off for 10 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .333",
            "b) .444",
            "c) .201",
            "d) .642"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The frequency is defined as the number of oscillations per second. It is reciprocal of the time period. DC supply magnitude is constant. It does not change with time so the frequency of DC supply is 0 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Swinburne’s test can be conducted on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Series motor",
            "b) Shunt motor",
            "c) Compound motor",
            "d) Shunt and compound motor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The test is practically applicable for machines which have flux constant like the shunt and compound machines as this is a no-load test and DC series motor should not be run at no-load because of high speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "The generated e.m.f from 20-pole armature having 800 conductors driven at 30 rev/sec having flux per pole as 60 mWb, with 16 parallel paths is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1900 V",
            "b) 1840 V",
            "c) 1700 V",
            "d) 1800 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The generated e.m.f can be calculated using the formula Eb = Φ×Z×N×P÷60×A, Φ represent flux per pole, Z represents the total number of conductors, P represents the number of poles, A represents the number of parallel paths, N represents speed in rpm. Eb = .06×20×1800×800÷60×16 = 1800 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Calculate the mass of the ball having a moment of inertia 4.5 kgm2 and radius of 14 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 229.59 kg",
            "b) 228.56 kg",
            "c) 228.54 kg",
            "d) 227.52 kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The active power in the electrical circuits is a useful power. It determines the power factor of the system. It is expressed in terms of Watt. P=VIcosΦ."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "What is the unit of the intensity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Watt/m2",
            "b) Watt/m",
            "c) Watt/m4",
            "d) Watt/m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the ball can be calculated using the formula I=∑miri2. The moment of inertia of ball and radius is given. M=(4.5)÷(.14)2 = 229.59 kg. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the frequency if the signal completes half of the cycle in 70 sec. Assume signal is periodic.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.00714 Hz",
            "b) 0.00456 Hz",
            "c) 0.00845 Hz",
            "d) 0.00145 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Field control method is generally used for obtaining the speeds greater than the base speed. It is also known as flux weakening method. It is suitable for constant power drives."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 26°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .487 Ω",
            "b) .482 Ω",
            "c) .483 Ω",
            "d) .448 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Intensity is defined as the amount of power incident on a particular area. It is mathematically expressed as I = Power incident (Watt)÷Area(m2)."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "For large DC machines, the yoke is usually made of which material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cast steel",
            "b) Cast iron",
            "c) Iron",
            "d) Cast steel or cast iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The frequency is defined as the number of oscillations per second. It is reciprocal of the time period. It is expressed in Hz. The given signal completes half of the cycle in 70 seconds then it will complete a full cycle in 140 seconds. F = 1÷T=1÷140=.00714 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Calculate the terminal voltage of Permanent Magnet DC motor having a resistance of 2 Ω and a full load current of 5 A with 20 V back e.m.f.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 V",
            "b) 25 V",
            "c) 20 V",
            "d) 31 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Permanent Magnet DC motor is a special type of motor in which flux remains constant. The terminal voltage can be calculated using the relation Vt = Eb+IaRa = 20+5×2 = 30 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "Calculate the velocity of the wheel if the angular speed is 25 rad/s and radius is 10 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 250 m/s",
            "b) 260 m/s",
            "c) 270 m/s",
            "d) 240 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Due to purely lagging load, armature current is in opposite phase with the field magneto-motive force. Armature magneto-motive force produced due to this current will be in the opposite phase with the field flux. It will try to reduce the net magnetic field."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "Displacement is a ____________ quantity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scalar",
            "b) Vector",
            "c) Scalar and Vector",
            "d) Tensor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magneto-motive force is defined as the product of current and turns. It is mathematically expressed as F=NI."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "When a UJT is used for triggering an SCR, then the wave shape of voltage obtained from the UJT circuit will be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Square",
            "b) Pulse",
            "c) Trapezoidal",
            "d) Saw-tooth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The velocity of the wheel can be calculated using the relation V=ω×r. The velocity is the vector product of angular speed and radius. V=Ω×r = 25×10 = 250 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the frequency if the time period of the signal is 0 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) infinity",
            "b) 0.4 Hz",
            "c) 0.2 Hz",
            "d) 0.78 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Displacement is a vector quantity. It depends on the initial and final position of the body. It has both direction and magnitude. Distance is a scalar quantity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "The slope of the I-V curve is 87°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.0524 Ω",
            "b) 0.0254 Ω",
            "c) 0.0543 Ω",
            "d) 0.0648 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: UJT relaxation oscillator using RC circuit is used for SCR triggering and the wave shape obtained is an exponentially decaying pulse. So, we can say pulse waveform is obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "The most suitable device for high-frequency inversion in switching mode power supply is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) GTO",
            "b) BJT",
            "c) MOSFET",
            "d) IGBT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The frequency is defined as the number of oscillations per second. It is reciprocal of the time period. It is expressed in Hz. F = 1÷0 = infinity. It signifies signal is aperiodic."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "In DC chopper, the waveform for input and output voltages is respectively __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Discontinuous and Continuous",
            "b) Continuous and Discontinuous",
            "c) Both continuous",
            "d) Both discontinuous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chopper has a perfect DC at the input which is chopped into pulses which means the output voltage is discontinuous and by varying the duty cycle we can vary the average output voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "A chopper behaves as a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) DC equivalent of AC switching device",
            "b) DC equivalent of AC transformer",
            "c) DC equivalent of AC relay",
            "d) AC equivalent of circuit breaker"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A chopper is used to step up or step down the DC voltage whereas the transformer is used to step up or step down AC voltage so chopper is DC equivalent of AC transformer."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "A DC chopper feeds an RLE load. If the value of E is increased by 20%, the current ripple ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases by 20%",
            "b) decreases by 20%",
            "c) increases only 20%",
            "d) remains the same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For a buck converter current ripple doesn’t depend on the value of E. ΔIL = Vdc×D×(1-D)×T÷L. The expression is independent of the value of E."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "The conduction loss versus device current characteristic of a power MOSFET is best approximated by a ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Straight line",
            "b) Rectangular hyperbola",
            "c) Parabola",
            "d) Exponential decaying functions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A MOSFET in ON state behaves as resistance so the conduction power loss is given by, P=I2R. Hence, the power vs current curve will be a parabola."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Which of the following device is NOT suitable for parallel operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MOSFET",
            "b) BJT",
            "c) IGBT",
            "d) TRIAC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: BJT has a negative temperature coefficient of resistance. If it is operated in parallel operation thermal run-away will take place and the device will damage."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Which of the following device should be used as a switch in a low power switched mode power supply (SMPS)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GTO",
            "b) BJT",
            "c) MOSFET",
            "d) TRIAC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SCR is uni-directional in nature. It only allows current to flow from anode to cathode. If the current is greater than the latching current then only it will work in forwarding conduction mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 78°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.732 Ω",
            "b) 4.608 Ω",
            "c) 4.543 Ω",
            "d) 4.648 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: MOSFET has a low power rating and high-frequency rating and so it can be used in low power switch mode power supply. MOSFET stands for metal oxide silicon field effect transistor."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "Calculate mark to space ratio if the system is on for 17 sec and time period is 30 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.307",
            "b) 1.457",
            "c) 1.478",
            "d) 1.146"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 78° so R=tan(78°)=4.732 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "Turn-on and turn-off times of transistor depend on _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Static Characteristic",
            "b) Junction Capacitance",
            "c) Current Gain",
            "d) Voltage Gain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The depletion layer capacitance and diffusion capacitance affects the turn-on and turn-off behavior of transistors. Due to these internal capacitances, transistors do not turn on instantly."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "The generated e.m.f from 45-pole armature having 400 turns driven at 70 rev/sec having flux per pole as 90 mWb, with 17 parallel paths is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 13341.17 V",
            "b) 12370.14 V",
            "c) 14700.89 V",
            "d) 15690.54 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The generated e.m.f can be calculated using the formula Eb = Φ×Z×N×P÷60×A, Φ represent flux per pole, Z represents the total number of conductors, P represents the number of poles, A represents the number of parallel paths, N represents speed in rpm. One turn is equal to two conductors. Eb = .09×45×400×2×4200÷60×17 = 13341.17 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the hollow cylinder having a mass of 78 kg and radius of 49 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9.363 kgm2",
            "b) 9.265 kgm2",
            "c) 9.787 kgm2",
            "d) 9.568 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Magnetic Flux density is defined as the number of magnetic lines passing through a certain point or a surface. It is generally expressed in terms of Tesla. Its C.G.S unit is Gauss."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the angular acceleration of the motor using the given data: J = 81 kg-m2, load torque = 74 N-m, motor torque = 89 N-m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .195 rad/s2",
            "b) .182 rad/s2",
            "c) .183 rad/s2",
            "d) .185 rad/s2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the hollow cylinder can be calculated using the formula I=miri2÷2. The mass of the hollow cylinder and radius is given. I=(78)×.5×(.49)2=9.363 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "340 V, 45 A, 1400 rpm DC separately excited motor having a resistance of .7 ohm excited by an external dc voltage source of 90 V. Calculate the torque developed by the motor on full load.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 94.73 N-m",
            "b) 94.52 N-m",
            "c) 93.37 N-m",
            "d) 94.42 N-m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Using the dynamic equation of motor J×(angular acceleration) = Motor torque – Load torque: 81×(angular acceleration) = 89-74=15, angular acceleration=.185 rad/s2."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the frequency if the time period of the signal is 99 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.08 Hz",
            "b) 0.02 Hz",
            "c) 0.01 Hz",
            "d) 0.04 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Back emf developed in the motor during the full load can be calculated using equation Eb = Vt-I×Ra = 308.5 V and machine constant Km = Eb÷Wm which is equal to 2.1053. Torque can be calculated by using the relation T = Km × I = 2.1053×45 = 94.73 N-m."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 31°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.600 Ω",
            "b) 0.607 Ω",
            "c) 0.543 Ω",
            "d) 0.648 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The frequency is defined as the number of oscillations per second. It is reciprocal of the time period. It is expressed in Hz. F = 1÷T=1÷99=.01 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Calculate the radius of the circular ring having a moment of inertia 59 kgm2 and mass of  69 kg.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .924 m",
            "b) .928 m",
            "c) .934 m",
            "d) .944 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 31° so R=tan(31°)=0.600 Ω. The resistance is the ratio of voltage and current."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "Calculate the power developed by a motor using the given data: Eb= 48 V and I= 86 A (Assume rotational losses are neglected.)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4128 W",
            "b) 4150 W",
            "c) 4140 W",
            "d) 4170 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the circular ring can be calculated using the formula I=∑miri2. The moment of inertia of a circular ring and mass is given. R=((59)÷(69)).5 = .924 m. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "780 V, 97 A, 1360 rpm separately excited dc motor with armature resistance (Ra) equal to 9 ohms.  Calculate back emf developed in the motor when it operates on one-fourth of the full load. (Assume rotational losses are neglected)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 564.75 V",
            "b) 561.75 V",
            "c) 562.45 V",
            "d) 565.12 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Power developed by the motor can be calculated using the formula P = Eb×I = 48×86 = 4128 W. If rotational losses are neglected, the power developed becomes equal to the shaft power of the motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Calculate the time period of the waveform y(t)=74cos(81πt+π).",
        "Options": [
            "a) .024 sec",
            "b) .027 sec",
            "c) .023 sec",
            "d) .025 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fundamental time period of the cosine wave is 2π. The time period of y(t) is 2π÷81π=.024 sec. The time period is independent of phase shifting and time shifting."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "The generated e.m.f from 42-pole armature having 74 turns driven at 64 rev/sec having flux per pole as 21 mWb, with wave winding is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4177.171 V",
            "b) 4177.152 V",
            "c) 4100.189 V",
            "d) 4190.454 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The generated e.m.f can be calculated using the formula Eb = Φ×Z×N×P÷60×A, Φ represent flux per pole, Z represents the total number of conductors, P represents the number of poles, A represents the number of parallel paths, N represents speed in rpm. One turn is equal to two conductors. In wave winding the number of parallel paths is equal to two. Eb=.021×42×74×2×3840÷60×2=4177.152 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "Calculate the phase angle of the sinusoidal waveform x(t)=20sin(9πt+π÷7).",
        "Options": [
            "a) π÷9",
            "b) π÷5",
            "c) π÷7",
            "d) π÷4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sinusoidal waveform is generally expressed in the form of V=Vmsin(ωt+α) where Vm represents peak value, ω represents angular frequency, α represents a phase difference."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the solid sphere having a mass of 28 kg and diameter of 15 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01575 kgm2",
            "b) 0.01875 kgm2",
            "c) 0.01787 kgm2",
            "d) 0.01568 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the solid sphere can be calculated using the formula I=2×miri2÷5. The mass of the solid sphere and diameter is given. I =(28)×.4×(.0375)2=.01575 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "R.M.S value of the trapezoidal waveform V=Vmsin(Ωt+α).",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vm÷2½",
            "b) Vm÷2¼",
            "c) Vm÷2¾",
            "d) Vm÷3½"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: R.M.S value of the sinusoidal waveform is Vm÷2½ and r.m.s value of the trapezoidal waveform is Vm÷3½. The peak value of the sinusoidal waveform is Vm."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "What is the unit of the admittance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ohm",
            "b) ohm-1",
            "c) ohm2",
            "d) ohm.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The admittance measures how easily current can flow in the circuit. It is the ratio of current and voltage. It is given in ohm-1. It is reciprocal of impedance."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the frequency if the inductive reactance is 45 Ω and the value of the inductor is 15 H.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.477 Hz",
            "b) 0.544 Hz",
            "c) 0.465 Hz",
            "d) 0.412 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The frequency is defined as the number of oscillations per second. The frequency can be calculated using the relation XL = 2×3.14×f×L. F = XL÷2×3.14×L = 45÷2×3.14×15 = .477 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 19°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .3254 Ω",
            "b) .3608 Ω",
            "c) .3543 Ω",
            "d) .3443 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 19° so R=tan(19°)=.3443 Ω. The slope of the V-I curve is resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 41 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 W",
            "b) 1 W",
            "c) 0 W",
            "d) .5 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90 = 0 W. Voltage leads the current in case of the inductor."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 19 F capacitor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7.8 W",
            "b) 0 W",
            "c) 5.4 W",
            "d) 1.5 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The capacitor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the capacitor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90 = 0 W. Current leads the voltage in case of the capacitor."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 241 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 21 W",
            "b) 11 W",
            "c) 0 W",
            "d) .51 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90o in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90 = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 5 Ω resistor with 5 A current flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 125 W",
            "b) 110 W",
            "c) 115 W",
            "d) 126 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P=I2R=5×5×5=125 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "Calculate the frequency of the waveform x(t)=45sin(40πt+5π).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24 Hz",
            "b) 27 Hz",
            "c) 23 Hz",
            "d) 20 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The fundamental time period of the sine wave is 2π. The frequency of x(t) is 40π÷2π=20 Hz. The frequency is independent of phase shifting and time shifting."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "The generated e.m.f from 16-pole armature having 57 turns driven at 78 rev/sec having flux per pole as 5 mWb, with lap winding is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 44.16 V",
            "b) 44.15 V",
            "c) 44.46 V",
            "d) 44.49 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The generated e.m.f can be calculated using the formula Eb = Φ×Z×N×P÷60×A, Φ represent flux per pole, Z represents the total number of conductors, P represents the number of poles, A represents the number of parallel paths, N represents speed in rpm. One turn is equal to two conductors. In lap winding, the number of parallel paths is equal to a number of poles. Eb = .005×16×57×2×4680÷60×16=44.46 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "Calculate the phase angle of the sinusoidal waveform x(t)=42sin(4700πt+2π÷3).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2π÷9",
            "b) 2π÷5",
            "c) 2π÷7",
            "d) 2π÷3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sinusoidal waveform is generally expressed in the form of V=Vmsin(ωt+α) where Vm represents peak value, ω represents angular frequency, α represents a phase difference."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the rod about its end having a mass of 39 kg and length of 88 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9.91 kgm2",
            "b) 9.92 kgm2",
            "c) 9.96 kgm2",
            "d) 9.97 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the rod about its end can be calculated using the formula I=ML2÷3. The mass of the rod about its end and length is given. I=(39)×.33×(.88)2=9.96 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the rod about its center having a mass of 11 kg and length of 29 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .091 kgm2",
            "b) .072 kgm2",
            "c) .076 kgm2",
            "d) .077 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the rod about its center can be calculated using the formula I=ML2÷12. The mass of the rod about its center and length is given. I=(11)×.0833×(.29)2=.077 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Calculate the shaft power developed by a motor using the given data: Eb = 404V and I = 25 A. Assume frictional losses are 444 W and windage losses are 777 W.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8879 W",
            "b) 2177 W",
            "c) 8911 W",
            "d) 8897 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shaft power developed by the motor can be calculated using the formula P = Eb*I-(rotational losses) = 404*25- (444+777) = 8879 W. If rotational losses are neglected, the power developed becomes equal to the shaft power of the motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the frequency if the capacitive reactance is 13 Ω and the value of the capacitor is 71 F.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .0001725 Hz",
            "b) .0001825 Hz",
            "c) .0001975 Hz",
            "d) .0001679 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The frequency is defined as the number of oscillations per second. The frequency can be calculated using the relation Xc=1÷2×3.14×f×C. F=1÷Xc×2×3.14×C = 1÷13×2×3.14×71 = .0001725 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 27°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .384 Ω",
            "b) .509 Ω",
            "c) .354 Ω",
            "d) .343 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 27° so R=tan(27°)=.509 ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 7481 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1562 W",
            "b) 4651 W",
            "c) 0 W",
            "d) 4654 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P=VIcos90 = 0 W. Voltage leads the current in case of the inductor."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 457 F capacitor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 715 W",
            "b) 565 W",
            "c) 545 W",
            "d) 0 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The capacitor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the capacitor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90 = 0 W. Current leads the voltage in case of the capacitor."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 181 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2448 W",
            "b) 1789 W",
            "c) 4879 W",
            "d) 0 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90 = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 17 ω resistor with 18 A current flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5508 W",
            "b) 5104 W",
            "c) 5554 W",
            "d) 5558 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 0°. P=I2R=18×18×17=5508 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "A three-phase slip ring induction motor is fed from the rotor side with the stator winding short-circuited. The frequency of the current flowing in the short-circuited stator is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slip frequency",
            "b) Supply frequency",
            "c) The frequency corresponding to rotor speed",
            "d) Zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The relative speed between rotor magnetic field and stator conductors is sip speed and hence the frequency of induced e.m.f is equal to slip frequency."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "An 8-pole, 3-phase, 50 Hz induction motor is operating at a speed of 720 rpm. The frequency of the rotor current of the motor in Hz is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Given a number of poles = 8. Supply frequency is 50 Hz. Rotor speed is 720 rpm. Ns = 120×f÷P=120×50÷8 = 750 rpm. S=Ns-Nr÷Ns = 750 – 720÷750 = .04. F2=sf=.04×50=2 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Calculate the phase angle of the sinusoidal waveform z(t)=78sin(456πt+2π÷78).",
        "Options": [
            "a) π÷39",
            "b) 2π÷5",
            "c) π÷74",
            "d) 2π÷4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sinusoidal waveform is generally expressed in the form of V=Vmsin(ωt+α) where Vm represents peak value, ω represents angular frequency, α represents a phase difference."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the disc having a mass of 54 kg and diameter of 91 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.512 kgm2",
            "b) 5.589 kgm2",
            "c) 5.487 kgm2",
            "d) 5.018 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the disc can be calculated using the formula I=mr2×.5. The mass of the disc and diameter is given. I=(54)×.5×(.455)2=5.589 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the thin spherical shell having a mass of 73 kg and diameter of 36 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.56 kgm2",
            "b) 1.47 kgm2",
            "c) 1.38 kgm2",
            "d) 1.48 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the thin spherical shell can be calculated using the formula I=mr2×.66. The mass of the thin spherical shell and diameter is given. I=(73)×.66×(.18)2=1.56 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "A 50 Hz, 4poles, a single phase induction motor is rotating in the clockwise direction at a speed of 1425 rpm. The slip of motor in the direction of rotation & opposite direction of the motor will be respectively.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.05, 0.95",
            "b) 0.04, 1.96",
            "c) 0.05, 1.95",
            "d) 0.05, 0.02"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Synchronous speed, Ns=120×50÷4=1500 rpm. Given a number of poles = 4. Supply frequency is 50 Hz. Rotor speed is 1425 rpm. S=Ns-Nr÷Ns=1500-1425÷1500=.05. Sb=2-s=1.95."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "The frame of an induction motor is made of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminum",
            "b) Silicon steel",
            "c) Cast iron",
            "d) Stainless steel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The frame of an induction motor is made of cast iron. The power factor of an induction motor depends upon the air gap between stator and rotor."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 5°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .3254 Ω",
            "b) .3608 Ω",
            "c) .3543 Ω",
            "d) .3443 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 5° so R=tan(5°)=.3443 ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "In an induction motor, when the number of stator slots is equal to an integral number of rotor slots _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) There may be a discontinuity in torque slip characteristics",
            "b) A high starting torque will be available",
            "c) The maximum torque will be high",
            "d) The machine may fail to start"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the number of stator slots is an integral multiple of a number of rotor slots the machine fails to start and this phenomenon is called cogging."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "A 3-phase induction motor runs at almost 1000 rpm at no load and 950 rpm at full load when supplied with power from a 50 Hz, 3-phase supply. What is the corresponding speed of the rotor field with respect to the rotor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 revolution per minute",
            "b) 40 revolution per minute",
            "c) 60 revolution per minute",
            "d) 50 revolution per minute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Supply frequency=50 Hz. No-load speed of motor = 1000 rpm. The full load speed of motor=950 rpm. Since the no-load speed of the motor is almost 1000 rpm, hence synchronous speed near to 1000 rpm. Speed of rotor field=1000 rpm. Speed of rotor field with respect to rotor = 1000-950 = 50 rpm."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 487 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2482 W",
            "b) 1545 W",
            "c) 4565 W",
            "d) 0 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90 = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 788 ω resistor with 178 A current flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24.96 MW",
            "b) 24.44 MW",
            "c) 24.12 MW",
            "d) 26.18 MW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P=I2R=178×178×788=24.96 MW."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "The direct axis is taken along ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inter-polar axis",
            "b) Rotor pole axis",
            "c) In between inter polar and rotor axis",
            "d) Parallel to interpolar axis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The direct axis is oriented along the rotor pole axis and the quadrature axis is 90° electrical to rotor pole axis. The direct axis is not oriented along the inter-polar axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "A 4-pole, 3-phase, 60 Hz induction motor is operating at a speed of 1500 rpm. The frequency of the rotor current of the motor in Hz is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Given a number of poles = 4. Supply frequency is 60 Hz. Rotor speed is 1500 rpm. Ns = 120×f÷P = 120×60÷4 = 1800 rpm. S=Ns-Nr÷Ns = 1800-1500÷1800 = .166. F2=sf=.166×60=4 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "Calculate the phase angle of the sinusoidal waveform z(t)=8cos(45t+2π÷15).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2π÷39",
            "b) 2π÷15",
            "c) π÷4",
            "d) 2π÷44"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sinusoidal waveform is generally expressed in the form of V=Vmsin(ωt+α) where Vm represents peak value, ω represents angular frequency, α represents a phase difference."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "The leakage flux paths are ________ on the angular position of the rotor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dependent",
            "b) Proportional",
            "c) Independent",
            "d) Dependent and independent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Leakage flux and leakage reactance are constant irrespective of rotor angular position. Armature reaction though is dependent on the angular position of the rotor in salient pole machine but in cylindrical rotor machine, both the quantities are independent of rotor position."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "The hunting phenomenon in a synchronous motor is also referred to as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surging",
            "b) Phase swinging",
            "c) Cogging",
            "d) Surging and phase swinging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: During hunting, power oscillates so power surges are observed and hence it can be called as surging. Also, the rotor phase angle oscillates and it is called as phase swinging."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Which of the following are used in preventing the hunting phenomenon in synchronous generators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Damper bars",
            "b) Short pitch chords",
            "c) Distributed winding",
            "d) Damper bars and short pitch chords"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Damper bars try to maintain synchronism between the rotating magnetic field and the rotor so they help in preventing hunting. It produces surges in the machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "In a synchronous machine, the phase sequence can be reversed by reversing the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rotor direction",
            "b) Field polarities",
            "c) Armature terminal",
            "d) Rotor direction and armature terminal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In synchronous generator, the phase sequence is governed by the direction of rotation of the rotor and in a synchronous motor, the phase sequence governs the direction of rotation of the rotor."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 7°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .122 Ω",
            "b) .360 Ω",
            "c) .377 Ω",
            "d) .578 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 7° so R=tan(7°)=.122 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "In an induction motor, when the number of stator slots is not equal to an integral number of rotor slots _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) There may be a discontinuity in torque slip characteristics",
            "b) A high starting torque will be available",
            "c) The machine performs better",
            "d) The machine may fail to start"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the number of stator slots is not an integral multiple of a number of rotor slots the machine will not fail to start. It does not cause the cogging phenomenon."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "A 3-phase induction motor runs at almost 1500 rpm at no load and 900 rpm at full load when supplied with power from a 50 Hz, 3-phase supply. What is the corresponding speed of the rotor field with respect to the rotor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300 revolution per minute",
            "b) 400 revolution per minute",
            "c) 600 revolution per minute",
            "d) 500 revolution per minute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Supply frequency=50 Hz. No-load speed of motor = 1500 rpm. The full load speed of motor=900 rpm. Since the no-load speed of the motor is almost 1500 rpm, hence synchronous speed near to 1500 rpm. Speed of rotor field=1500 rpm. Speed of rotor field with respect to rotor = 1500-900 = 600 rpm."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "For a practical synchronous motor, the pull-out torque will occur when the torque angle is nearly equal to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0°",
            "b) 30°",
            "c) 45°",
            "d) 75°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a practical synchronous motor, the armature resistance cannot be neglected and hence the pull-out occurs at delta=beta which is the impedance angle and is practically 75°."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in an 8 Ω resistor with 8 A current flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 512 W",
            "b) 514 W",
            "c) 512 W",
            "d) 518 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = I2R = 8×8×8 = 512 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "The ferrite  cores are used for ____________ transformers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small transformers",
            "b) Medium transformers",
            "c) Large transformers",
            "d) Medium and small transformers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ferrite cores are used for cores of small transformers used in communication circuits at high frequencies and low energy levels. Because ferrites have high resistivity they will have lower eddy current losses."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "A 2-pole, 3-phase, 50 Hz induction motor is operating at a speed of 400 rpm. The frequency of the rotor current of the motor in Hz is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 43.33",
            "b) 42.54",
            "c) 43.11",
            "d) 41.47"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Given a number of poles = 2. Supply frequency is 50 Hz. Rotor speed is 400 rpm. Ns = 120×f÷P=120×50÷2 = 3000 rpm. S=Ns-Nr÷Ns = 3000-400÷3000 = .8666. F2=sf=.8666×50=43.33 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "Calculate the phase angle of the sinusoidal waveform w(t)=.45sin(87πt+8π÷787).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2π÷39",
            "b) 8π÷787",
            "c) 5π÷74",
            "d) 42π÷4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sinusoidal waveform is generally expressed in the form of V=Vmsin(ωt+α) where Vm represents peak value, ω represents angular frequency, α represents a phase difference."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the disc having a mass of 1 kg and radius of 1 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 kgm2",
            "b) .5 kgm2",
            "c) 2 kgm2",
            "d) 3 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the disc can be calculated using the formula I=mr2×.5. The mass of the disc and diameter is given. I=(1)×.5×(1)2=.5 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the thin spherical shell having a mass of 3 kg and diameter of 6 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .0178 kgm2",
            "b) .0147 kgm2",
            "c) .0398 kgm2",
            "d) .0144 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the thin spherical shell can be calculated using the formula I=mr2×.66. The mass of the thin spherical shell and diameter is given. I=(3)×.66×(.03)2=.0178 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "The power factor of a synchronous motor __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improves with an increase in excitation and may even become leading at high excitations",
            "b) Decreases with increase in excitation",
            "c) Is independent of its excitation",
            "d) Increase with loading for a given excitation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From inverted V-curve we can see when the power factor is leading power factor decreases when the excitation increases and it is over-excited conditions and when power factor is lagging if the motor power factor is increasing if excitation increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "The frame of a synchronous motor is made of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminum",
            "b) Silicon steel",
            "c) Cast iron",
            "d) Stainless steel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The frame of a synchronous motor is made of cast iron. The power factor of a synchronous motor depends upon maximum power transfer capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 45°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 Ω",
            "b) 3 Ω",
            "c) 4 Ω",
            "d) 1 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 45° so R=tan(45°)=1 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Which one of the following methods would give a higher than the actual value of regulation of the alternator.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ZPF method",
            "b) MMF method",
            "c) EMF method",
            "d) ASA method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: EMF method is a pessimistic method of voltage regulation as it gives higher than the actual value of voltage regulation. EMF method will the values that are greater than the actual value."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "A 3-phase induction motor runs at almost 1100 rpm at no load and 640 rpm at full load when supplied with power from a 50 Hz, 3-phase supply. What is the corresponding speed of the rotor field with respect to the rotor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 430 revolution per minute",
            "b) 440 revolution per minute",
            "c) 460 revolution per minute",
            "d) 450 revolution per minute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Supply frequency=50 Hz. No-load speed of motor = 1100 rpm. The full load speed of motor=640 rpm. Since the no-load speed of the motor is almost 1100 rpm, hence synchronous speed near to 1100 rpm. Speed of rotor field=1100 rpm. Speed of rotor field with respect to rotor = 1100-640 = 460 rpm."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "Which of the following core has linear characteristics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air core",
            "b) Steel core",
            "c) CRGO core",
            "d) Iron core"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Air core coils have linear magnetization characteristics that are they do not saturate. Open circuit characteristics graph is linear in case of synchronous machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 1 Ω resistor with 2 A current flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 W",
            "b) 4 W",
            "c) 7 W",
            "d) 1 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = I2R = 2×2×1=4 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 13°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .2544 Ω",
            "b) .7771 Ω",
            "c) .2308 Ω",
            "d) .5788 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 13° so R=tan(13°)=.2308 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "A 2-pole lap wound generator with 44 armature conductors and a flux per pole of .07 Wb has an armature current of 80 A. The developed torque is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 39.7 N-m",
            "b) 39.2 N-m",
            "c) 38.4 N-m",
            "d) 37.2 N-m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The developed torque in the motor is Km×I. The value of machine constant(Km) is Eb÷ωm = Φ×Z×P÷2×3.14×A = .07×44×2÷2×3.14×2 = .49 Vs/rad. The developed torque is .49×80 = 39.2 N-m."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a .45 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.11 W",
            "b) 0.14 W",
            "c) 0.15 W",
            "d) 0 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P=VIcos90° = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "A 10-pole, 3-phase, 60 Hz induction motor is operating at a speed of 100 rpm. The frequency of the rotor current of the motor in Hz is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 52.4",
            "b) 54.8",
            "c) 51.66",
            "d) 51.77"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given a number of poles = 10. Supply frequency is 60 Hz. Rotor speed is 100 rpm. Ns = 120×f÷P=120×60÷10 = 720 rpm. S=Ns-Nr÷Ns = 720-100÷720=.86. F2=sf=.86×60=51.66 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "Calculate the phase angle of the sinusoidal waveform z(t)=.99sin(4578πt+78π÷78).",
        "Options": [
            "a) π÷3",
            "b) 2π",
            "c) π÷7",
            "d) π"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sinusoidal waveform is generally expressed in the form of V=Vmsin(ωt+α) where Vm represents peak value, Ω represents angular frequency, α represents a phase difference."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the disc having a mass of 4 kg and diameter of 1458 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 106.288 kgm2",
            "b) 104.589 kgm2",
            "c) 105.487 kgm2",
            "d) 107.018 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the disc can be calculated using the formula I=mr2×.5. The mass of the disc and diameter is given. I=(4)×.5×(7.29)2=106.288 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the thin spherical shell having a mass of 703 kg and diameter of 376 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1639.89 kgm2",
            "b) 1628.47 kgm2",
            "c) 1678.12 kgm2",
            "d) 1978.19 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the thin spherical shell can be calculated using the formula I=mr2×.66. The mass of the thin spherical shell and diameter is given. I=(703)×.66×(1.88)2=1639.89 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the torque when 89 N force is applied perpendicular to a 78 m length of stick fixed at the center.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6942 N-m",
            "b) 3000 N-m",
            "c) 1000 N-m",
            "d) 4470 N-m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Torque can be calculated using the relation T = (length of stick) × (Force applied) = r×F×sin90. F is given as 89 N and r is 78 m then torque is 89×78 = 6942 N-m. (the angle between F and r is 90 degrees)."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "100 V, 2 A, 90 rpm separately excited dc motor with armature resistance (Ra) equal to 8 ohms.  Calculate back emf developed in the motor when it operates on 3th/4 of the full load. (Assume rotational losses are neglected)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 V",
            "b) 87 V",
            "c) 88 V",
            "d) 90 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Back emf developed in the motor can be calculated using the relation Eb = Vt-I×Ra. In question, it is asking for 3th/4  load, but the data is given for full load so current becomes 3th/4  of the full load current = 2÷1.33 = 1.5 A. 100 V is terminal voltage it is fixed so Eb = 100-1.5×8 = 88 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 16.8°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .324 Ω",
            "b) .301 Ω",
            "c) .343 Ω",
            "d) .398 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 16.8° so R=tan(16.8°)=.301 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the torque when 1 N force is applied perpendicular to a 1 m length of chain fixed at the center.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 N-m",
            "b) 3 N-m",
            "c) 2 N-m",
            "d) 4 N-m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Torque can be calculated using the relation T = (length of chain) × (Force applied) = r×F×sin90. F is given as 1 N and r is 1 m then torque is 1×1 = 6942 N-m. (the angle between F and r is 90 degrees)."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "A 3-phase induction motor runs at almost 140 rpm at no load and 50 rpm at full load when supplied with power from a 50 Hz, 3-phase supply. What is the corresponding speed of the rotor field with respect to the rotor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 revolution per minute",
            "b) 80 revolution per minute",
            "c) 90 revolution per minute",
            "d) 70 revolution per minute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Supply frequency=50 Hz. No-load speed of motor= 140 rpm. The full load speed of motor=50 rpm. Since the no-load speed of the motor is almost 140 rpm, hence synchronous speed near to 140 rpm. Speed of rotor field=140 rpm. Speed of rotor field with respect to rotor = 140-50 = 90 rpm."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a .7889 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .123 W",
            "b) .155 W",
            "c) 0 W",
            "d) .487 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90° = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a .8 Ω resistor with 2 A current flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.4 W",
            "b) 3.4 W",
            "c) 2.2 W",
            "d) 3.2 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P=I2R=2×2×.8=3.2 MW."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a .56 F capacitor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 37.8 W",
            "b) 0 W",
            "c) 15.4 W",
            "d) 124.5 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Angular frequency is defined as the rate of change of angular displacement with respect to time. Angular displacement is generally expressed in terms of a radian. The unit of angular frequency is Hz. ω=2×3.14×f."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the angular acceleration of the motor using the given data: J = .01 kg-m2, load torque= 790 N-m, motor torque= 169 N-m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) -62100 rad/s2",
            "b) -62456 rad/s2",
            "c) -34056 rad/s2",
            "d) -44780 rad/s2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Using the dynamic equation of motor J*(angular acceleration) = Motor torque – Load torque: .01*(angular acceleration) = 169-790=-621, angular acceleration=-62100 rad/s2.The motor will decelerate and will fail to start."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "A 14-pole, 3-phase, 50 Hz induction motor is operating at a speed of 99 rpm. The frequency of the rotor current of the motor in Hz is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 39.5",
            "b) 40",
            "c) 38.45",
            "d) 39.9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given a number of poles = 14. Supply frequency is 50 Hz. Rotor speed is 699 rpm. Ns=120×f÷P=120×50÷14 = 428.57 rpm. S=Ns-Nr÷Ns=428.57-99÷428.57=.769. F2=sf=.769×50=38.45 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Calculate the phase angle of the sinusoidal waveform z(t)=18cos(1546πt+1900π÷76).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25π÷39",
            "b) 25π÷5",
            "c) 25π÷1",
            "d) π÷4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sinusoidal waveform is generally expressed in the form of V=Vmsin(ωt+α) where Vm represents peak value, Ω represents angular frequency, α represents a phase difference."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Calculate the mass of the solid sphere having a moment of inertia 17 kgm2 and radius of 4 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10624 kg",
            "b) 10625 kg",
            "c) 10628 kg",
            "d) 10626 kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the ball can be calculated using the formula I=Σmiri2. The moment of inertia of ball and radius is given. M=(17)÷(.04)2 = 10625 kg. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the thin spherical shell having a mass of 3 kg and diameter of 66 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .2156 kgm2",
            "b) .2147 kgm2",
            "c) .2138 kgm2",
            "d) .2148 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the thin spherical shell can be calculated using the formula I=mr2×.66. The mass of the thin spherical shell and diameter is given. I=(3)×.66×(.33)2=.2156 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the time period if the frequency of the signal is 1 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 sec",
            "b) 2 sec",
            "c) .5 sec",
            "d) 1.5 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The time period is defined as the time after the signal repeats itself. It is expressed in second. T = 1÷F=1÷1=1 sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 270°. Calculate the value of resistance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 112 Ω",
            "b) 178 Ω",
            "c) infinite Ω",
            "d) 187 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 270° so R=tan(270°)=infinite Ω. It behaves as an open-circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 23.56°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .464 Ω",
            "b) .436 Ω",
            "c) .443 Ω",
            "d) .463 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 23.56° so R=tan(23.56°)=.436 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "Calculate the reactive power in a 23 Ω resistor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45 VAR",
            "b) 10 VAR",
            "c) 245 VAR",
            "d) 0 VAR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 90°. Q = VIsin0° = 0 VAR."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "A 3-phase induction motor runs at almost 50 rpm at no load and 25 rpm at full load when supplied with power from a 50 Hz, 3-phase supply. What is the corresponding speed of the rotor field with respect to the rotor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25 revolution per minute",
            "b) 20 revolution per minute",
            "c) 10 revolution per minute",
            "d) 30 revolution per minute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Supply frequency=50 Hz. No-load speed of motor= 50 rpm. The full load speed of motor=25 rpm. Since the no-load speed of the motor is almost 50 rpm, hence synchronous speed near to 50 rpm. Speed of rotor field=50 rpm. Speed of rotor field with respect to rotor = 50-25 = 25 rpm."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the frequency of the 220 V DC supply.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 Hz",
            "b) 0 Hz",
            "c) 20 Hz",
            "d) 90 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The frequency is defined as the number of oscillations per second. It is reciprocal of the time period. DC supply magnitude is constant. It does not change with time so the frequency of DC supply is 0 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the duty cycle if the system is on for 48 sec and off for 1 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .979",
            "b) .444",
            "c) .145",
            "d) .578"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Duty cycle is Ton÷Ttotal. It is the ratio of time for which the system is active and the time taken by the signal to complete one cycle. D = Ton÷Ttotal = 48÷49 = .979."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the frequency if the signal completes half of the cycle in 30 sec. Assume signal is periodic.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.028 Hz",
            "b) 0.016 Hz",
            "c) 0.054 Hz",
            "d) 0.045 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The frequency is defined as the number of oscillations per second. It is reciprocal of the time period. It is expressed in Hz. The given signal completes half of the cycle in 30 seconds then it will complete a full cycle in 60 seconds. F = 1÷T = 1÷60 = .016 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Calculate the velocity of the disc if the angular speed is 5 rad/s and radius is 2 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25 m/s",
            "b) 20 m/s",
            "c) 25 m/s",
            "d) 10 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The velocity of the disc can be calculated using the relation V=ω×r. The velocity is the vector product of angular speed and radius. V = ω×r = 5×2 = 10 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "440 V, 77 A, 700 rpm DC separately excited motor having a resistance of 0.11 ohms excited by an external dc voltage source of 24 V. Calculate the torque developed by the motor on full load.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 453.51 N-m",
            "b) 451.24 N-m",
            "c) 440.45 N-m",
            "d) 452.64 N-m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Back emf developed in the motor during the full load can be calculated using equation Eb = Vt-I×Ra = 431.53  V and machine constant Km = Eb÷Wm which is equal to 5.88. Torque can be calculated by using the relation T = Km × I = 5.88×77 = 453.51 N-m."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "Calculate the power developed by a motor using the given data: Eb = 55 V and I = 6 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 440 W",
            "b) 220 W",
            "c) 330 W",
            "d) 550 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Power developed by the motor can be calculated using the formula P = Eb×I = 55×6 = 330 W. If rotational losses are neglected, the power developed becomes equal to the shaft power of the motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the angular acceleration of the motor using the given data: J = 36 kg-m2, load torque = 66 N-m, motor torque = 26 N-m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.11 rad/s2",
            "b) 2.22 rad/s2",
            "c) 3.33 rad/s2",
            "d) 4.44 rad/s2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Using the dynamic equation of motor J×(angular acceleration) = Motor torque – Load torque: 36×(angular acceleration) = 66-26 = 40, angular acceleration = 1.11 rad/s2."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the apple having a mass of .4 kg and diameter of 12 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .0008 kgm2",
            "b) .0007 kgm2",
            "c) .0009 kgm2",
            "d) .0001 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the apple can be calculated using the formula I=mr2×.5. The mass of the apple and diameter is given. I=(.4)×.5×(.06)2 = .0007 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the thin spherical shell having a mass of 3.3 kg and diameter of .6 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .00125 kgm2",
            "b) .00196 kgm2",
            "c) .00145 kgm2",
            "d) .00178 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the thin spherical shell can be calculated using the formula I=mr2×.66. The mass of the thin spherical shell and diameter is given. I=(3.3)×.66×(.03)2=.00196 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Calculate the time period of the waveform y(t)=7cos(54πt+2π÷4).",
        "Options": [
            "a) .055 sec",
            "b) .037 sec",
            "c) .023 sec",
            "d) .017 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The fundamental time period of the cosine wave is 2π. The time period of y(t) is 2π÷54π=.037 sec. The time period is independent of phase shifting and time shifting."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "Calculate the useful power developed by a motor using the given data: Pin= 1500 W, Ia= 6 A, Ra=.2 Ω. Assume frictional losses are 50 W and windage losses are 25 W.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1400 W",
            "b) 1660.5 W",
            "c) 1417.8 W",
            "d) 1416.7 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Useful power is basically the shaft power developed by the motor that can be calculated using the formula Psh = Pdev-(rotational losses). Pdev = Pin-Ia2Ra = 1500-62(.2)=1492.8 W. The useful power developed by the motor is Psh = Pdev-(rotational losses) = 1492.8 –(50+25) = 1417.8 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 15.5°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .277 Ω",
            "b) .488 Ω",
            "c) .443 Ω",
            "d) .457 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 15.5° so R=tan(15.5°)=.277 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "The generated e.m.f from 2-pole armature having 2 conductors driven at 3000 rpm having flux per pole as 4000 mWb, with 91 parallel paths is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8.64 V",
            "b) 8.56 V",
            "c) 8.12 V",
            "d) 8.79 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The generated e.m.f can be calculated using the formula Eb = Φ×Z×N×P÷60×A, Φ represent flux per pole, Z represents the total number of conductors, P represents the number of poles, A represents the number of parallel paths, N represents speed in rpm. Eb = 4×2×3000×2÷60×91 = 8.79 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "A 3-phase induction motor runs at almost 888 rpm at no load and 500 rpm at full load when supplied with power from a 50 Hz, 3-phase supply. What is the corresponding speed of the rotor field with respect to the rotor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 388 revolution per minute",
            "b) 400 revolution per minute",
            "c) 644 revolution per minute",
            "d) 534 revolution per minute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Supply frequency=50 Hz. No-load speed of motor = 888 rpm. The full load speed of motor=500 rpm. Since the no-load speed of the motor is almost 888 rpm, hence synchronous speed near to 888 rpm. Speed of rotor field=888 rpm. Speed of rotor field with respect to rotor = 888-500 = 388 rpm."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 157.1545 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4577 W",
            "b) 4567 W",
            "c) 4897 W",
            "d) 0 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90° = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 1.2 Ω resistor with 1.8 A current flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.88 W",
            "b) 3.44 W",
            "c) 3.12 W",
            "d) 2.18 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 90o. P=I2R=1.8×1.8×1.2=3.88 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "Calculate the total heat dissipated in a resistor of 12 Ω when 9.2 A current flows through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.01 KW",
            "b) 3.44 KW",
            "c) 1.01 KW",
            "d) 2.48 KW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P=I2R=9.2×9.2×12=1.01 kW."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "Calculate mark to space ratio if the system is on for 9 sec and time period is 11 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.6",
            "b) 4.8",
            "c) 4.5",
            "d) 4.9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mark to space is Ton÷Toff. It is the ratio of time for which the system is active and the time for which is inactive. M = Ton÷Toff=9÷(11-9) = 4.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Calculate the angular frequency of the waveform y(t)=69sin(40πt+4π).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40π Hz",
            "b) 60π Hz",
            "c) 70π Hz",
            "d) 20π Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fundamental time period of the sine wave is 2π. The sinusoidal waveform is generally expressed in the form of V=Vmsin(Ωt+α) where Vm represents peak value, Ω represents angular frequency, α represents a phase difference. Ω can be directly calculated by comparing the equations. Ω = 40π Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "The generated e.m.f from 22-pole armature having 75 turns driven at 78 rpm having flux per pole as 400 mWb, with lap winding is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 76 V",
            "b) 77 V",
            "c) 78 V",
            "d) 79 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The generated e.m.f can be calculated using the formula Eb = Φ×Z×N×P÷60×A, Φ represent flux per pole, Z represents the total number of conductors, P represents the number of poles, A represents the number of parallel paths, N represents speed in rpm. One turn is equal to two conductors. In lap winding, the number of parallel paths is equal to a number of poles. Eb = .4×22×75×2×78÷60×22 = 78 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "Calculate the phase angle of the sinusoidal waveform u(t)=154sin(9.85πt-π÷89).",
        "Options": [
            "a) -78π÷9",
            "b) -12π÷5",
            "c) -π÷89",
            "d) -2π÷888"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sinusoidal waveform is generally expressed in the form of V=Vmsin(Ωt+α) where Vm represents peak value, Ω represents angular frequency, α represents a phase difference."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the stick about its end having a mass of 22 kg and length of 22 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .088 kgm2",
            "b) .087 kgm2",
            "c) .089 kgm2",
            "d) .086 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the stick about its end can be calculated using the formula I=ML2÷3. The mass of the stick about its end and length is given. I = (22)×.33×(.11)2 =.087 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the stick about its center having a mass of 1.1 kg and length of 2.9 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .66 kgm2",
            "b) .77 kgm2",
            "c) .88 kgm2",
            "d) .47 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the stick about its center can be calculated using the formula I=ML2÷12. The mass of the stick about its center and length is given. I=(1.1)×.0833×(2.9)2=.77 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "Calculate the useful power developed by a motor using the given data: Eb = 4V and I = 52 A. Assume frictional losses are 3 W and windage losses are 2 W.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 203 W",
            "b) 247 W",
            "c) 211 W",
            "d) 202 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Useful power developed by the motor can be calculated using the formula P = Eb*I -(rotational losses) = 4*52 – (5) = 203 W. If rotational losses are neglected, the power developed becomes equal to the shaft power of the motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the frequency if the capacitive reactance is .1 Ω and the value of the capacitor is .02 F.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 71.25 Hz",
            "b) 81.75 Hz",
            "c) 79.61 Hz",
            "d) 79.54 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The frequency is defined as the number of oscillations per second. The frequency can be calculated using the relation Xc = 1÷2×3.14×f×C. F = 1÷Xc×2×3.14×C = 1÷.1×2×3.14×.02 = 79.61 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 6.9°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .38 Ω",
            "b) .59 Ω",
            "c) .34 Ω",
            "d) .12 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 6.9° so R=tan(6.9°)=.12 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in an 8764 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8645 W",
            "b) 6485 W",
            "c) 0 W",
            "d) 4879 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90° = 0 W. Voltage leads the current in case of the inductor."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 543 F capacitor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 581 W",
            "b) 897 W",
            "c) 0 W",
            "d) 892 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The capacitor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the capacitor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P=VIcos90°= 0 W. Current leads the voltage in case of the capacitor."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 32 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 28 W",
            "b) 189 W",
            "c) 4 W",
            "d) 0 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90° = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in an 8965 Ω resistor with .23 A current flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 547.12 W",
            "b) 474.24 W",
            "c) 554.78 W",
            "d) 123.88 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 0°. P=I2R=.23×.23×8965=474.24 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Which one of the following methods would give a lower than the actual value of regulation of the alternator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ZPF method",
            "b) MMF method",
            "c) EMF method",
            "d) ASA method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MMF method is an optimistic method of voltage regulation as it gives lower than the actual value of voltage regulation. MMF method will give the values that are lesser than the actual value."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "The advantage of the double squirrel cage induction motor over a single cage rotor is that its _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Efficiency is higher",
            "b) Power factor is higher",
            "c) Slip is larger",
            "d) Starting current is lower"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The starting current flows through the outer cage which has higher resistance and hence starting current is lower. This is one the important advantage of the double squirrel cage induction motor over a single cage rotor."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "A 16-pole, 3-phase, 60 Hz induction motor is operating at a speed of 150 rpm. The frequency of the rotor current of the motor in Hz is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 40",
            "c) 30",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Given a number of poles = 16. Supply frequency is 60 Hz. Rotor speed is 150 rpm. Ns=120×f÷P=120×60÷16 = 450 rpm. S=Ns-Nr÷Ns=450-150÷450=.666. F2=sf=.666×60=40 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "Calculate the amplitude of the sinusoidal waveform z(t)=715sin(165πt+2π÷468).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 710",
            "b) 715",
            "c) 716",
            "d) 718"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sinusoidal waveform is generally expressed in the form of V=Vmsin(Ωt+α) where Vm represents peak value, Ω represents angular frequency, α represents a phase difference."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "R.M.S value of the sinusoidal waveform V=48sin(6.5πt+89π÷46.8).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 33.94 V",
            "b) 33.56 V",
            "c) 33.12 V",
            "d) 33.78 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: R.M.S value of the sinusoidal waveform is Vm÷2½ = 48÷2½ = 33.94 V and r.m.s value of the trapezoidal waveform is Vm÷3½. The peak value of the sinusoidal waveform is Vm."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "The short circuit test on a 3-φ induction motor is conducted at a rotor speed of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) < Ns",
            "c) > Ns",
            "d) Ns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Short-circuit test in an induction motor is also called a Blocked rotor test so it is conducted at zero speed. Net input power taken is equal to the variable losses."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "If induction motor air gap power is 10 KW and mechanically developed power is 8 KW, then rotor ohmic loss will be _________ KW.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rotor ohmic losses are due to the resistance of armature windings. Net input power to the rotor is equal to the sum of rotor ohmic losses and mechanically developed power. Rotor ohmic losses=Air gap power-Mechanical developed power=10-8=2 KW."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "A 3-phase induction machine draws active power P and reactive power Q from the grid. If it is operated as a generator, then P and Q will be _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Positive and Negative",
            "b) Negative and Positive",
            "c) Positive and Positive",
            "d) Negative and Negative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Induction generator will be delivering power to the bus to generate flux it will consume reactive power from the bus. Since active power is delivered the active power drawn will be negative but reactive power is absorbed and hence active power absorbed is positive."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 39.1°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .81 Ω",
            "b) .36 Ω",
            "c) .75 Ω",
            "d) .84 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 39.1° so R=tan(39.1°)=.81 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "If induction motor air gap power is 48 KW and gross developed power is 28 KW, then rotor ohmic loss will be _________ KW.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 20",
            "c) 30",
            "d) 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rotor ohmic losses are due to the resistance of armature windings. Net input power to the rotor is equal to the sum of rotor ohmic losses and mechanically developed power. Rotor ohmic losses=Air gap power-Mechanical developed power=48-28=20 KW."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "The power factor of a squirrel cage induction motor is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low at light load only",
            "b) Low at heavy loads only",
            "c) Low at the light and heavy loads both",
            "d) Low at rate load only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At light loads, the current drawn is largely a magnetizing current due to the air gap and hence the power factor is low."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a .154 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 22 W",
            "b) 14 W",
            "c) 45 W",
            "d) 0 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90° = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "Calculate the time period of the waveform z(t)=24sin(πt+π÷4)+4sin(2πt+π÷6).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 sec",
            "b) 3 sec",
            "c) 4 sec",
            "d) 1 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fundamental time period of the sine wave is 2π. The time period of z(t) is L.C.M {2,1}=2 sec. The time period is independent of phase shifting and time shifting."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "Calculate the total heat dissipated in a resistor of 50 Ω when 1.4 A current flows through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 98 W",
            "b) 92 W",
            "c) 91 W",
            "d) 93 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P=I2R=1.4×1.4×50=98 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "Calculate mark to space ratio if the system is on for 26.3 sec and off for 24.2 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.086",
            "b) 1.042",
            "c) 1.214",
            "d) 1.876"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mark to space is Ton÷Toff. It is the ratio of time for which the system is active and the time for which is inactive. M = Ton÷Toff=26.3÷24.2=1.086."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "A particular current is made up of two components: a 10 A and a sine wave of peak value 14.14 A. The average value of current is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) 24.14 A",
            "c) 10 A",
            "d) 14.14 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Average value of DC current is 10 A. Average value of AC current is 0 A as it is alternating in nature. The average value of current is 10+0 = 10 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "A 38-pole, 3-phase, 80 Hz induction motor is operating at a speed of 12 rpm. The frequency of the rotor current of the motor in Hz is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 75.2",
            "b) 76.1",
            "c) 79.2",
            "d) 79.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Given a number of poles = 8. Supply frequency is 50 Hz. Rotor speed is 720 rpm. Ns=120×f÷P=120×80÷38 = 252.63 rpm. S=Ns-Nr÷Ns = 252.63-12÷252.63 = .952. F2 = sf = .952×80 = 76.1 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "Calculate the phase angle of the sinusoidal waveform i(t)=sin(.6πt+π÷.88).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100π÷88",
            "b) 100π÷8",
            "c) 100π÷8",
            "d) π÷88"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sinusoidal waveform is generally expressed in the form of V=Vmsin(ωt+α) where Vm represents peak value, ω represents angular frequency, α represents a phase difference."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the satellite having a mass of 79 kg and diameter of 83 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 13.65 kgm2",
            "b) 13.60 kgm2",
            "c) 12.67 kgm2",
            "d) 13.82 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the satellite can be calculated using the formula I=mr2. The mass of the satellite and diameter is given. I=(79)×(.415)2=13.60 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "A particular voltage is made up of two components: a 5 A and a cosine wave of peak value 7.8 A. The average value of voltage is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) 35.14 A",
            "c) 78 A",
            "d) 5 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Average value of DC voltage is 5 A. Average value of AC current is 0 A as it is alternating in nature. The average value of current is 5+0 = 5 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 4.9°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .03 Ω",
            "b) .08 Ω",
            "c) .04 Ω",
            "d) .07 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Due to a purely capacitive load, armature current is in phase with the field magneto-motive force. Armature magneto-motive force produced due to this current will be in phase with the field flux. It will try to increase the net magnetic field."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Calculate the velocity of the satellite if the angular speed is 87 rad/s and radius is 7.4 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 643.8 m/s",
            "b) 642.4 m/s",
            "c) 641.9 m/s",
            "d) 643.2 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Due to a purely resistive load, armature current is in quadrature with the field magneto-motive force. Armature magneto-motive force produced due to this current will be in quadrature with the field flux. It will try to increase the net magnetic field."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "A 3-phase induction motor runs at almost 70 rpm at no load and 50 rpm at full load when supplied with power from a 50 Hz, 3-phase supply. What is the corresponding speed of the rotor field with respect to the rotor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 revolution per minute",
            "b) 30 revolution per minute",
            "c) 40 revolution per minute",
            "d) 50 revolution per minute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 4.9° so R=tan(4.9°)=.08 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 9.854 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.98 W",
            "b) 0 W",
            "c) 8.59 W",
            "d) 1 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The velocity of the satellite can be calculated using the relation V=Ω×r. The velocity is the vector product of angular speed and radius. V=Ω×r = 87×7.4 = 643.8 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Calculate the reactive power in a 45 Ω resistor with 1.78 A current flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 28.8 VAR",
            "b) 23.4 VAR",
            "c) 25.82 VAR",
            "d) 0 VAR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Supply frequency=50 Hz. No-load speed of motor = 70 rpm. The full load speed of motor=50 rpm. Since the no-load speed of the motor is almost 70 rpm, hence synchronous speed near to 70 rpm. Speed of rotor field=70 rpm. Speed of rotor field with respect to rotor=70-50= 20 rpm."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the frequency if the inductive reactance is 72 Ω and the value of the inductor is 7 H.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.63 Hz",
            "b) 1.54 Hz",
            "c) 1.78 Hz",
            "d) 1.32 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P=VIcos90° = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 2 Ω resistor with 8 A current flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 125 W",
            "b) 128 W",
            "c) 123 W",
            "d) 126 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 0°. Q=VIsin(0°)=0 VAR."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "In the chopper circuit, commutation times are _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Current commutation is equal to voltage commutation",
            "b) Current commutation is less as compared to that of voltage commutation",
            "c) Current commutation is more as compared to that of voltage commutation",
            "d) Both commutation techniques are not comparable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In current commutation, commutation time=CVr÷Io. In voltage commutation, commutation time= CVs÷Io. Hence, the commutation time of the current commutation is less as compared to voltage commutation."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "The generated e.m.f from 4-pole armature having 1 conductors driven at 1 rev/sec having flux per pole as 10 Wb, with wave winding is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 V",
            "b) 40 V",
            "c) 70 V",
            "d) 20 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The generated e.m.f can be calculated using the formula Eb = Φ×Z×N×P÷60×A, Φ represent flux per pole, Z represents the total number of conductors, P represents the number of poles, A represents the number of parallel paths, N represents speed in rpm. In wave winding number of parallel paths are 2. Eb = 10×4×1×60÷60×2 = 20 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the sphere having a mass of 8.4 kg and radius of 61 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.124 kgm2",
            "b) 3.125 kgm2",
            "c) 4.545 kgm2",
            "d) 5.552 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The voltage is equal to one volt when 1 A of current flows through 1 Ω resistor. It is mathematically represented as I×R. It is expressed in terms of a volt(V)."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "The most suitable control-motor application is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) AC shunt motor",
            "b) DC separately motor",
            "c) AC one-phase induction motor",
            "d) DC shunt motor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the egg can be calculated using the formula I=Σmiri2. The mass of egg and radius is given. I=(8.4)×(.61)2=3.125 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "In a DC series motor, the e.m.f developed is proportional to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) N×Ia",
            "b) N×Ia2",
            "c) N×Ia3",
            "d) N×Ia.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: DC separately motor has definite full-load speed, so they don’t ‘run away’ when the load is suddenly thrown off provided the field circuit remains closed. The speed for any load within the operating range of the motor can be readily obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the time period if the frequency of the signal is .07 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 14.28 sec",
            "b) 14.31 sec",
            "c) 14.23 sec",
            "d) 14.78 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a DC series motor, the e.m.f developed is equal to KmΦN. In a DC series, the motor field winding is connected in series with the armature so the flux in the field winding is proportional to current. Eb = KmΦN α Ia×N."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 13.89°. Calculate the value of resistance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .247 Ω",
            "b) .345 Ω",
            "c) .231 Ω",
            "d) .222 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The time period is defined as the time after the signal repeats itself. It is expressed in second. T = 1÷F=1÷.07=14.28 sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "In a DC shunt motor, the e.m.f developed is proportional to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ia",
            "b) Ia2",
            "c) Ia3",
            "d) Iao"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 13.89° so R=tan(13.89°)=.247 Ω. It behaves like a normal resistor."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "Calculate the power factor angle during the resonance condition.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0°",
            "b) 10°",
            "c) 80°",
            "d) 90°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a DC shunt motor, the e.m.f developed is equal to KmΦN. In a DC shunt, the motor field windings are connected separately and excited by a constant DC voltage. E = KmΦN α Ia°."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the duty cycle if the system is on for 5 sec and off for inf sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) .4",
            "c) .2",
            "d) .1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: During the resonance condition, the reactive power generated by the capacitor is completely absorbed by the inductor. Only active power flows in the circuit. Net reactive power is equal to zero and Φ=0°."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the frequency of the AC supply in India.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 Hz",
            "b) 50 Hz",
            "c) 49 Hz",
            "d) 60 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Duty cycle is Ton÷Ttotal. It is the ratio of time for which the system is active and the time taken by the signal to complete one cycle. D = Ton÷Ttotal=5÷inf=0."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the frequency if the time period of the signal is .2 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 Hz",
            "b) 4 Hz",
            "c) 2 Hz",
            "d) 3 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The frequency is defined as the number of oscillations per second. It is reciprocal of the time period. AC supply magnitude is variable. It changes with time so the frequency of AC supply is 50 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "40 V, 7 A, 70 rpm DC separately excited motor having a resistance of 0.3 ohms excited by an external dc voltage source of 4 V. Calculate the torque developed by the motor on half load.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18.10 N-m",
            "b) 4.24 N-m",
            "c) 40.45 N-m",
            "d) 52.64 N-m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Back emf developed in the motor during the full load can be calculated using equation Eb = Vt-I×Ra = 37.9 V and machine constant Km = Eb÷Wm which is equal to 5.17. Torque can be calculated by using the relation T = Km× I = 5.17×3.5 = 18.10 N-m."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power developed by a motor using the given data: Eb = 5.5 V and I = .5 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.75 W",
            "b) 2.20 W",
            "c) 5.30 W",
            "d) 5.50 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Power developed by the motor can be calculated using the formula P = Eb×I = 5.5×.5 = 2.75 W. If rotational losses are neglected, the power developed becomes equal to the shaft power of the motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the angular acceleration of the motor using the given data: J = .1 kg-m2, load torque = 45 N-m, motor torque = 55 N-m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 rad/s2",
            "b) 222 rad/s2",
            "c) 300 rad/s2",
            "d) 400 rad/s2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Using the dynamic equation of motor J×(angular acceleration) = Motor torque – Load torque: .1×(angular acceleration) = 55-45=10, angular acceleration = 100 rad/s2."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the tennis ball having a mass of 7 kg and diameter of 152 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.55 kgm2",
            "b) 4.47 kgm2",
            "c) 2.66 kgm2",
            "d) 1.41 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the tennis ball can be calculated using the formula I=mr2×.5. The mass of the ball and diameter is given. I=(7)×.5×(.76)2=2.66 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the thin spherical shell having a mass of 7.8 kg and diameter of 145.6 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.72 kgm2",
            "b) 5.96 kgm2",
            "c) 5.45 kgm2",
            "d) 2.78 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the thin spherical shell can be calculated using the formula I=mr2×.66. The mass of the thin spherical shell and diameter is given. I=(7.8)×.66×(.728)2=2.72 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "Calculate the time period of the waveform y(t)=87cos(πt+289π÷4).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 sec",
            "b) 37 sec",
            "c) 3 sec",
            "d) 1 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fundamental time period of the cosine wave is 2π. The time period of y(t) is a 2π÷π=2 sec. The time period is independent of phase shifting and time shifting."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "Calculate the useful power developed by a motor using the given data: Pin = 10 W, Ia = .6 A, Ra=.2 Ω. Assume frictional losses are 2 W and windage losses are 3 W.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.928 W",
            "b) 1.955 W",
            "c) 1.485 W",
            "d) 1.488 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Useful power is basically the shaft power developed by the motor that can be calculated using the formula Psh = Pdev-(rotational losses). Pdev = Pin-Ia2Ra = 10-.62(.2)=9.92 W. The useful power developed by the motor is Psh = Pdev-(rotational losses) = 9.92 –(5) = 4.928 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 86.5°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 16.34 Ω",
            "b) 15.88 Ω",
            "c) 48.43 Ω",
            "d) 54.57 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 16.34° so R=tan(16.34°)=16.34 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 7481 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1562 W",
            "b) 4651 W",
            "c) 0 W",
            "d) 4654 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90 = 0 W. Voltage leads the current in case of the inductor."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 56 F capacitor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.45 W",
            "b) 0 W",
            "c) 15.45 W",
            "d) 14.23 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The capacitor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the capacitor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P=VIcos90 = 0 W. Current leads the voltage in case of the capacitor."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in .an 18.064 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.48 W",
            "b) 17.89 W",
            "c) 0 W",
            "d) 25.45 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90 = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 1.7 Ω resistor with 1.8 A current flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.5 W",
            "b) 5.1 W",
            "c) 5.4 W",
            "d) 5.7 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 0°. P=I2R=1.8×1.8×1.7=5.5 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the time period if the frequency of the signal is .48 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 Hz",
            "b) 3 Hz",
            "c) 7 Hz",
            "d) 9 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The time period is defined as the time after the signal repeats itself. It is expressed in second. T = 1÷F=1÷.48=2 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "Choose the correct in the case of V/F control.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ns-Nr=constant",
            "b) Ns*Nr=constant",
            "c) Ns%Nr=constant",
            "d) Ns+Nr=constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In variable frequency control Ns-Nr remains constant. V/f control is part of the synchronous speed changing technique. It is the most used technique in controlling the induction motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "A 32-pole, 3-phase, 70 Hz induction motor is operating at a speed of 112 rpm. The frequency of the rotor current of the motor in Hz is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40.2",
            "b) 46.1",
            "c) 40.1",
            "d) 40.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given a number of poles = 32. Supply frequency is 70 Hz. Rotor speed is 112 rpm. Ns = 120×f÷P=120×70÷32 = 262.5 rpm. S=Ns-Nr÷Ns = 262.5-112÷262.5=.573. F2=sf=.573×70=40.1 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "A 20-pole, 3-phase, 90 Hz induction motor is operating at a speed of  _______ rpm. The frequency of the rotor current of the motor in Hz is 20.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 418.56",
            "b) 420.12",
            "c) 421.23",
            "d) 422.45"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Given a number of poles = 20. Supply frequency is 90 Hz. Ns=120×f÷P=120×90÷20 = 540 rpm. S=20÷90 = .222 Hz. Nr=(1-s)Ns = 420.12 rpm. Rotor speed is 420.12 rpm."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "Calculate the amplitude of the sinusoidal waveform z(t)=.27sin(.369πt+.142π÷4.25).",
        "Options": [
            "a) .287",
            "b) .270",
            "c) .216",
            "d) .287"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sinusoidal waveform is generally expressed in the form of V=Vmsin(ωt+α) where Vm represents peak value, ω represents angular frequency, α represents a phase difference. By comparing the waveform z(t) with the generalized sinusoidal expression we can see Vm=.27 and ω=.369π rad/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "R.M.S value of the sinusoidal waveform q(t)=2.11cos(87.25t+78π÷478.23).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.49 V",
            "b) 1.56 V",
            "c) 1.12 V",
            "d) 1.78 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: R.M.S value of the sinusoidal waveform is Vm÷2½ and r.m.s value of the trapezoidal waveform is Vm÷3½. The peak value of the sinusoidal waveform is Vm. The r.m.s value is Vrms = 2.11÷2½ = 1.49 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "The no-load circuit test on a 3-Φ induction motor is conducted at a rotor speed of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) < Ns",
            "c) > Ns",
            "d) Ns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: No-load circuit test in an induction motor is also called an open circuit test so it is conducted at synchronous speed. Net input power taken is equal to the no-load rotational losses."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "If induction motor air gap power is 67 KW and mechanically developed power is 26 KW, then rotor ohmic loss will be _________ KW.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 41",
            "b) 42",
            "c) 43",
            "d) 44"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rotor ohmic losses are due to the resistance of armature windings. Net input power to the rotor is equal to the sum of rotor ohmic losses and mechanically developed power. Rotor ohmic losses=Air gap power-Mechanical developed power=67-26=41 KW."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "Calculate the line voltage in star connection when phase voltage=45 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 77.9 V",
            "b) 77.6 V",
            "c) 77.2 V",
            "d) 77.8 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The line voltage in case of star connection is 1.73 times of phase voltage. It leads the phase voltage by an angle of 30°. VL-L=1.73×45=77.9 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 1.1°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .019 Ω",
            "b) .036 Ω",
            "c) .075 Ω",
            "d) .084 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 1.° so R=tan(1.1°)=.019 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "If induction motor rotor power is 157.5 KW and gross developed power is 79.9 KW, then rotor ohmic loss will be _________ KW.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 77.5",
            "b) 77.6",
            "c) 76.9",
            "d) 77.1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rotor ohmic losses are due to the resistance of armature windings. Net input power to the rotor is equal to the sum of rotor ohmic losses and mechanically developed power. Rotor ohmic losses=Air gap power-Mechanical developed power=157.5-79.9=77.6 KW."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "The power factor of a squirrel cage induction motor generally is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) .6-.8",
            "b) .1-.2",
            "c) .2-.4",
            "d) .5-.7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At light loads, the current drawn is largely a magnetizing current due to the air gap and hence the power factor is low. The power factor of a squirrel cage induction motor generally is .6-.8."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a .89 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.535 W",
            "b) 0 W",
            "c) 2.484 W",
            "d) 1.598 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P=VIcos90° = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "Calculate the time period of the waveform i(t)=sin(πt+6π÷4)+sin(πt+5π÷6).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 sec",
            "b) 4 sec",
            "c) 5 sec",
            "d) 3 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fundamental time period of the sine wave is 2π. The time period of i(t) is L.C.M {2,2}=2 sec. The time period is independent of phase shifting and time shifting."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "Calculate the total heat dissipated in a rotor resistor of 14.23 Ω when .65 A current flows through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.45 W",
            "b) 6.01 W",
            "c) 6.78 W",
            "d) 6.98 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rotor resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P=I2R=.65×.65×14.23=6.01 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "Calculate mark to space ratio if the system is on for 4.3 sec and off for 78.2 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .054",
            "b) .047",
            "c) .039",
            "d) .018"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mark to space is Ton÷Toff. It is the ratio of time for which the system is active and the time for which is inactive. M = Ton÷Toff = 4.3÷78.2 = .054."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "In the rotor voltage injection method, when an external voltage source is in phase with the main voltage then speed will ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Remain unchanged",
            "d) First increases then decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the rotor injection method, when an external voltage is in phase with the main voltage net voltage increases and the value of slip decreases and the value of rotor speed increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "A 2-pole, 3-phase, ______ Hz induction motor is operating at a speed of 550 rpm. The frequency of the rotor current of the motor in Hz is 2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9.98",
            "b) 9.71",
            "c) 9.12",
            "d) 9.37"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Given a number of poles = 2. Rotor speed is 550 rpm. Ns=120×f÷P=120×f÷2 = 60f rpm. S=Ns-Nr÷Ns. F2=sf. S=F2÷f. Supply frequency is 9.37 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "Calculate the average value of the sinusoidal waveform x(t)=848sin(1.65πt+2π÷0.68).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 78 V",
            "c) 15 V",
            "d) 85 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sinusoidal waveform is generally expressed in the form of V=Vmsin(Ωt+α) where Vm represents peak value, Ω represents angular frequency, α represents a phase difference. The average value of a sine wave is zero because of equal and opposite lobes areas."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "R.M.S value of the periodic square waveform of amplitude 72 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 72 V",
            "b) 56 V",
            "c) 12 V",
            "d) 33 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: R.M.S value of the periodic square waveform is Vm and r.m.s value of the trapezoidal waveform is Vm÷3½. The peak value of the periodic square waveform is Vm."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "In the rotor voltage injection method, when an external voltage source is in opposite phase with the main voltage then speed will ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Remain unchanged",
            "d) First increases then decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the rotor injection method, when an external voltage is in opposite phase with the main voltage net voltage decreases and the value of slip increases and the value of rotor speed decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 9.1°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .16 Ω",
            "b) .26 Ω",
            "c) .25 Ω",
            "d) .44 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rotor injection method comes under slip changing technique. It uses an external voltage source to change the slip value. The load torque remains constant here."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "If induction motor air gap power is 1.8 KW and gross developed power is .1 KW, then rotor ohmic loss will be _________ KW.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.7",
            "b) 2.7",
            "c) 3.7",
            "d) 4.7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Slip recovery scheme comes under the synchronous speed changing technique. It uses an external induction machine to change the frequency value. The load torque remains constant here."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "The power factor of a squirrel cage induction motor is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High at light load only",
            "b) High at heavy loads only",
            "c) Low at the light and heavy loads both",
            "d) Low at rate load only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 9.1° so R=tan(9.1°)=.16 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "At low values of slip, the electromagnetic torque is directly proportional to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) s",
            "b) s2",
            "c) s3",
            "d) s4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rotor ohmic losses are due to the resistance of armature windings. Net input power to the rotor is equal to the sum of rotor ohmic losses and mechanically developed power. Rotor ohmic losses=Air gap power-Mechanical developed power = 1.8-.1=1.7 KW."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "Calculate the time period of the waveform v(t)=12sin(8πt+8π÷15)+144sin(2πt+π÷6)+ 445sin(πt+7π÷6).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8 sec",
            "b) 4 sec",
            "c) 7 sec",
            "d) 3 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At heavy loads, the current drawn is high due to which active power component increases. Increase in active power component increases the power factor of the machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "Calculate the total heat dissipated in a resistor of 44 Ω when 0 A current flows through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 W",
            "b) 2 W",
            "c) 1.5 W",
            "d) .3 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At low values of slip, the electromagnetic torque is directly proportional to slip value. Due to heavy loading slip value decreases which increases the ratio of R2÷s."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "The value of slip at which maximum torque occurs ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) R2÷X2",
            "b) 4R2÷X2",
            "c) 2R2÷X2",
            "d) R2÷3X2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The fundamental time period of the sine wave is 2π. The time period of z(t) is L.C.M {4,1,2}=4 sec. The time period is independent of phase shifting and time shifting."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Calculate the voltage regulation in the synchronous machine if the no-load voltage is 12 V and the full load voltage is 15V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) -20%",
            "b) -40%",
            "c) -60%",
            "d) -80%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Voltage regulation is defined as the fluctuation in the load voltage when the load is varied from no-load to full load. V.R(%) = (No-load voltage-Full load voltage) ÷ Full load voltage=12-15÷15 = -20%."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "Calculate the condition for maximum voltage regulation in the synchronous machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Φ=ϴs",
            "b) Φ=2ϴs",
            "c) Φ=4ϴs",
            "d) Φ=8ϴs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Voltage regulation is maximum in case of inductive load. The condition for maximum voltage regulation is when the power factor angle of the load becomes equal to the impedance angle. V.R=Rp.ucos(Φ)+Xp.usin(Φ). Differentiate V.R with respect to Φ and put it equal to zero. We will get tan(Φ) = Xp.u÷Rp.u=tan(ϴs) then Φ=ϴs."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "R.M.S value of the sinusoidal waveform v(t)=211sin(7.25t+7π÷78.3).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 149.19 V",
            "b) 156.23 V",
            "c) 116.57 V",
            "d) 178.64 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Zero voltage regulation only occurs during a leading power factor load. Condition for zero voltage regulation occurs when Φ+ϴs > 90o. For example – Capacitive load."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Calculate the peak value of sinusoidal waveform if the r.m.s value is 21 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 29.69 V",
            "b) 48.74 V",
            "c) 69.23 V",
            "d) 25.74 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: R.M.S value of the sinusoidal waveform is Vm÷2½ = 211÷2½ = 149.19 V and r.m.s value of the trapezoidal waveform is Vm÷3½. The peak value of the sinusoidal waveform is Vm."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "If induction motor air gap power is 2 KW and mechanically developed power is 1 KW, then rotor ohmic loss will be _________ KW.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: R.M.S value of the sinusoidal waveform is Vpeak÷2½ and r.m.s value of the trapezoidal waveform is Vm÷3½. The peak value of the sinusoidal waveform is Vr.m.s×2½. Vpeak = Vr.m.s×2½=21×1.414=29.69 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Calculate the line voltage in the delta connection when phase voltage=45 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 46 V",
            "b) 47 V",
            "c) 45 V",
            "d) 78 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rotor ohmic losses are due to the resistance of armature windings. Net input power to the rotor is equal to the sum of rotor ohmic losses and mechanically developed power. Rotor ohmic losses=Air gap power-Mechanical developed power=2-1=1 KW."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 35.48°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.452 Ω",
            "b) 0.462 Ω",
            "c) 0.752 Ω",
            "d) 0.712 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The line voltage in case of delta connection is phase voltage. Line current leads the phase current by an angle of 30°. VL-L=Vph = 45 V. "
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "If induction motor rotor power is 157.5 KW and gross developed power is 79.9 KW, then rotor ohmic loss will be _________ KW.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 77.5",
            "b) 77.6",
            "c) 76.9",
            "d) 77.1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 35.48° so R=tan(35.48°)=.712 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "Calculate the line current in the delta connection when phase current=17 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 29.44 A",
            "b) 24.64 A",
            "c) 23.48 A",
            "d) 26.56 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rotor ohmic losses are due to the resistance of armature windings. Net input power to the rotor is equal to the sum of rotor ohmic losses and mechanically developed power. Rotor ohmic losses=Air gap power-Mechanical developed power=157.5-79.9=77.6 KW."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 168.12 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 65 W",
            "b) 0 W",
            "c) 68 W",
            "d) 64 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The line voltage in case of delta connection is phase voltage. Line current leads the phase current by an angle of 30°. IL-L = 1.73×Iph = 29.44 A. "
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Calculate the maximum value of slip when rotor resistance is 2 Ω and rotor reactance is 3 Ω.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.66",
            "b) 0.33",
            "c) 0.44",
            "d) 0.99"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90° = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "Calculate the total heat dissipated in a rotor resistor of 21 Ω when .81 A current flows through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 13.77 W",
            "b) 12.56",
            "c) 16.78 W",
            "d) 13.98 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum torque occurs when the slip value is equal to R2÷X2. Maximum torque is also known as breakdown torque, stalling torque and pull-out torque. The maximum value of slip is R2÷X2=2/3=.66. "
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in an 8.12 F capacitor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 89 W",
            "b) 41 W",
            "c) 0 W",
            "d) 48 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rotor resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P=I2R=.81×.81×21=13.77 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of new slip using the given data: V1=12 V, S1=.1, V2=5.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.576",
            "b) 0.247",
            "c) 0.487",
            "d) 0.987"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Stator voltage control method comes under slip changing technique. The load torque remains constant here. SV2=constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "Calculate the average value of the sinusoidal waveform y(t)=4.56cos(77.64πt+4800π÷68).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 41 V",
            "b) 0 V",
            "c) 48 V",
            "d) 78 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This question is based on the concept of stator voltage control method. The load torque remains constant. S1V12=S2V22=constant. S2=.576. "
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "R.M.S value of the periodic square waveform of amplitude 20 V is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 V",
            "b) 18 V",
            "c) 17 V",
            "d) 13 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sinusoidal waveform is generally expressed in the form of V=Vmsin(ωt+α) where Vm represents peak value, ω represents angular frequency, α represents a phase difference. The average value of a sine wave is zero because of equal and opposite lobes areas. Since sine wave is an odd function then the net area of the waveform over a period is Net area = A+(-A) = 0. The average value is Net area÷Time=0."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "Calculate the time period of the waveform y(t)=sin(.1πt)+cos(.2πt).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 sec",
            "b) 30 sec",
            "c) 40 sec",
            "d) 10 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: R.M.S value of the periodic square waveform is Vm and r.m.s value of the trapezoidal waveform is Vm÷3½. The peak value of the periodic square waveform is Vm. Vm=20 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 56.489°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5 Ω",
            "b) 1.6 Ω",
            "c) 2.5 Ω",
            "d) 1.4 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fundamental time period of the sine and cosine wave is 2π. The time period of y(t) is L.C.M {20,10}=20 sec. The time period is independent of phase shifting and time shifting."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "If induction motor air gap power is 28.63 KW and gross developed power is 18.8 KW, then rotor ohmic loss will be _________ KW.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9.83",
            "b) 10.55",
            "c) 15.54",
            "d) 4.74"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: V/F control comes under the synchronous speed changing technique. Speed above or below synchronous speed can be achieved using V/F control."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of inductive reactance if F=50 Hz and L=12 H.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3768\tΩ",
            "b) 2578 Ω",
            "c) 2477 Ω",
            "d) 2456 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 56.489° so R=tan(56.489°)=1.5 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of capacitive reactance if F=60 Hz and C=14 H.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 189.5 mΩ",
            "b) 252.4 mΩ",
            "c) 244.5 mΩ",
            "d) 244.8 mΩ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rotor ohmic losses are due to the resistance of armature windings. Net input power to the rotor is equal to the sum of rotor ohmic losses and mechanically developed power. Rotor ohmic losses=Air gap power-Mechanical developed power=28.63-18.8=9.83 KW."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "Calculate the time period of the waveform v(t)=.6sin(.1πt+8π)+17cos(2πt+π)+ 4tan(.1πt).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 88 sec",
            "b) 20 sec",
            "c) 70 sec",
            "d) 43 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Inductive reactance can be calculated using the relation XL=2×3.14×f×L. The value of inductive reactance is XL=2×3.14×50×12=3768 Ω. "
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of resistance if total heat dissipated is 78 W when 5 A current flows through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.12 Ω",
            "b) 2.24 Ω",
            "c) 1.45 Ω",
            "d) 5.13 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Capacitive reactance can be calculated using the relation Xc=1÷2×3.14×f×L. The value of capacitive reactance is Xc=1÷2×3.14×50×12=189.5 mΩ. "
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "The value of slip at the starting of an induction motor is  ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The fundamental time period of the sine wave is 2π. The time period of v(t) is L.C.M {20,1,20}=20 sec. The time period is independent of phase shifting and time shifting."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "The value of the slip of an induction motor during full load condition is  ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.99",
            "b) .1",
            "c) .8",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 0°. R=P÷I2=3.12 Ω."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "40 V, 7 A, 70 rpm DC separately excited motor having a resistance of 0.3 ohms excited by an external dc voltage source of 4 V. Calculate the torque developed by the motor on half load.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18.10 N-m",
            "b) 4.24 N-m",
            "c) 40.45 N-m",
            "d) 52.64 N-m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Back emf developed in the motor during the full load can be calculated using equation Eb = Vt-I×Ra = 37.9 V and machine constant Km = Eb÷Wm which is equal to 5.17. Torque can be calculated by using the relation T = Km× I = 5.17×3.5 = 18.10 N-m."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power developed by a motor using the given data: Eb = 5.5 V and I = .5 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.75 W",
            "b) 2.20 W",
            "c) 5.30 W",
            "d) 5.50 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Power developed by the motor can be calculated using the formula P = Eb×I = 5.5×.5 = 2.75 W. If rotational losses are neglected, the power developed becomes equal to the shaft power of the motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the angular acceleration of the motor using the given data: J = .1 kg-m2, load torque = 45 N-m, motor torque = 55 N-m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 rad/s2",
            "b) 222 rad/s2",
            "c) 300 rad/s2",
            "d) 400 rad/s2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Using the dynamic equation of motor J×(angular acceleration) = Motor torque – Load torque: .1×(angular acceleration) = 55-45=10, angular acceleration = 100 rad/s2."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the tennis ball having a mass of 7 kg and diameter of 152 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.55 kgm2",
            "b) 4.47 kgm2",
            "c) 2.66 kgm2",
            "d) 1.41 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the tennis ball can be calculated using the formula I=mr2×.5. The mass of the ball and diameter is given. I=(7)×.5×(.76)2=2.66 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the thin spherical shell having a mass of 7.8 kg and diameter of 145.6 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.72 kgm2",
            "b) 5.96 kgm2",
            "c) 5.45 kgm2",
            "d) 2.78 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the thin spherical shell can be calculated using the formula I=mr2×.66. The mass of the thin spherical shell and diameter is given. I=(7.8)×.66×(.728)2=2.72 kgm2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "Calculate the time period of the waveform y(t)=87cos(πt+289π÷4).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 sec",
            "b) 37 sec",
            "c) 3 sec",
            "d) 1 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fundamental time period of the cosine wave is 2π. The time period of y(t) is a 2π÷π=2 sec. The time period is independent of phase shifting and time shifting."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Calculate the useful power developed by a motor using the given data: Pin = 10 W, Ia = .6 A, Ra=.2 Ω. Assume frictional losses are 2 W and windage losses are 3 W.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.928 W",
            "b) 1.955 W",
            "c) 1.485 W",
            "d) 1.488 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Useful power is basically the shaft power developed by the motor that can be calculated using the formula Psh = Pdev-(rotational losses). Pdev = Pin-Ia2Ra = 10-.62(.2)=9.92 W. The useful power developed by the motor is Psh = Pdev-(rotational losses) = 9.92 –(5) = 4.928 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 86.5°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 16.34 Ω",
            "b) 15.88 Ω",
            "c) 48.43 Ω",
            "d) 54.57 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 16.34° so R=tan(16.34°)=16.34 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 7481 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1562 W",
            "b) 4651 W",
            "c) 0 W",
            "d) 4654 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90 = 0 W. Voltage leads the current in case of the inductor."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 56 F capacitor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.45 W",
            "b) 0 W",
            "c) 15.45 W",
            "d) 14.23 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The capacitor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the capacitor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P=VIcos90 = 0 W. Current leads the voltage in case of the capacitor."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in .an 18.064 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.48 W",
            "b) 17.89 W",
            "c) 0 W",
            "d) 25.45 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90 = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 1.7 Ω resistor with 1.8 A current flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.5 W",
            "b) 5.1 W",
            "c) 5.4 W",
            "d) 5.7 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 0°. P=I2R=1.8×1.8×1.7=5.5 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the time period if the frequency of the signal is .48 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 Hz",
            "b) 3 Hz",
            "c) 7 Hz",
            "d) 9 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The time period is defined as the time after the signal repeats itself. It is expressed in second. T = 1÷F=1÷.48=2 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "Choose the correct in the case of V/F control.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ns-Nr=constant",
            "b) Ns*Nr=constant",
            "c) Ns%Nr=constant",
            "d) Ns+Nr=constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In variable frequency control Ns-Nr remains constant. V/f control is part of the synchronous speed changing technique. It is the most used technique in controlling the induction motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "Calculate the minimum value of the active power in the cylindrical rotor synchronous machine? (Eb represents armature emf, Vt represents terminal voltage, δ represents rotor angle, X represents reactance)",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eb×Vt×sinδ÷X",
            "b) 0",
            "c) Eb2×Vt×sinδ÷X",
            "d) Eb×Vt÷X"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The real power in the cylindrical rotor machine is Eb×Vt×sinδ÷X. It is inversely proportional to the reactance. The stability of the machine is decided by the maximum power transfer capability. Its minimum value occurs for delta=0°."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "Calculate the power factor if the power angle is 45°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .707",
            "b) .407",
            "c) .608",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cylindrical pole machines are less stable than salient rotor machines because of the less short circuit ratio and less real power transfer capability. The air gap length in cylindrical pole machines is less as compare to salient rotor machines."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "Calculate the reactive power in a 451.26 Ω resistor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 VAR",
            "b) .6 VAR",
            "c) 0 VAR",
            "d) .9 VAR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Area is defined as the product of length and breadth. The length and breadth are expressed in the meter. The unit of area is m2."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "What is the unit of displacement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) m/s",
            "b) m",
            "c) atm/m",
            "d) Volt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Power factor is the ratio of the real power to the apparent power. It measures the useful power contained in the total power cosΦ=cos(45°)=.707."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "Calculate the reactive power in a 725.45 Ω resistor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 122.1 VAR",
            "b) 261.1 VAR",
            "c) 0 VAR",
            "d) 199.7 VAR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 0°. Q=VIsin0° = 0 VAR."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "The slope of the I-V curve is 180°. Calculate the value of resistance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) inf Ω",
            "b) .81 Ω",
            "c) 45 Ω",
            "d) 41.2 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Displacement is the difference between the final and initial point. It is a vector quantity. It is expressed in the meter. It is not a tensor quantity. It has direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the duty cycle if the system is on for 1 sec and off for inf sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) .89",
            "c) .148",
            "d) .46"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 0°. Q = VIsin0° = 0 VAR."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "The phase difference between voltage and current in the purely inductive coil.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20°",
            "b) 90°",
            "c) 40°",
            "d) 88°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slope of the I-V curve is the reciprocal of the resistance. The slope given is 180° so R=1÷tan(180°)=inf Ω. The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. It behaves as an open circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the short circuit ratio if Voc=78 V, Isc=15 A with field current = 5 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.2",
            "b) 4.8",
            "c) 3.2",
            "d) 1.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Duty cycle is Ton÷Ttotal. It is the ratio of time for which the system is active and the time taken by the signal to complete one cycle. D = Ton÷Ttotal=1÷inf = 0."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the short circuit ratio if the per unit value of synchronous reactance is 1.5 Ω.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.66",
            "b) 0.33",
            "c) 0.17",
            "d) 0.12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the short circuit ratio determines the stability of the synchronous machine. It is inversely proportional to the per unit value of reactance. SCR=1÷Xs(p.u)=1÷1.5=.66. "
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "Calculate the power factor if the power angle is 12°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .87",
            "b) .47",
            "c) .97",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SCR is inversely proportional to the per unit value of synchronous reactance. Armature reaction depends upon the value of the synchronous reactance. A higher value of armature reaction means the lower value of the short circuit ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "Calculate the reactive power in an 84 MΩ resistor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.47 VAR",
            "b) 45.6 VAR",
            "c) 0.59 VAR",
            "d) 0 VAR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: SCR is the ratio of the field currents required to produce open circuit voltage and short circuit current. It is a ratio. It has no unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the resistance of a wire of length = 12 m, area = 2 m2 and Ρ = 6 Ω-m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 36 Ω",
            "b) 6 Ω",
            "c) 26 Ω",
            "d) 10 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Power factor is the ratio of the real power to the apparent power. It measures the useful power contained in the total power cosΦ=cos(12°)=.97."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "Calculate the reactive power in a 29.6 Ω resistor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45.1 VAR",
            "b) 41.1 VAR",
            "c) 46 VAR",
            "d) 0 VAR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 0°. Q=VIsin0° = 0 VAR."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "The slope of the I-V curve is 160°. Calculate the value of resistance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .36 Ω",
            "b) .41 Ω",
            "c) .89 Ω",
            "d) 2.74 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Resistance is the opposition offered by the body to the flow of the current. It is expressed in terms of Ω. R = ΡL/A = 36 Ω."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the power if voltage=4.2 V and current=10 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 42 W",
            "b) 12 W",
            "c) 16 W",
            "d) 18 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 0°. Q=VIsin0° = 0 VAR."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "1 calorie is equal to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.18 J",
            "b) 5.23 J",
            "c) 6.23 J",
            "d) 8 J"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The slope of the I-V curve is the reciprocal of the resistance. The slope given is 160° so R=1÷tan(160°)=2.74 Ω. The slope of the V-I curve is resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "1 Horse-power is equal to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 745.7 W",
            "b) 741 W",
            "c) 747.7 W",
            "d) 740 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Power is the product of the voltage and current. It is generally expressed in term of W. P=vi=4.2×10=42 W. 1 horsepower=746 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the time period if the frequency of the signal is 58 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .017 sec",
            "b) .014 sec",
            "c) .045 sec",
            "d) .077 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The calorie is the unit of energy. It is equal to 4.18 Joule. It is the amount of heat energy required to raise the temperature of one 1 g of water by 1° Celsius."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the short circuit ratio if the per unit value of synchronous reactance is 4.2 Ω.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.26",
            "b) 0.23",
            "c) 0.67",
            "d) 0.72"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 1 Horse-power is equal to 745.7 W. It is equal to the rate at which work is done. Horse-power is the amount of work done by horse in carrying the weight of 90 kg for 50 meters in 60 seconds."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the short circuit ratio if the per unit value of synchronous reactance is 1 Ω. Assume armature resistance is 0 ohm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The time period is defined as the time after the signal repeats itself. It is expressed in second. T=1÷F=1÷58=.017 sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "Full form of SCIM.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Squirrel cage induction motor",
            "b) Solid cage induction motor",
            "c) Square cage induction motor",
            "d) Squirrel cage inverter motor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In regenerative braking, the motor acts as a generator. The back emf is more than the terminal voltage in case of regenerative braking."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "Wound rotor induction motor has better ________ characteristics than Squirrel cage induction motor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Starting",
            "b) Running",
            "c) Modified",
            "d) Quasi-state"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In regenerative braking, the power is fed back to the source from the battery. The kinetic energy of the motor shaft is converted into electrical energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "All circuits are always _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Networks",
            "b) Resistors",
            "c) Capacitors",
            "d) Inductors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SCIM stands for squirrel cage induction motor. SCIM rotor is made up of aluminum, copper bars. There are no armature conductors involved in it."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "The dead network does not have any _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dependent source",
            "b) Independent source",
            "c) Resistor",
            "d) Capacitor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wound rotor induction motor has better starting characteristics because external resistance can be connected to it using slip rings to start the motor. In the case of SCIM, no external resistance can be connected to the rotor side."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "During short circuit condition, the voltage is equal to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 V",
            "b) 0 V",
            "c) 1 V",
            "d) 3 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The network is defined as the interconnection of electrical elements that may or may not has a closed path. The circuit is defined as the interconnection of an element that must have at least one closed path. All circuits are always networks but vice-versa is not true."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "When 5 A current flows into the positive terminal of voltage source 6 V. Calculate the power delivered by the source.",
        "Options": [
            "a) -30 W",
            "b) 36 W",
            "c) -43 W",
            "d) 50 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the case of the dead network there are no independent sources available in the electrical circuit. The Thevenin voltage of the circuit is zero because no force is available to drive the current in the circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "When 10 A current leaves the positive terminal of resistance 5Ω. Calculate the power absorbed by the resistance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) -308 W",
            "b) 500 W",
            "c) -63 W",
            "d) 60 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During the short circuit condition, the voltage is equal to zero volts. According to Ohm’s law, V=IR=0 V. The value of the current can be positive, negative or zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "Calculate the equivalent inductance when two inductors are connected in series of values 4 H and 9 H.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 13 H",
            "b) 10 H",
            "c) 11 H",
            "d) 12 H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the current enters the positive terminal of an element it will always absorb the power and when the current leaves the positive terminal it will deliver the power. Power delivered is -5×6=-30 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "Calculate the equivalent resistance when three resistances are connected in series of values 8 Ω, 3 Ω, 1 Ω.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12 Ω",
            "b) 18 Ω",
            "c) 15 Ω",
            "d) 16 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the current enters the positive terminal of an element it will always absorb the power and when the current leaves the positive terminal it will deliver the power. Power delivered is 100×5=500 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in an inf Ω resistor with 0 current flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) inf MW",
            "b) 4.44 MW",
            "c) 12 MW",
            "d) 6.18 MW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When two inductors are connected in series their equivalent inductance is equal to the sum of the individual inductances. Leq=L1+L2=4+9=13 H."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "When 15 A current flows into the positive terminal of voltage source 60 V. Calculate the power delivered by the source.",
        "Options": [
            "a) -900 W",
            "b) 936 W",
            "c) -943 W",
            "d) 950 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When three resistances are connected in series their equivalent resistance is equal to the sum of the individual resistances. Req=R1+ R3+R2=12 Ω."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "Source transformation is not valid for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ideal voltage source",
            "b) Ideal current and voltage source",
            "c) Practical voltage source",
            "d) Practical current source"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 0°. P=I2R=0×0×inf=inf MW."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "Which braking method is the best method for obtaining high braking torque?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Regenerative braking",
            "b) Plugging",
            "c) Dynamic braking",
            "d) Rheostatic braking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Plugging is the best braking method among all braking techniques. In plugging the value of the armature current reverses and the mechanical energy is extracted. A very high braking torque is produced in case of plugging."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "The polarity of back e.m.f changes in which of the method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plugging",
            "b) Regenerative braking",
            "c) Dynamic braking",
            "d) Rheostatic braking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In case of Plugging braking technique polarity of the back e.m.f voltage changes due to which current direction changes and mechanical, electrical energy are wasted in the form of heat in resistors."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "Full form of WRIM.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wound round induction motor",
            "b) World cage induction motor",
            "c) Wolf cage induction motor",
            "d) Squirrel cage inverter motor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: WRIM stands for wound round induction motor. WRIM rotor is made up of armature conductors. There are no copper bars, rods involved in it."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "Calculate the energy stored in the capacitor if the voltage across the capacitor is 20 V and capacitance value is 2 F.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400 J",
            "b) 200 J",
            "c) 100 J",
            "d) 50 J"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The energy stored in the capacitor is .5×C×V2. It is the total amount of energy stored in the capacitor in the steady state condition. E=.5×C×V2=.5×2×20×20=400 J."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "Calculate the energy stored in the inductor if the current value is 4 A and inductance value is 1 H.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 J",
            "b) 2 J",
            "c) 8 J",
            "d) 5 J"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The energy stored in the inductor is .5×L×I2. It is the total amount of energy stored in the inductor in the steady state condition. E=.5×L×I2=.5×1×4×4=8 J."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "During the open circuit condition, the current is equal to ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 A",
            "b) 0 A",
            "c) 4 A",
            "d) 7 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The network is defined as the interconnection of electrical elements that may or may not has a closed path. The circuit is defined as the interconnection of an element that must have at least one closed path. All networks are not always circuits but vice-versa is true."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "The minimum value of the impedance in case of the series RLC network is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) R",
            "b) 0",
            "c) Xl",
            "d) Xc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the case of the dead network there are no independent sources available in the electrical circuit. The Thevenin voltage of the circuit is zero because no force is available to drive the current in the circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "Calculate the quality factor for the purely inductive coil.",
        "Options": [
            "a) inf",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During the open circuit condition, the current is equal to zero amperes. According to Ohm’s law, I=V/R=0 A. The value of the voltage can be positive, negative or zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "Calculate the quality factor for the pure capacitor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) inf",
            "b) 0",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum value of the series impedance in case of the series RLC network is R. During resonance condition Xl=Xc so Z=(R2+(Xl-XC)2).5=R."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "Calculate the equivalent inductance when n inductors are connected in series of values L.",
        "Options": [
            "a) n2L H",
            "b) nL H",
            "c) .5L H",
            "d) 2 H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The quality factor is defined as the ratio of the reactive power to the active power consumed. The purely inductive coil always absorb reactive power. The value of active power consumed is 0. Quality factor=Q/0=inf."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Calculate the equivalent resistance when two resistances are connected in series of values 12 Ω, 10 Ω.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 32 Ω",
            "b) 22 Ω",
            "c) 47 Ω",
            "d) 17 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The quality factor is defined as the ratio of the reactive power to the active power consumed. The pure capacitor always absorbs reactive power. The value of active power consumed is 0. Quality factor=Q/0=inf."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "The value of unit step function at t=5 sec is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1",
            "c) -1",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Unit step function is discontinuous at t=0. The value of the unit step function is 1 for t>0 and zero for t<0. It is right handed and bounded signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "The value of impulse at t=0 is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 1",
            "d) infinite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Impulse function is neither an energy signal nor a power signal. It is a pulse of infinite amplitude and zero width. The value of impulse is 0 for time not equal to zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "Full form of IFOC.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indirect field oriented control",
            "b) Inverter field oriented control",
            "c) Isolated field oriented control",
            "d) Insight field oriented control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IFOC stands for indirect field oriented control. DTC and IFOC are the techniques used for controlling the speed and torque of a 3-phase induction motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "The characteristics shown by an element in the I-V curve is a straight line passing through the origin with a positive slope. The nature of the element is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-linear, Bilateral",
            "b) Linear, Unilateral",
            "c) Linear, Bilateral",
            "d) Non-linear, Unilateral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The nature of the element is linear and bilateral. It follows the principle of homogeneity and law of additivity. For bilateral nature, it should be symmetrical in the first and third quadrant."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "Calculate the total energy stored in the inductor if the current value is 4 A and inductance values are 1 H and 2 H.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 72 J",
            "b) 22 J",
            "c) 82 J",
            "d) 24 J"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The energy stored in the inductor is .5×Leq×I2. The value of Leq=1+2=3 H. The total amount of energy stored in the inductor in the steady state condition. E=.5×eq×I2=.5×3×4×4=24 J."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "The minimum value of the admittance in case of the parallel RLC network is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) R",
            "b) 1÷R",
            "c) Xl-Xc",
            "d) Xc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mesh analysis is one of the network tools to find the responses in the circuits. It is only applicable to planar circuits. Planar circuits are 2-D circuits as mesh analysis involves mesh circulating currents."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the inductive reactance during resonance if the value of capacitive reactance is 2 ohm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8 Ω",
            "b) 2 Ω",
            "c) 3 Ω",
            "d) 1 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Loop is defined as the closed path which can contain small closed paths. Mesh does not contain any closed path. All meshes are loops but vice-versa is not true."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "Calculate the quality factor for the resistor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) inf",
            "b) 0",
            "c) 1",
            "d) .7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The nodal method is one of the best methods to solve any circuit problem. It is based on the KCL equation. It is applicable for planar and non-planar circuits. Mesh analysis cannot be applicable for non-planar circuits."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "Calculate the equivalent resistance when two resistances are connected in parallel of values 2 Ω, 2 Ω.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 Ω",
            "b) 2 Ω",
            "c) 4 Ω",
            "d) 7 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum value of the admittance in case of the parallel RLC network is R. During resonance condition Xl=Xc so Y=1÷Z=(R2+(Xl-Xc)2).5=1÷R."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "Calculate the equivalent capacitance when two capacitors are connected in parallel of values 8 F, 7 F.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15 F",
            "b) 20 F",
            "c) 40 F",
            "d) 7 F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Resonance is defined as the phenomenon in which energy of any element changes from one form to another. During resonance condition Xl=Xc=2 Ω."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "A circuit consists of 3 F capacitor and 5 H inductor. Determine the order of the circuit.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The order of the circuit is the number of memory/storing elements which are non-separable present in the circuit. In mathematics, the order is defined as the highest order derivate in the differential equation. The order of the circuit is 2."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "Full form of DTC.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct torque control",
            "b) Digital torque control",
            "c) Discrete torque control",
            "d) Distribution torque control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The steady-state response is a part of the forced response. The forced response is due to the electrical source present in the circuit. Its mathematical equation involves the source present in the circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "The characteristics shown by an element in the I-V curve is V=I2. The nature of the element is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-linear, Bilateral, Passive",
            "b) Linear, Unilateral, Active",
            "c) Linear, Bilateral, Passive",
            "d) Non-linear, Unilateral, Active"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: DTC stands for Direct torque control. DTC and IFOC are the techniques used for controlling the speed and torque of a 3-phase induction motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "Calculate the steady state value for x(t)=4(1-e-3t).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The nature of the element is non-linear, unilateral and active. The shape of the characteristic is parabolic. For bilateral nature, it should be symmetrical in the first and third quadrant. Its slope is negative in the second quadrant which determines its active nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "The natural response is due to _________ conditions present in the circuit.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Initial",
            "b) Final",
            "c) Zero",
            "d) Negative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Transient response is a primary response in the circuit. It is a temporary response which dies out at t=infinity. It consists of exponential decaying functions."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the coefficient of coupling for the isolated coils.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The steady state value is obtained at t=∞. The value of x(t) at t=∞ is 4(1-e-∞)=4(1-0)=4. The term e-3t is an exponentially decaying function."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of equivalent inductance for series aiding of two coils whose self inductances are 5 H, 2 H, and mutual inductance value is 4 H.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15 H",
            "b) 12 H",
            "c) 13 H",
            "d) 11 H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The natural response is due to the initial conditions present in the circuit. The natural response is a complete part of the transient response. It is mathematically represented as y(t)=yo×e-at."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of equivalent inductance for series subtracting polarity of two coils whose self inductances are 14 H, 5 H, and mutual inductance value is 1 H.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15 H",
            "b) 17 H",
            "c) 12 H",
            "d) 10 H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The coefficient of coupling expresses how the two coils are magnetically coupled. It is mathematically represented as K=M÷√L1.L2. For the isolated coils, the value of the mutual inductance is 0. The value of the coefficient of coupling is 0."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the capacitive reactance during resonance if the value of the inductor is 5 H and supply frequency is 20 rad/sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 Ω",
            "b) 200 Ω",
            "c) 300 Ω",
            "d) 700 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The equivalent inductance for series aiding of two coils is Leq=L1+L2+2M=5+2+8=15 H. The value of equivalent inductance increases due to mutually induced e.m.f in case of the magnetically coupled circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "Calculate the quality factor for the R-L circuit if R=28 Ω and L=2 H.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 14",
            "b) 16",
            "c) 10",
            "d) 17"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The equivalent inductance for series subtracting of two coils is Leq=L1+L2-2M=14+5-2=17 H. The value of equivalent inductance decreases due to negatively mutually induced e.m.f in case of the magnetically coupled circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "The quality factor is calculated for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Power factor loads",
            "b) Inductive coils",
            "c) Lagging loads",
            "d) Leading loads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Resonance is defined as the phenomenon in which energy of any element changes from one form to another. During resonance condition Xc=Xl=ΩL=20×5=100 Ω."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "Calculate the equivalent resistance when two resistances are connected in parallel of values 8 Ω, 8 Ω.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 Ω",
            "b) 2 Ω",
            "c) 4 Ω",
            "d) 7 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The quality factor is defined as the ratio of the reactive power to the active power consumed. The resistor always absorbs active power and inductor absorbs the reactive power. Quality factor=R÷L=28÷2=14."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "Calculate the quality factor for the R-C circuit if R=2 Ω and C=1 F.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.2",
            "b) 0.4",
            "c) 0.6",
            "d) 0.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Quality factor is calculated for inductive coils, not for power factor loads. Its value determines the quality of the inductor or capacitor. It shows how good an inductor or capacitor can absorb reactive power. "
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "What is the condition for maximum power transfer theorem in DC circuits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RL=2Rth",
            "b) RL≠Rth",
            "c) RL≫Rth",
            "d) RL=Rth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The condition for maximum power transfer theorem is load should be variable and RL=Rth. During maximum power transfer condition voltage across load becomes half of Thevenin voltage and efficiency becomes 50 %."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "The length of phasor is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) R.M.S",
            "b) Average",
            "c) Peak to Peak",
            "d) Minimum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 3-φ system is more economical than 2-∅ system because of no vibrations in power waveform. The instantaneous power in the 3-∅ system is constant. P=3VpIpcos(φ)=√3VLILcos(∅)."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "Calculate the velocity of the ball if the angular speed is 7 rad/s and radius is .2 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5 m/s",
            "b) 1.4 m/s",
            "c) 4.5 m/s",
            "d) 1.0 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Phasors are the rotating values which rotate with some angular frequency Ω. The length of the phasor value is r.m.s value. "
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the time period if the frequency of the signal is .001 Hz.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000 sec",
            "b) 2000 sec",
            "c) 5000 sec",
            "d) 1500 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bounded systems are those systems which have some finite maximum value and are decaying functions. Transient analysis is only applicable to bounded signals as they achieve steady state after some time."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the frequency of the 440 V DC supply.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 Hz",
            "b) 0 Hz",
            "c) 200 Hz",
            "d) 500 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The velocity of the ball can be calculated using the relation V=Ω×r. The velocity is the vector product of angular speed and radius. V = Ω×r = 7×.2 = 1.4 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of power factor if the values of R and Z are 2 Ω and 10 Ω.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.8",
            "b) 0.5",
            "c) 0.2",
            "d) 0.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The time period is defined as the time after the signal repeats itself. It is expressed in second. T = 1÷F=1÷.001=1000 sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of capacitor voltage during resonance condition if the value of supply voltage is 20 V and the quality factor is 3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60 V",
            "b) 50 V",
            "c) 10 V",
            "d) 30 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The frequency is defined as the number of oscillations per second. It is reciprocal of the time period. DC supply magnitude is constant. It does not change with time so the frequency of DC supply is 0 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "When 30 A current flows into the positive terminal of current source 8 V. Calculate the power delivered by the source.",
        "Options": [
            "a) -240 W",
            "b) 360 W",
            "c) -430 W",
            "d) 500 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The power factor is defined as the ratio of active power to the apparent power. Cos(φ)=R÷Z=2÷10=.2. It has no unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve is 17.587o. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .322 Ω",
            "b) .360 Ω",
            "c) .316 Ω",
            "d) .778 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During the resonance condition XL=Xc. The value of the capacitor voltage is Q×Vs. The power factor of the circuit is one. Vc=20×3=60 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "Calculate the equivalent inductance when two inductors are connected in parallel of values 12 H and 12 H.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 H",
            "b) 10 H",
            "c) 12 H",
            "d) 8 H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the current enters the positive terminal of an element it will always absorb the power and when the current leaves the positive terminal it will deliver the power. Power delivered is -30×8=-240 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in an 0 Ω resistor with 0 current flowing through it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) inf MW",
            "b) 0 MW",
            "c) 2 MW",
            "d) 18 MW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve is resistance. The slope given is 17.587o so R=tan(17.587o)=.316 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "When 1 A current flows out of the positive terminal of voltage source 6 V. Calculate the power delivered by the source.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 W",
            "b) 7 W",
            "c) -9 W",
            "d) -5 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When two inductors are connected in parallel their equivalent inductance is equal to the harmonic mean of the inductances. Leq=L1×L2÷(L1+L2)=6 H."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of inductor voltage during resonance condition if the value of supply voltage is 7 V and the quality factor is 9.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 59 V",
            "b) 63 V",
            "c) 73 V",
            "d) 33 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 0o. P=I2R=0×0×0=0 MW."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "Full form of NENO.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neither even nor odd",
            "b) Neither energy nor odd",
            "c) Neither even nor original",
            "d) Neither even nor orthogonal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The odd functions are those functions which are symmetric about the origin. The sine function is an odd function whose time period is 2π."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "The characteristics shown by an element in the V-I curve is V=Is(1-e-V/K). The nature of the element is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-linear, Bilateral, Passive",
            "b) Linear, Unilateral, Active",
            "c) Linear, Bilateral, Passive",
            "d) Non-linear, Unilateral, Passive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The even functions are those functions which are a mirror image of the y-axis. The cosine function is an even function whose time period is 2π."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "Calculate the resonant frequency if the values of the capacitor and inductor are 2 F and 2 H.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .5 rad/sec",
            "b) .6 rad/sec",
            "c) .8 rad/sec",
            "d) .9 rad/sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: NENO stands for Neither even nor odd. The functions which are not the mirror image of the y-axis and nor symmetric about the origin are NENO functions."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "Calculate the steady state value for x(t)=7e-9t.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 8",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The nature of the element is non-linear, unilateral and passive. The shape of the characteristic is exponential rising. For bilateral nature, it should be symmetrical in the first and third quadrant. Its slope is positive in the first quadrant which determines its passive nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "The maximum Voltage across the capacitor Vc(t)=Vo(1- e-t) is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vo",
            "b) 2Vo",
            "c) 3Vo",
            "d) -Vo"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During resonance condition XL=Xc. The value of the resonant frequency is 1÷√LC=1÷√4=.5 rad/sec. The Voltage across the capacitor and inductor becomes equal."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the coefficient of coupling for the tightly coupled coils.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The steady state value is obtained at t=∞. The value of x(t) at t=∞ is 7e-∞=4(0)=0. The term e-9t is an exponentially decaying function."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "The maximum current in the inductor IL(t)=Io(1 – e-t/α) is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Io e-t/α",
            "b) Io",
            "c) 2Io",
            "d) -Io"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Vc(t)=Vo(1- e-t) is Vo is the transient equation of the capacitor Voltage. At the steady state (t=∞) Vc(t)=Vo(1- e-∞) is Vo. The maximum Voltage across the capacitor is Vo."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "20 V, 10 A, 10 rpm separately excited dc motor with armature resistance (Ra) equal to .8 ohms.  Calculate back emf developed in the motor when it operates on the full load. (Assume rotational losses are neglected)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12 V",
            "b) 14 V",
            "c) 13 V",
            "d) 11 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The coefficient of coupling expresses how the two coils are magnetically coupled. It is mathematically represented as K=M÷√L1.L2. For tightly coupled coils, the value of the mutual inductance is √L1.L2. The value of the coefficient of coupling is 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "Speed of DC shunt motor is directly proportional to___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eb",
            "b) Φ",
            "c) Vt",
            "d) Ia.Ra"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The IL(t)=Io(1 – e-t/α)  is Io is the transient equation of the inductor current. At the steady state (t=∞) IL(t)=Io(1- e-∞) is Io. The maximum current in the inductor is Io."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the angular acceleration of the DC shunt motor using the given data: J = 1 kg-m2, load torque = 1 N-m, motor torque = 2 N-m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 rad/s2",
            "b) 2 rad/s2",
            "c) 3 rad/s2",
            "d) 5 rad/s2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Back emf developed in the motor can be calculated using the relation Eb = Vt – I×Ra. In question, it is asking for a full load. 20 V is terminal Voltage it is fixed so Eb = 20-10×.8 = 12 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "Calculate the quality factor for the R-L circuit if R=16 Ω and XL=8 Ω with supply frequency is 1 rad/sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 0",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The back e.m.f in case of DC shunt motor is Eb=Vt-Ia.Ra. The speed in DC shunt motor is\nEb÷Kv. The speed is directly proportional to Eb."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "Calculate the equivalent resistance when two armature resistances are connected in parallel of values 6 Ω, 3 Ω.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 Ω",
            "b) 2 Ω",
            "c) 4 Ω",
            "d) 7 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Using the dynamic equation of motor J×(angular acceleration) = Motor torque – Load torque: 1×(angular acceleration) = 2-1=1, angular acceleration=1 rad/s2."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "Calculate the quality factor for the R-C circuit if R=1 Ω and C=1 F.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The quality factor is defined as the ratio of the reactive power to the active power consumed. The resistor always absorbs active power and inductor absorbs the reactive power. ΩL=8, L=8 Henry and quality factor=R÷L=16÷8=2."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Dynamic braking requires a strong _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetic field",
            "b) Electrostatic field",
            "c) Nuclear field",
            "d) Gravitational field"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dynamic braking requires a strong magnetic field to convert energy from the magnetic domain into the electrical domain. The kinetic energy is wasted at a higher rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "At the starting, the field is very strong but it decreases with time because of the ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduction in armature current",
            "b) Increase in armature current",
            "c) Reduction in speed",
            "d) Increase in speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In series DC machine, the field winding is in series with the armature winding. The armature current flows through the field winding. F=NIa=R∅. Ia∝∅."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "Calculate the time period of the waveform x(t)=1cot(πt+7π).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 sec",
            "b) 1 sec",
            "c) 3 sec",
            "d) 5 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For faster braking, the series field is separated from the armature circuit. The series field is excited by a different voltage source."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "In dynamic braking, DC series motor behaves as a ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Separately excited motor",
            "b) Transformer",
            "c) Induction motor",
            "d) Thyristor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At the starting, the field is very strong but it decreases with time because of the reduction in armature current. ∅∝Ia.\t"
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "Calculate the flux produced by the DC series field winding using the following data: Ia=5 A, N=23, R=23.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 Wb",
            "b) 6 Wb",
            "c) 9 Wb",
            "d) 8 Wb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The fundamental time period of the cot wave is π. The time period of x(t) is a π÷π=1 sec. The time period is independent of phase shifting and time shifting."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "The shape of the speed-armature current characteristics in DC series motor are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hyperbolic",
            "b) Parabola",
            "c) Circle",
            "d) Ellipse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In dynamic braking, DC series motor behaves as a separately excited motor as the motor armature is disconnected from the source and connected across resistance RB."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "The shape of the speed-torque current characteristics in DC series motor are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rectangular Hyperbolic",
            "b) Parabola",
            "c) Circle",
            "d) Ellipse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In DC series motor, field windings are connected in series with the armature circuit. F=NIa=R∅. Ia∝∅. ∅=F÷R=5 wb."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "DC series motors are used where the high ________ torque is required.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum",
            "b) Minimum",
            "c) Starting",
            "d) Stalling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The shape of the speed-armature current characteristics in DC series motor is hyperbolic. The motor equation is Eb=Vt-IaRa=Km∅ωm. N=(Vt/KmIa)-Ra/Km. N∝1÷Ia."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "The shape of the current-torque current characteristics in DC series motor is a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rectangular Hyperbolic",
            "b) Parabola",
            "c) Circle",
            "d) Ellipse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The shape of the speed-torque characteristics in the DC series motor is a rectangular hyperbola. The motor equation is Eb=Vt-IaRa=Km∅ωm. N=(Vt/KmIa)-Ra/Km. Ia∝√T  .N∝1÷√T."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "Calculate the current in DC series field winding using the following data: Ia=3 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 A",
            "b) 2 A",
            "c) 3 A",
            "d) 6 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: DC series motors are used where the high starting torque is required. At starting the torque produced by DC series motor is very high. To start a motor torque should be greater than load torque."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "For a given torque, increasing diverter resistance of a DC series motor causes the ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) decrease in speed and less armature current",
            "b) decrease in speed but armature current remains the same",
            "c) increase in speed and more armature current",
            "d) increase in speed but armature current remains the same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The shape of the current-torque characteristics in the DC series motor is a parabola. The motor equation is Eb=Vt-IaRa=Km∅ωm. T=Km∅Ia. ∅∝Ia. T∝Ia2."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "The field diverter resistance for a DC series motor is kept ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High",
            "b) Low",
            "c) zero",
            "d) one"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In DC series motor, field windings are connected in series with the armature circuit. The armature current will also flow through the series winding. If=Ia=3 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "Plugging is suitable for __________ type loads.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravitational",
            "b) Electrostatic",
            "c) Weightless",
            "d) Leading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Plugging is suitable for gravitational type loads. It halts the motor operation. It can reverse the direction of rotation of the motor. It can hold the motor at zero speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "Torque developed in the motor is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) KmΦIa",
            "b) KmΦIa3",
            "c) 2KmΦIa",
            "d) KmΦIa2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In shunt DC machine, the field winding is in parallel with the armature winding. The armature current flows through the armature winding. IF∝∅∝Vt."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "Full form of TVR is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Terminal voltage reversal",
            "b) Total voltage reversal",
            "c) Terminal voltage redirect",
            "d) Total voltage reversal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During braking, a high current flows in the armature circuit. To limit the braking current a proper value of braking resistance should be selected."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "Calculate the current in DC shunt field winding using the following data: Ia=15 A, IL=21, R=22, N=484.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 A",
            "b) 2 A",
            "c) 7 A",
            "d) 6 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The torque developed in the motor is directly proportional to the flux, machine constant, armature current. It is mathematically represented as T= KmΦIa.\t"
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "Calculate the flux produced by the DC shunt field winding using the following data: Ia=5 A, IL=11, R=2, N=4.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 14 Wb",
            "b) 12 Wb",
            "c) 17 Wb",
            "d) 18 Wb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: TVR stands for terminal voltage reversal. It is one of the methods of countercurrent braking of the DC shunt motor. It halts the motor rapidly and reverses its direction of rotation."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "The shape of the speed-armature current characteristics in DC shunt motor is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hyperbolic",
            "b) Parabola",
            "c) Negative slope linear line",
            "d) Ellipse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In DC shunt motor, field windings are connected in parallel with the armature circuit. IF=IL-Ia=11-5=6 A. Motor current is the sum of field and armature current."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "The shape of the speed-torque characteristics in DC shunt motor is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rectangular Hyperbolic",
            "b) Whole x-y plane",
            "c) Circle",
            "d) Ellipse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In DC shunt motor, field windings are connected in parallel with the armature circuit. IF=IL-Ia=11-5=6 A. F=NIF=R∅. IF∝∅. ∅=F÷R=12 wb."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "DC shunt motors are used where the high _________ is required.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Starting torque",
            "b) Maximum torque",
            "c) Minimum torque",
            "d) Breakdown torque"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The shape of the speed-armature current characteristics in DC shunt motor is negative slope linear line. The motor equation is Eb=Vt-IaRa=Km∅ωm. N=(Vt-IRa)/Km. N vs Ia is a negative slope line with slope = -Ra/Km."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "The shape of the current-torque characteristics in DC shunt motor is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rectangular Hyperbola",
            "b) Parabola",
            "c) Straight line",
            "d) Ellipse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The shape of the speed-torque characteristics in the DC shunt motor is a rectangular hyperbola. The motor equation is Eb=Vt-IaRa=Km∅ωm. N=(Vt/KmIa)-Ra/Km. Ia∝√T  .N∝1÷√T."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "The relationship between the torque(T) and power(P) developed in the DC shunt motor is ___________ (Neglecting all the losses)",
        "Options": [
            "a) T ∝ √P",
            "b) T ∝ P2",
            "c) T ∝ ∛P",
            "d) T ∝ P"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: DC series motors are used where the high starting torque is required. At starting the torque produced by DC series motor is very high. "
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "The value of current at time of starting is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Very low",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The shape of the current-torque characteristics in the DC shunt motor is a straight line. The motor equation is Eb=Vt-IaRa=Km∅ωm. T=Km∅Ia. ∅∝If. Torque ∝ Ia."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Calculate the bandwidth in series RLC circuit if the frequency is 20 Hz and the quality factor is 5.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 Hz",
            "b) 4 Hz",
            "c) 6 Hz",
            "d) 8 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The torque developed in the DC shunt motor is the ratio of power developed and angular\nspeed of the motor. T=EbIa÷ωm=P÷ωm. T ∝ P."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "Power input to an induction motor is given by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3VpIpcosΦ",
            "b) 2VpIpcosΦ",
            "c) VpIpcosΦ",
            "d) 5VpIpcosΦ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Power input to a 3-Φ induction motor is 3VpIpcosΦ. The power remains the same for Delta and star connection. The power is constant and has no vibrations."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "For motoring mode, the phase angle between the stator phase voltage and stator phase current should be _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) < 90°",
            "b) > 90°",
            "c) < 40°",
            "d) 180°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For motoring mode, the phase angle between the stator phase voltage and stator phase current should be < 90°. The rotor magnetic field tries to catch up the stator magnetic field."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "The relative speed between the stator magnetic field and rotor in the induction motor is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ns",
            "b) Ns-Nr",
            "c) Ns+Nr",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In induction motor rotor tries to catch up the stator magnetic field in order to satisfy Lenz law. Effect opposes the cause. Stator magnetic field rotates at the speed of synchronous speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "The relative speed between the stator magnetic field and rotor in the synchronous generator is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ns",
            "b) Ns-Nr",
            "c) Ns+Nr",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In synchronous generator rotor and stator magnetic field rotates at speed of synchronous speed in order to produce the steady state torque. "
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "The relative speed between the stator magnetic field and stator in the induction motor is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ns",
            "b) Ns-Nr",
            "c) Ns+Nr",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Induction motor stator magnetic field rotates at the speed of synchronous speed. The stator is made up of Silicon steel and remains at rest. The relative speed is Ns-0 = Ns."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "The relative speed between the rotor and stator in the induction motor is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nr",
            "b) Ns-Nr",
            "c) Ns+Nr",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Induction motor rotor tries to catch up the stator magnetic field in order to satisfy Lenz law. Effect opposes the cause. Stator remains at rest. The relative speed is Nr-0=Nr."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "What will happen if we increase the air gap in the induction motor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Power factor will reduce",
            "b) Power factor will increase",
            "c) Reduction in harmonics",
            "d) Speed will increase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If we increase the air gap in the induction motor, the machine will draw more magnetizing current to maintain flux in the air gap. The power factor of the machine will reduce."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "The ratio of the rotor copper loss and air gap power is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) s",
            "b) 1-s",
            "c) 1+s",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ratio of the rotor copper loss and air gap power is s. The air gap power in the induction motor is Pg and the rotor copper loss is s×Pg. The ratio is s."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "Magnetizing current in the induction motor is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) more than the transformer",
            "b) equal as a transformer",
            "c) less than the transformer",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The magnetizing current in the induction motor is (23-25)% of the full load current. The magnetizing current in the transformer is 3-5% of the full load."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "What is the speed of the 6th order time harmonics in the induction motor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ns",
            "b) Ns/6",
            "c) 6×Ns",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The single-phase induction motor is not self-starting because of the equal and opposite forward & backward magnetic field. The net torque developed is zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "What is the speed of the 11th order harmonics in the induction motor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ns",
            "b) Ns/11",
            "c) 2×Ns",
            "d) Nr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The time harmonics are present in the supply voltage. The speed of the 6th order time harmonics in the induction motor is Ns/6. "
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "A 3 – phase, 4 pole IM is supplied from a 40 Hz source. Calculate rotor frequency when the rotor runs 100 rpm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35 Hz",
            "b) 36.6 Hz",
            "c) 9 Hz",
            "d) 8 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The speed of the 6k±1 is Ns÷6k±1. The speed of the 11th order time harmonics in the induction motor is Ns/11. "
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "Calculate the three-phase power using the following data: Vp=23 V, Ip=23 A, ∅=60.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 793.5 W",
            "b) 790 W",
            "c) 792 W",
            "d) 791 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The slip of the induction motor can be calculated using the relation s = Ns-Nr÷ Ns. Ns=120F÷P=1200 rpm. The value of slip is .91. The rotor frequency is 36.6 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "Choose the Induction motor with peak speed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 Pole",
            "b) 12 Pole",
            "c) 14 Pole",
            "d) 16 Pole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The order of the circuit is the number of memory/storing elements which are non-separable present in the circuit. The examples of memory elements are capacitor, inductor."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "Which starting method is the best method in Induction motor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct online starting",
            "b) Autotransformer starting",
            "c) Reactance starting",
            "d) Star-Delta starting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lamination thickness basically depends upon the frequency. The rotor frequency is s×f where f is stator supply frequency. The rotor laminations are thicker than stator laminations because rotor frequency is less."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "Induction motor is analogous to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transformer",
            "b) DC machine",
            "c) Synchronous motor",
            "d) Synchronous generator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Synchronous speed of Induction motor is Ns=120×f÷P. Ns∝(1÷P). The synchronous speed is inversely proportional to the pole. The maximum speed will be achieved with a minimum number of poles."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "Which type of Induction motor is best for pole changing method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SCIM",
            "b) WRIM",
            "c) Single-phase IM",
            "d) Linear IM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Star-Delta starting method is one of the best methods for the starting of the Induction motor. This method is cheaper and the line current in the star is 1÷3 times of in delta connection."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "_________ motor operates at high power factor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Capacitor start",
            "b) Capacitor run",
            "c) Shaded pole",
            "d) Reluctance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Induction motor is analogous to the transformer. It is also known as a rotating transformer. Both works on the principle of electromagnetic induction."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "The use of the capacitor banks in the 3-phase Induction motor is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To increase the power factor",
            "b) To decrease the speed",
            "c) To increase the speed",
            "d) To decrease the power factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pole changing method is used to control the speed of Induction motor. It is only applicable for SCIM because SCIM rotor is made up of aluminum, copper bars."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "The concept of the slip is used in  ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Synchronous machine",
            "b) Induction machine",
            "c) DC machine",
            "d) Transformer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the capacitor run, the capacitor is permanently connected with auxiliary windings. The capacitor is used for reactive power compensation. It improves the power factor of the machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "Which type of Induction motor is best for e.m.f injection method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SCIM",
            "b) WRIM",
            "c) Single-phase IM",
            "d) Linear IM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Capacitor banks are used with 3-phase Induction motor in order to improve the power factor of the machine. The inductor motor generally operates with .6-.8 power factor range."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "The slots used in the Induction motor are  ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Semi-closed",
            "b) Closed",
            "c) Vacuum",
            "d) Open"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The slip in the Induction motor is s = Ns-Nr÷ Ns. The slip existence is due to the relative speed between the stator magnetic field and rotor."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "The slots used in the Synchronous machines are  ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Closed",
            "b) Semi-open",
            "c) Vacuum",
            "d) Open"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: E.M.F injection method is used to control the speed of Induction motor. It is only applicable for WRIM because WRIM rotor consists of copper windings connected in star connection. The external e.m.f can be connected with it using the slip rings."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "The unbalanced set of 3-phase voltages causes ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Positive sequence current",
            "b) Negative sequence current",
            "c) Zero sequence current",
            "d) Half sequence current"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slots used in the Induction motor are semi-closed. Open slots are used in the synchronous machine. Semi-closed slots have moderate air gap and lesser flux leakage."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "The ratio of the rotor gross power and air gap power is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) s",
            "b) 1-s",
            "c) 1+s",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The slots used in the Synchronous machine are open. Open slots have higher air gap and minimum flux leakage. The maximum power transfer capability increase due to a decrease in the leakage reactance."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the classes of insulating material in electrical machines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Γ, A, E, F, H, C",
            "b) Γ, E, B, F, H, C",
            "c) A, E, B, F, H, C",
            "d) Γ, A, E, F, C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Iron losses consist of eddy current and hysteresis losses. These are constant losses. Iron losses are independent of the load current. The copper losses are variable losses."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "Cooling air travels 10 m distance in 5 sec from point A to point B. Calculate the velocity of the cooling air.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 m/s",
            "b) 4 m/s",
            "c) 6 m/s",
            "d) 10 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Depending upon the temperature limits, insulating materials are classified into seven classes Γ, A, E, B, F, H, C. The insulation has the lowest temperature limit."
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "Calculate the heating time constant of the machine if the thermal capacity (c) of the machine is 24 watts/℃ and heat dissipation constant value (D) is 3 watts/℃.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8 sec",
            "b) 7 sec",
            "c) 6 sec",
            "d) 9 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The velocity of the cooling air can be calculated using the ratio of displacement and time. The value of the displacement is 10 m. The value of the velocity is 10÷5=2 sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "Inadequate rating of the equipment can  ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase the speed",
            "b) Decrease the speed",
            "c) Damage the winding",
            "d) Increase the efficiency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The heating time constant of the machine is the ratio of the thermal capacity of the machine and heat dissipation constant value. Τ = c÷D=24÷3 = 8 sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "What is heating time constant of the machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The ratio of the thermal capacity and heat dissipation constant value",
            "b) The ratio of the thermal capacity and heat dissipation constant value",
            "c) The ratio of the thermal capacity and heat dissipation constant value",
            "d) The ratio of the thermal capacity and heat dissipation constant value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inadequate rating of the equipment can damage the winding and stops the machine operation. The windings can burn out."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "A circuit consists of two 7 F capacitors connected in series and 12 H inductor. Determine the order of the circuit.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 0",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The heating time constant of the machine is the ratio of the thermal capacity of the machine and heat dissipation constant value. Τ = c÷D. It has a unit of second."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "Calculate the steady state temperature value for T(t)=1.5(1-e-17t).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5",
            "b) 4.8",
            "c) 3.9",
            "d) 2.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The inadequate rating of the equipment can damage the winding and halt the machine operation. The windings can burn out and lead to the breakdown of the machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "Calculate the quality factor for the R-C circuit connected in the cooling system if R=1 Ω and C=10 F.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1",
            "b) 0.2",
            "c) 0.3",
            "d) 0.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The order of the circuit is the number of memory/storing elements which are non-separable present in the circuit. In mathematics, the order is defined as the highest order derivate in the differential equation. The order of the circuit is 2 because two 7 F capacitors combine to form a single capacitor."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "Calculate the heat absorbed by a 3 Ω resistor when 6 V is applied across it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12 W",
            "b) 10 W",
            "c) 8 W",
            "d) 11 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The steady state temperature value is obtained at t=∞. The value of T(t) at t=∞ is 1.5(1-e-∞)=1.5(1-0)=1.5. The term e-17t is an exponentially decaying function."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "What is the unit of power?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Joule/sec",
            "b) Joule/sec2",
            "c) Joule/sec3",
            "d) Joule/sec4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The quality factor is defined as the ratio of the reactive power to the active power consumed. The resistor always absorbs active power and capacitor absorbs the reactive power. Quality factor=1÷RC=1÷10=.1."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "Convert 20 ℃ into Fahrenheit.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 68 ℉",
            "b) 58 ℉",
            "c) 78 ℉",
            "d) 48 ℉"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resistor always absorbs active power and dissipates in the form of the heat. Power absorbed by a 3 Ω resistor is 6×6÷3=12 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "Convert 50℉ into Celsius.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 ℃",
            "b) 10 ℃",
            "c) 30 ℃",
            "d) 40 ℃"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The power is defined as the rate at which work is done. The ratio of energy and time is power. It is expressed in Watt or Joule/sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Which duty cycle has on load and off-loads period?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intermittent duty",
            "b) Short time duty",
            "c) Continuous duty with constant load",
            "d) Continuous duty with variable load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Intermittent duty cycle has frequent on load and off-loads period. The on-load period and off-loads periods are too short to achieve steady-state thermal condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "Which motor is preferred for Jaw crushers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) WRIM",
            "b) SCIM",
            "c) Belt slip ring IM",
            "d) DC shunt motor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Belt slip ring IM is preferred for the operation of Jaw crushers. A high starting is provided by the Belt ring IM. Slip rings are used to add external resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "Which starting method is the worst method in Induction motor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct online starting",
            "b) Autotransformer starting",
            "c) Reactance starting",
            "d) Star-Delta starting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Belt Conveyors can provide continuous-flow transportation. The amount of material transported on a conveyor system depends upon belt speed, belt width."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "Induction motor is also known as  __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency changer",
            "b) Frequency remover",
            "c) Time period remover",
            "d) DC machine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Reactance starting method is the worst method in an Induction motor. It uses the concept of the potential divider. The losses are very high in case of Reactance starting method."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "1800 second rated motors are used for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heavy duty cranes",
            "b) Light duty cranes",
            "c) Medium duty cranes",
            "d) Intermittent duty cranes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Induction motor is also known as frequency changer. The stator frequency can be changed using the slip concept. The rotor frequency of IM is slip×(stator frequency)."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "Calculate the frequency of the rotor side of the IM if the value of slip is 0.34 and the supply frequency is 70 Hz.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 23.8 Hz",
            "b) 22.7 Hz",
            "c) 24.5 Hz",
            "d) 23.1 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cranes are used to carry or lift the heavy loads. The capacity of a Crane is expressed in terms of tonnes. 1 tonne is equal to 1000 Kg."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "Calculate the frequency of the stator side of the IM if the value of slip is 0.04 and rotor frequency is 2 Hz.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 Hz",
            "b) 49 Hz",
            "c) 45 Hz",
            "d) 51 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Medium duty crane motor is used to develop high starting torque. They provide the output for a specified interval of time without exceeding a specified temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "Calculate the resonant frequency if the values of the capacitor and inductor are 4 F and 4 H.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .25 rad/sec",
            "b) .26 rad/sec",
            "c) .28 rad/sec",
            "d) .29 rad/sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The frequency of the rotor side is low as compared to supply frequency. The rotor frequency is slip×(supply frequency)=.34×70=23.8 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the angular acceleration of the Heavy duty crane using the given data: J = 5 kg-m2, load torque = 30 N-m, motor torque = 80 N-m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 rad/s2",
            "b) 20 rad/s2",
            "c) 30 rad/s2",
            "d) 50 rad/s2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The frequency of the stator side is high as compared to the rotor side. The stator frequency is (rotor frequency) ÷ slip = 2÷.04 = 50 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the angular acceleration of the machine using the given data: J = .541 kg-m2, load torque = 10 N-m, motor torque = 2 N-m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45 rad/s2",
            "b) The machine will fail to start",
            "c) 30 rad/s2",
            "d) 51 rad/s2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During resonance condition XL=Xc. The value of the resonant frequency is 1÷√LC=1÷√16=.25 rad/sec. The voltage across the capacitor and inductor becomes equal."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "The direction of the single-phase IM can be reversed by using which one of the method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By interchanging the supply terminals",
            "b) By removing the capacitor",
            "c) By changing the direction of auxiliary winding current",
            "d) By removing the main winding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Using the dynamic equation of motor J×(angular acceleration) = Motor torque – Load torque: 5×(angular acceleration) = 80-30=50, angular acceleration=10 rad/s2."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "Which motor is preferred for overhead traveling cranes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intermittent periodic motor",
            "b) Continuous duty motor",
            "c) Slow speed duty motor",
            "d) Short time rated motor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Using the dynamic equation of motor J×(angular acceleration) = Motor torque – Load torque: .541×(angular acceleration) = 2-10=-8, angular acceleration=-14.78 rad/s2. The load torque is greater than the motor torque. The motor will fail to start."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "Which one of the following motor is a 1-Φ AC motor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Synchronous motor",
            "b) Series motor",
            "c) Shunt motor",
            "d) Capacitor run"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Capacitor run motor is a 1-Φ AC motor. The capacitor is used to provide a 90° phase difference between the currents of main and auxiliary winding."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "450-seconds rated motor is preferable for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Light duty cranes",
            "b) Medium duty cranes",
            "c) Intermittent duty cranes",
            "d) Heavy duty cranes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The current rating of the Induction motor depends upon the cross-section area of the conductors. Resistance ∝ 1÷Area, I ∝Area."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Calculate the 3-∅ power developed in the IM using the following data: VL=20 V, IL=5 A, cosΦ=.8.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 138.56 W",
            "b) 128.41 W",
            "c) 163.78 W",
            "d) 177.59 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The voltage rating of the IM depends upon the insulation level. The insulation level is also decided on the basis of the over-voltages."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "Calculate mark to space ratio if the system is on for 20 sec and off for 3 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.66",
            "b) 4.48",
            "c) 8.2",
            "d) 5.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Light duty cranes are used in power plants, compressor plants. 450-seconds rated motor is preferable for light-duty cranes. They can safely operate for 450-seconds without exceeding the specified temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "Calculate the average power dissipated if the value of the duty cycle is .5 and Pmax=12 W.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 W",
            "b) 5 W",
            "c) 4 W",
            "d) 3 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The power developed in the IM is √3VLILcos∅. The power is independent of time and frequency. P=√3VLILcos∅=√3×20×5×.8=138.56 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "Full form of PWM.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulse width modulation",
            "b) Pulse run modulation",
            "c) Power width modulation",
            "d) Pulse wisdom mode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The moment of inertia is taken as the sum of the product of the mass of each particle with the square of their distance from the axis of the rotation. The unit of the moment of inertia is kg×m2=kgm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "What is the correct relationship between the phase voltage and line voltage in Delta connection with the positive sequence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) VL=Vp",
            "b) VL=√3Vp",
            "c) VL=√2Vp",
            "d) IL=√2Ip"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mark to space ratio is Ton÷Toff. It is the ratio of time for which the system is active and the time for which is inactive. M = Ton÷Toff=20÷3=6.66."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "What is the relationship between line and phase current in Star connection with the positive sequence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) VL=Vp",
            "b) VL=√9Vp",
            "c) VL=√2Vp",
            "d) IL=Ip"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The average power dissipated can be calculated using the relation Pavg=D×Pmax. The value of the average power is .5×12=6 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Choose the correct relationship in delta connection with the positive sequence.",
        "Options": [
            "a) IL=Ip",
            "b) VL=√3Vp",
            "c) VL=Vp",
            "d) IL=√3Ip"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PWM stands for pulse width modulation. This technique is used to alter the voltage level of the output of the inverter. We can control the voltage level using the PWM technique."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "Choose the correct relationship in Star connection with the positive sequence.",
        "Options": [
            "a) VL=Vp",
            "b) VL=√3Vp",
            "c) VL=√2Vp",
            "d) IL=√3Ip"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the delta connection line voltage is the same as the phase voltage. The line current is √3 times of the phase current and leads by 30°."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "Calculate the 3-∅ power developed in the IM connected in star using the following data: Vp=7 V, IL=7 A, cosΦ=.6.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 88.5 W",
            "b) 88.4 W",
            "c) 88.8 W",
            "d) 88.2 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the star connection line current is the same as the phase current. The line voltage is √3 times of the phase voltage and leads by 30°."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "Calculate the load stress if the value of force is 20 N and the area of cross-section is 2 m2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 N/m2",
            "b) 20 N/m2",
            "c) 30 N/m2",
            "d) 40 N/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hooke’s law is only applicable within the elastic limit. It states that within the elastic limit the strain is directly proportional to the stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "What is the effect of impurities on elasticity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It will increase",
            "b) Remains the same",
            "c) It will decrease",
            "d) It will slightly increase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The stress is defined as the ratio of the internal restoring force and area of the cross-section. Stress=Fres÷A=20÷2=10 N/m2."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the types of Stress?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Longitudinal stress, Volume stress, Tangential stress",
            "b) Longitudinal stress, Volume stress",
            "c) Longitudinal stress, Lateral stress, Tangential stress",
            "d) Longitudinal stress, Shear stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Young modulus of elasticity is slightly increased by the addition of impurities. The intermolecular forces inside the wire effectively increase by impurity due to this external force can be easily opposed."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "The relationship between Young’s modulus (Y), Bulk modulus (K) and Poisson’s ratio (μ) is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Y=K(1-2μ)",
            "b) Y=3K(1-2μ)",
            "c) Y=5K(1-2μ)",
            "d) Y=4K(1-8μ)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are three types of stress that are Longitudinal stress, Volume stress, Tangential or Shear stress. Stress is the ratio of restoring force and cross-section area."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "Calculate the work done in stretching the wire of volume=22 m3 and the values of stress and strain are 2 N/m2 and 4.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 66 J",
            "b) 44 J",
            "c) 22 J",
            "d) 88 J"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The relationship between Young’s modulus (Y), Bulk modulus (K) and Poisson’s ratio (μ) is Y=3K(1-2μ). The Young modulus of elasticity is defined as the ratio of Longitudinal stress and Longitudinal strain."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "_________ motor operates at low power factor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Capacitor run",
            "b) Capacitor start",
            "c) Shaded pole",
            "d) Reluctance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The work done in stretching a wire is .5×Stress×Strain×Volume. The value of the work done is .5×22×4×2=88 J."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "Calculate the compensator rating required for cos(Φ)=.7.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.71 P.U",
            "b) 0.21 P.U",
            "c) 0.47 P.U",
            "d) 0.12 P.U"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Plasticity is the ability of the material to deform without breaking. Plastic deformation occurs in metal forming processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "Full form of SPWM.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sinusoidal pulse width modulation",
            "b) State per width modulation",
            "c) State pulse width modulation",
            "d) Sinusoidal per width modulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shaded pole motors operate at a low power factor. There is a weak magnetic field develops in the case of Shaded pole motor. It is a single-phase AC Induction motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "Which harmonic is not present in 3-Φ fully controlled rectifier?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3rd harmonic",
            "b) 5th harmonic",
            "c) 7th harmonic",
            "d) 11th harmonic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The compensator rating can be calculated using the relation QP.U=√1-cos2(∅)=√1-.49=.71. This per unit value VAR compensator is required to improve the power factor of the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "Lowest order harmonic present in 3-Φ fully controlled rectifier is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5th",
            "b) 7th",
            "c) 3rd",
            "d) 2nd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SPWM stands for sinusoidal pulse width modulation. SPWM is a high-frequency PWM technique. This technique is used to achieve variable voltage level."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the circular hollow disk having a mass of 2 kg and an internal radius of 5 m and an external radius of 10 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 125 kgm2",
            "b) 127 kgm2",
            "c) 122 kgm2",
            "d) 123 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Triplen harmonics are absent in the case of 3-phase fully controlled rectifier. Because of the absence of triplen harmonics THD of the rectifier 31%."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "Calculate the mass of the solid cylinder having a mass of 4 kgm2 and radius of 4 m & length of 12 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 64 kgm2",
            "b) 68 kgm2",
            "c) 67 kgm2",
            "d) 69 kgm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Only 6k±1 order harmonics are present in 3-Φ fully controlled rectifier. The lowest order harmonic is 5th harmonic for k=1. Third order harmonics are absent in 3-Φ fully controlled rectifier."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "Calculate the moment of inertia of the flywheel of mass 45 kg and radius of 2 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 185 kg-m2",
            "b) 180 kg-m2",
            "c) 175 kg-m2",
            "d) 170 kg-m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The moment of inertia of the flywheel can be calculated using the formula I=M(R2). The mass of flywheel and radius is given. I=(45)×(2)2=180 kg-m2. It depends upon the orientation of the rotational axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the types of Longitudinal stress?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tensile stress, Compressive stress",
            "b) Tensile stress, Volume stress",
            "c) Tensile stress, Shear stress",
            "d) Tensile stress, Lateral stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electric motor and control system are the basic elements of the electric drive. The electric drive uses the control system methods to control the speed and torque of the motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "Which type of motor is used for milling and grinding operations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SCIM",
            "b) WRIM",
            "c) Split phase",
            "d) Reluctance motor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Capacitor start capacitor run single-phase Induction motor is used in ceiling fan. The motor operation is silent and non-vibrational. It provides a high starting torque."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "Calculate the work done in stretching the wire of length=2 m and the values of stress and strain are 16 N/m2 and 24.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1566 J",
            "b) 1644 J",
            "c) 1522 J",
            "d) 1536 J"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Longitudinal stress is one the type of stress. Longitudinal stress is of two types. It consists of Tensile stress and Compressive stress. It has a unit of N/m2."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "Which type of force phenomenon is used in Sugar mills?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Centripetal force",
            "b) Centrifugal force",
            "c) Electrostatic force",
            "d) Nuclear forces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Squirrel cage Induction motor is used for milling and grinding operations. SCIM has a rigid structure and high tolerating capability. It provides good running characteristics."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "The Speed control by variation of field flux results in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant torque drive",
            "b) zero speed",
            "c) Variable torque drive",
            "d) Variable power drive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The work done in stretching a wire is .5×Stress×Strain×Volume. The value of the work done is .5×8×16×24=1536 J. The volume of wire is 2×2×2=8 m3."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "Calculate the compensator rating required for sin(Φ)=.8.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.9 P.U",
            "b) 0.8 P.U",
            "c) 0.7 P.U",
            "d) 0.2 P.U"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In sugar mills, a centrifugal is used to separate out sugar crystals from the syrup by the action of centrifugal forces. Centrifugal force acts away from the center."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "Calculate the heating time constant of the machine if the thermal capacity (c) of the machine is 16 watts/℃ and heat dissipation constant value (D) is 4 watts/℃.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 sec",
            "b) 7 sec",
            "c) 4 sec",
            "d) 9 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Field flux control method is used to achieve the speed above the base speed. It provides constant power drive and variable torque drive."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "Calculate the heat absorbed by a 20 Ω resistor when 40 V is applied across it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 120 W",
            "b) 100 W",
            "c) 80 W",
            "d) 110 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The compensator rating can be calculated using the relation QP.U=√1-cos2(∅)=sin(∅)=.8. This per unit value VAR compensator is required to improve the power factor of the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "Full form of VFD is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variable frequency drive",
            "b) Variable force drive",
            "c) Value frequency drive",
            "d) Variable force diverter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The heating time constant of the machine is the ratio of the thermal capacity of the machine and heat dissipation constant value. τ = c÷D = 16÷4 = 4 sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "What is Load Equalisation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process of smoothing the fluctuating load",
            "b) Process of removing the load",
            "c) Process of changing the voltage level",
            "d) Process of changing the speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The resistor always absorbs active power and dissipates in the form of the heat. Power absorbed by a 20 Ω resistor is 40×40÷20=80 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "Which device is used to store the energy during load equalization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flywheel",
            "b) Capacitor",
            "c) Inductor",
            "d) Resistor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: VFD stands for variable frequency drive. It is a controller for AC or DC motors to achieve the desired speed. It can perform the four quadrant operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "Which test is used to determine the conditions where electric motors are being used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermography",
            "b) Geography",
            "c) Seismography",
            "d) Anthropology"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thermography is used to detect heat patterns. It uses an Infrared rays camera. This test is used to determine the conditions where electric motors are being used."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "What is the range of size of the motor (kW) for efficiency nearly equals to 90%?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15-150",
            "b) 0-2",
            "c) 3-15",
            "d) 150-250"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the size of the motor increases its speed decreases. The range of size of the motor (kW) for efficiency nearly equals to 90 % is 15-150. The efficiency increases as the size increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "Calculate the heat loss in the electric motor for time interval 0-5 sec using the following data: Ia=2 A, Ra=.8Ω.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 16 J-sec",
            "b) 14 J-sec",
            "c) 12 J-sec",
            "d) 10 J-sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The heat loss can be calculated using the Joule law of heating effect. The value of the heat loss is Ia2×Ra×t=4×4=16 J-sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "1 Btu/h is equal to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) .641",
            "b) .334",
            "c) .293",
            "d) .417"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: One British thermal unit is equal to .293 Watt. 1 Btu/h is the amount of energy requires to increase the temperature of one pound of water by 1℉."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "Overloading can be prevented using _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Over-current protection",
            "b) Speed protection",
            "c) Over frequency protection",
            "d) Oversize protection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Overloading can be prevented using over-current protection. It will detect the over-current and interrupt the supply. IDMT over-current relay can be used for the protection purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "Full form of IDMT is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inverse definite minimum time",
            "b) Inverter definite minimum time",
            "c) Inverter definite maximum time",
            "d) Insert definite minimum time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IDMT stands for Inverse definite minimum time over-current relay. It has both the characteristics of inverse over-current and definite time over-current relay."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "The most common cause of motor failure is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Overloading",
            "b) Low resistance",
            "c) Contamination",
            "d) Over-Heating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most common cause of motor failure is low resistance. Overheating, corrosion can damage the insulation of the windings which leads to low resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "Full form of THD is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Total harmonic diverter",
            "b) Total harmonic digital",
            "c) Total harmonic distortion",
            "d) Total harmonic discrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: THD stands for total harmonic distortion. It measures the harmonic distortion in the signal. According to IEEE-1992, only 5% of THD is valid."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "Calculate the compensator rating required for a sec(Φ)=1.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.64 P.U",
            "b) 0.21 P.U",
            "c) 0.57 P.U",
            "d) 0 P.U"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The compensator rating can be calculated using the relation QP.U=√1-cos2(∅)=0. This per unit value VAR compensator is required to improve the power factor of the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of Voltage ripple factor if the Form factor is 1.1.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45.8 %",
            "b) 46.2 %",
            "c) 47.5 %",
            "d) 49.9 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Voltage ripple factor measures the harmonics on the DC side of the converter. The value of voltage ripple factor is √F.F2-1=45.8 %. The form factor is Vr.m.s÷Vavg."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of THD if the distortion factor is .8.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 76 %",
            "b) 75 %",
            "c) 74 %",
            "d) 73 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: THD measures the harmonics distortion in the signal. The value of THD is √(1÷D)2-1=75 %. The value of the distortion factor is Ior.m.s÷IR.m.s."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "Full form of VRF.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Voltage ripple factor",
            "b) Voltage revert factor",
            "c) Volume ripple factor",
            "d) Volume revert factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Voltage ripple factor measures the harmonics on the DC side of the converter. The value of voltage ripple factor is √F.F2-1. The form factor is Vr.m.s÷Vavg."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "Second lowest order harmonic present in 3-Φ fully controlled rectifier is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5th",
            "b) 7th",
            "c) 3rd",
            "d) 2nd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only 6k±1 order harmonics are present in 3-Φ fully controlled rectifier. The second lowest order harmonic is 7th harmonic for k=1. Third order harmonics are absent in 3-Φ fully controlled rectifier."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "Electric motors are placed in __________ to protect them from dust and contamination.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enclosures",
            "b) Open environment",
            "c) Moisturizing environment",
            "d) Hot environment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electric motors are placed in enclosures to protect them from dust and contamination. There are seven most common types of enclosures. For example- Open Drip Proof."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "In Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier calculate the average value of the voltage if the supply is 23sin(50t).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7.32 V",
            "b) 8.32 V",
            "c) 9.32 V",
            "d) 7.60 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: RLE load is a current stiff load because of the presence of the inductor. The load current does not suddenly with a change in voltage. Inductor opposes the change of current."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "In Half-wave controlled rectifier calculate the average value of the voltage if the supply is 10sin(50t) and firing angle is 30°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.32 V",
            "b) 2.97 V",
            "c) 4.26 V",
            "d) 5.64 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier, the average value of the voltage is Vm÷π=23÷π=7.32 V. The diode will conduct only for the positive half cycle. The conduction period of the diode is π."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "Calculate the extinction angle in purely inductive load if the firing angle is π÷4.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 315°",
            "b) 145°",
            "c) 345°",
            "d) 285°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Half-wave controlled rectifier, the average value of the voltage is Vm(1+cos(∝))÷2π=10(1+cos(30°)÷6.28=2.97 V. The thyristor will conduct from ∝ to π."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "Calculate the conduction angle in purely inductive load if the firing angle is π÷2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 205°",
            "b) 175°",
            "c) 180°",
            "d) 195°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The extinction angle in the purely inductive load is 2π-∝=360°-45°=315°. The extinction angle is the angle at which current in the circuit becomes zero. The average value of the voltage in a purely inductive load is zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "In single phase RLE load, calculate the voltage across the thyristor when current decays to zero using the data: (Vs)r.m.s=220 V, f=40 Hz, R=1 Ω, E=90 V, β=230°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) -328.33 V",
            "b) -325.48 V",
            "c) -254.85 V",
            "d) -284.48 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The conduction angle in the purely inductive load is β-α=2(π-∝)=2(180°-90°). The conduction angle is the angle for which the current exists in the circuit. The average value of the voltage in a purely inductive load is zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "Calculate the displacement factor if the fundamental voltage is 24sin(140πt-240°) and fundamental current is 47sin(140πt-120°).",
        "Options": [
            "a) -0.5",
            "b) -0.7",
            "c) 0.9",
            "d) 0.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: RLE load is also known as DC motor load because the armature circuit consists of back e.m.f, inductive coils, and armature resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "Calculate the PIV for the Mid-point configuration of Full-wave rectifier if the peak value of the supply voltage is 311.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 622 V",
            "b) 620 V",
            "c) 624 V",
            "d) 626 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In single phase RLE load the voltage across the thyristor when current decays to zero VT=Vmsin(β)-E=220×√2sin(230°)-90=-328.33 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "Calculate the average value of the current through the thyristor in case of 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier if the value of the load current is 42 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 21 A",
            "b) 12 A",
            "c) 14 A",
            "d) 16 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The displacement factor is the cosine of the angle difference between the fundamental voltage and fundamental current. D.F=cos(120°)=-0.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Calculate the r.m.s value of the current through the thyristor in case of 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier if the value of the load current is 2 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.414 A",
            "b) 1.214 A",
            "c) 1.347 A",
            "d) 1.657 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The peak inverse voltage for the Mid-point configuration of Full wave rectifier is 2Vm=2×311=622 V. The peak inverse is the maximum negative voltage across the thyristor."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of THD value for 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 48.43 %",
            "b) 47.25 %",
            "c) 49.26 %",
            "d) 50.48 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The average value of the current through the thyristor in case of 1-∅ full wave bridge rectifier is Io÷2=21 A. Each thyristor conducts for 180°."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the Input power factor for 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier if the firing angle value is 45°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .65",
            "b) .64",
            "c) .61",
            "d) .63"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The r.m.s value of the current through the thyristor in case of 1-∅ full wave bridge rectifier is Io÷√2=√2 A=1.414 A. Each thyristor conducts for 180°."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the fundamental displacement factor for 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier if the firing angle value is 60°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .5",
            "b) .4",
            "c) .2",
            "d) .8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the distortion factor is .9. The value of THD value for 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier is √(1÷.9)2-1=48.43 %. THD measures the amount of harmonic distortion."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the fundamental displacement factor for 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter if the firing angle value is 20°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .82",
            "b) .98",
            "c) .74",
            "d) .26"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of the input power factor for 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier is .9cos(45°)=.63. The input power factor is a product of distortion factor and displacement factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "Calculate the output frequency for the two-pulse converter if the supply frequency is 20 Hz.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 Hz",
            "b) 20 Hz",
            "c) 60 Hz",
            "d) 90 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The output of a two-pulse converter consists of two pulses in one cycle. The output frequency of the two pulse converter is 2×supply frequency=2×20=40 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "Calculate the pulse number if the supply frequency is 2π and the output frequency is π÷3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The pulse number can be calculated using the ratio of input frequency to the output frequency. The value of pulse number (P) is 2π÷π÷3=6. It is a six-pulse converter."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "In 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier calculate the average value of the voltage if the supply is 400 V and firing angle is 15°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 521.2 V",
            "b) 522 V",
            "c) 523 V",
            "d) 524 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier, the average value of the voltage is 3Vml(cos(∝))÷π=3×400×√2(cos(15°))÷3.14=522 V. "
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the Input power factor for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier if the firing angle value is 70°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .32",
            "b) .38",
            "c) .31",
            "d) .33"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the input power factor for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier is .95cos(70°)=.32. The input power factor is a product of distortion factor and displacement factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of THD value for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 48.43 %",
            "b) 47.25 %",
            "c) 39.26 %",
            "d) 31 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of the distortion factor is .95. The value of THD value for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier is √(1÷.95)2-1=31 %. THD measures the amount of harmonic distortion."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "In 3-Φ Semi-controlled rectifier calculate the average value of the voltage if the supply is 440 V and firing angle is 22°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 571.5 V",
            "b) 572.8 V",
            "c) 548.3 V",
            "d) 524.1 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In 3-Φ Semi-controlled rectifier, the average value of the voltage is 3Vml(1+cos(∝))÷2π=3×440×√2(1+cos(22°))÷6.28=572.8 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "Calculate the circuit turn-off time for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier if the firing angle is 20° and supply frequency is 60 Hz.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8.8 msec",
            "b) 7.4 msec",
            "c) 10.1 msec",
            "d) 6.5 msec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The circuit turn-off time for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier is (240°-α)÷ω. The value of circuit turn-off time for ∝ < 60° is (240°-20°)÷6.28×60=10.1 msec."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "Calculate the circuit turn-off time for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier if the firing angle is 110° and supply frequency is 50 Hz.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.8 msec",
            "b) 5.2 msec",
            "c) 9.3 msec",
            "d) 8.7 msec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The circuit turn-off time for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier is (180°-α)÷ω;. The value of circuit turn-off time for ∝ ≥ 60° is (180°-110°)÷6.28×50=3.8 msec."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "Calculate peak-peak voltage if Vmax=80 V and Vmin=20 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60 V",
            "b) 50 V",
            "c) 70 V",
            "d) 10 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Peak-Peak voltage is equal to the difference between the maximum and minimum voltage. It is mathematically represented as Vp-p=Vmax-Vmin=80-20=60 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of Crest factor if Vpeak=12 V and Vr.m.s=24 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .2",
            "b) .3",
            "c) .4",
            "d) .5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of the crest factor is Vpeak÷Vr.m.s=12÷24=.5. It signifies the peak value is .5 times than the r.m.s value."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "Calculate the output voltage of the Buck converter if the supply voltage is 11 V and duty cycle value is .4.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.4 V",
            "b) 2.2 V",
            "c) 4.8 V",
            "d) 6.4 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The output voltage of the buck converter is Vo = Vin×(D)=11×.4=4.4 V. The value of the duty cycle is less than one which makes the Vo < Vin. The buck converter is used to step down the voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "Calculate the output voltage of the Boost converter if the supply voltage is 8 V and duty cycle value is .6.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 V",
            "b) 20 V",
            "c) 48 V",
            "d) 51 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The output voltage of the boost converter is Vo = Vin ÷ (1-D) = 8÷.4 = 20 V. The value of the duty cycle is less than one which makes the Vo > Vin as denominator value decreases and becomes less than one. The boost converter is used to step up the voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "Calculate the output voltage of the Buck-Boost converter if the supply voltage is 78 V and duty cycle value is .1.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7.2 V",
            "b) 4.5 V",
            "c) 8.6 V",
            "d) 5.1 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The output voltage of the buck-boost converter is Vo = D×Vin ÷ (1-D)=.1(78)÷.9=8.6 V. It can step up and step down the voltage depending upon the value of the duty cycle. If the value of the duty cycle is less than .5 it will work as a buck converter and for duty cycle greater than .5 it will work as a boost converter."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "An infinite bus-bar has _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant voltage",
            "b) Constant frequency",
            "c) Constant voltage and frequency",
            "d) constant speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Reluctance motors are singly-excited. Stator side of the motor is excited by an AC source. Due to excitation, a revolving magnetic field is a created and rotor rotates with the synchronous speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the Input power factor for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier if the firing angle value is 90°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) .2",
            "c) .3",
            "d) .4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Reluctance motor can operate on AC supply. It cannot operate on DC supply. Reluctance motors are singly-excited."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "Which of the following motor is used in recording instruments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reluctance motor",
            "b) Induction motor",
            "c) Synchronous motor",
            "d) DC motor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An infinite bus-bar has constant voltage and constant speed. It has many types like single bus-bar, double bus-bar. It is connected to the grid."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "Increasing the stator poles ___________ the speed of Reluctance motor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases",
            "b) Increases",
            "c) Remains the same",
            "d) Negative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the input power factor for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier is .95cos(90°)=0. The input power factor is a product of distortion factor and displacement factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "Calculate the circuit turn-off time for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier if the firing angle is 27° and supply frequency is 50 Hz.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11.8 msec",
            "b) 14.4 msec",
            "c) 16.1 msec",
            "d) 16.5 msec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Reluctance motor is used in recording instruments. It is used for many constant speed applications. The starting torque of the motor depends upon the rotor position."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "Calculate the circuit turn-off time for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier if the firing angle is 120° and supply frequency is 60 Hz.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.8 msec",
            "b) 3.2 msec",
            "c) 6.3 msec",
            "d) 2.7 msec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Increasing the stator poles decreases the speed of Reluctance motor. The rotating magnetic field is developed which rotates at the speed of Ns . Ns∝(1÷P)."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "Calculate peak-peak voltage if Vmax=180 V and Vmin=60 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 120 V",
            "b) 150 V",
            "c) 170 V",
            "d) 110 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The circuit turn-off time for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier is (240°-α)÷ω. The value of circuit turn-off time for ∝ < 60° is (240°-27°)÷6.28×50=11.8 msec."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of Crest factor if Vpeak=798 V and Vr.m.s=489 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.63",
            "b) 1.54",
            "c) 1.59",
            "d) 1.26"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The circuit turn-off time for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier is (180°-α)÷ω. The value of circuit turn-off time for ∝ ≥ 60° is (180°-120°)÷6.28×60=2.7 msec."
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "Reluctance motor operates at power factor of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) .8",
            "b) .2",
            "c) .3",
            "d) .9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Peak-Peak voltage is equal to the difference between the maximum and minimum voltage. It is mathematically represented as Vp-p=Vmax-Vmin=180-60=120 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "Calculate the reactive power in a 24.5 Ω resistor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 VAR",
            "b) 5 VAR",
            "c) 8 VAR",
            "d) 9 VAR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the crest factor is Vpeak÷Vr.m.s=798÷489=1.63 V. It signifies the peak value is 1.63 times than the r.m.s value."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the duty cycle if the system is on for 1 sec and off for 17 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .055",
            "b) .781",
            "c) .484",
            "d) .947"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Reluctance motor operates at a power factor of .8. The Reluctance motor works on the principle of an Induction motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "Calculate mark to space ratio if the system is on for 4 sec and off time is 9 sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .54",
            "b) .44",
            "c) .45",
            "d) .46"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resistor is a linear element. It only absorbs real power and dissipates it in the form of heat. The voltage and current are in the same phase in case of the resistor so the angle between V & I is 0°. Q = VIsin0 = 0 VAR."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the frequency if the inductive reactance is 60 Ω and the value of the inductor is 4 H.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.38 Hz",
            "b) 5.54 Hz",
            "c) 4.65 Hz",
            "d) 9.42 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Duty cycle is Ton÷Ttotal. It is the ratio of time for which the system is active and the time taken by the signal to complete one cycle. D = Ton÷Ttotal=1÷18=.055."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "BLDC motor is analogous to ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Permanent magnet synchronous motor",
            "b) DC motor",
            "c) Rotating Transformer",
            "d) Single-phase Induction motor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Hall effect sensor is used as the rotor position sensor for the BLDC motor. It is used to measure the strength of the magnetic field."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "The speed of a BLDC motor can be controlled by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Changing input DC voltage",
            "b) Changing temperature",
            "c) Changing wind direction",
            "d) Cannot be controlled"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In BLDC motor armature windings are placed on the stator side. It is more economical and less maintenance is required. Permanent magnets are placed on the rotor side."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "Due to low inertia, BLDC motors have __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faster acceleration",
            "b) Slower acceleration",
            "c) High-cost",
            "d) Low cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: BLDC motor is analogous to Permanent magnet synchronous motor. In BLDC motor armature windings are placed on the stator side. It is more economical and less maintenance is required. Permanent magnets are placed on the rotor side."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "Calculate the electrical angle for 6 pole machine. (θm represents mechanical angle)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4×θm",
            "b) 5×θm",
            "c) 2×θm",
            "d) 3×θm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The speed of a BLDC motor can be controlled by changing the input DC voltage or the current using PWM. It can be achievable by using a transistor and chopper."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the types of BLDC motor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unipolar, Bipolar",
            "b) Unipolar, PWM",
            "c) Bipolar, PWM",
            "d) Synchronous, Induction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The BLDC motor is used in low power application. They have many advantages like low cost, simplicity, reliability, good performance, long life."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "Calculate peak-peak voltage if Vmax=45 V and Vmin=45 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60 V",
            "b) 30 V",
            "c) 50 V",
            "d) 0 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Due to low inertia, BLDC motors have faster acceleration. BLDC motors have less weight. They can run at high speed than a conventional DC motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of Crest factor if Vpeak=141 V and Vr.m.s=100 V for sinusoidal voltage.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.41",
            "b) 2.38",
            "c) 4.42",
            "d) 5.58"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The electrical angle for 6 pole machine is 3×θm. One electrical angle is equal to 180° mechanical angle. θe=(P÷2)×θm."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "In the biomedical instruments like artificial heart pumps, the motor used is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) DC shunt motor",
            "b) DC series motor",
            "c) Induction motor",
            "d) BLDC motor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Unipolar and Bipolar are the types of BLDC motor. They use the Hall effect rotor position sensor and optical rotor position sensor."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "Calculate the output power of the Buck converter if the supply voltage is 4 V and duty cycle value is .1 for 4 Ω load.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 mW",
            "b) 20 mW",
            "c) 50 mW",
            "d) 60 mW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Peak-Peak voltage is equal to the difference between the maximum and minimum voltage. It is mathematically represented as Vp-p=Vmax-Vmin=45-45=0 V. It signifies the signal is DC signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "Calculate the compensator rating required for cos(Φ)=.1.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.91 P.U",
            "b) 0.99 P.U",
            "c) 0.97 P.U",
            "d) 0.92 P.U"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the crest factor is Vpeak÷Vr.m.s=141÷100=1.41. It signifies the peak value is 1.41 times than the r.m.s value."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "Calculate the average inductor current of the Boost converter if the load current is 7 A and duty cycle value is .8.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 36 A",
            "b) 35 A",
            "c) 34 A",
            "d) 31 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: BLDC motors are widely used in various applications of the medical industry. Sensorless BLDC motor and with sensor BLDC motors are used because of easy operation and high reliability compare to conventional motors."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "Calculate the output voltage of the Buck-Boost converter if the supply voltage is 14 V and duty cycle value is .85.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 79.3 V",
            "b) 45.5 V",
            "c) 86.5 V",
            "d) 54.7 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The output voltage of the buck converter is Vo = Vin×(D)=.4. The value of the duty cycle is less than one which makes the Vo < Vin. The buck converter is used to step down the voltage. The output power is Vo2÷R=40 mW."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "Who is larger in size?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Base",
            "b) Collector",
            "c) Emitter",
            "d) P-N Junction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The base of a transistor is lightly doped because it carries the electrons from the emitter and passed it to the collector region. There should be less recombination in the base region."
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "Calculate the collector current using the data: IE=14 mA, IB=7 mA.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7 mA",
            "b) 8 mA",
            "c) 9 mA",
            "d) 10 mA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Collector is larger in size because it receives the electrons from the base region. If it is not bigger in sizer there will be crowding of electrons which causes high power dissipation."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "Calculate the current gain using the data: Ic=25 mA, IB=10 mA.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.5",
            "b) 2.5",
            "c) 1.4",
            "d) 7.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The collector current in the transistor is IE-IB=14-7=7 mA. The KCL equation IE=IB+Ic is always in every configuration of the transistor."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of ∝ using the data: Ic=18 mA, IE=17 mA.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.05",
            "b) 1.47",
            "c) 1.89",
            "d) 2.55"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The current gain is represented as β in electronic circuits. The current gain is the ratio of the collector current and base current. β=Ic÷IB=25÷10=2.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "In a transistor, Ic=47 mA and IE=53 mA. The value of β is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8.48",
            "b) 7.83",
            "c) 9.26",
            "d) 3.15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of ∝ is Ic÷IE. The current gain is the ratio of the collector current and base current. ∝=Ic÷IE=18÷17=1.05."
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "Choose the correct relationship between β and ∝.",
        "Options": [
            "a) β=∝/(1-∝)",
            "b) β=1/(1+∝)",
            "c) β=1/(1-∝)",
            "d) β=1/(∝)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of β is Ic÷IB. The value of IB=IE-Ic=53-47=6 mA. The value of β is Ic÷IB=47÷6=7.83."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of β for α=.8.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 8",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The relationship between β and ∝ is β=∝/(1-∝). The current gain is the ratio of the collector current and base current. The value of β is Ic÷IB."
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IE=IB+Ic",
            "b) IE=IB-Ic",
            "c) IE=Ic",
            "d) IE=IB"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Transistor is a current operated device. The value of collector current is α times of the emitter current. It is a current controlled device."
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "In a transistor, IB=2 mA and Ic=3 mA. The value of β is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5",
            "b) 5.8",
            "c) 9.6",
            "d) 3.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The relationship between β and ∝ is β=∝/(1-∝)=.8÷.2=4. The current gain is the ratio of the collector current and base current. The value of β is Ic÷IB."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "In a transistor, β=75 and Ic=53 mA. The value of IB is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) .70 mA",
            "b) .25 mA",
            "c) .26 mA",
            "d) .15 mA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The KCL equation that holds correct is IE=IB+Ic. At any point emitter current is the sum of the base current and collector current."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of Vpeak if crest factor=5 and Vr.m.s=4 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 V",
            "b) 30 V",
            "c) 40 V",
            "d) 50 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of β is Ic÷IB. The value of IB and Ic are 2 mA, 3 mA. The value of β is Ic÷IB=3÷2=1.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of α for β=.2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .85",
            "b) .15",
            "c) .23",
            "d) .16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of β is Ic÷IB. The value of IB=IE-Ic. The value of IB is Ic÷β=53÷75=.70 mA. The relationship between β and ∝ is β=∝/(1-∝)."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "Calculate the work done in stretching the wire of volume=12 m3 and the values of stress and strain are 28 N/m2 and 7.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1176 J",
            "b) 1544 J",
            "c) 2542 J",
            "d) 8788 J"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the crest factor is Vpeak÷Vr.m.s. The value of Vpeak is (crest factor) × Vr.m.s=5×4=20 V. It signifies the ratio of Vpeak and Vr.m.s."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "Calculate the compensator rating required for cos(Φ)=.35.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .936 P.U",
            "b) .154 P.U",
            "c) .481 P.U",
            "d) .289 P.U"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The relationship between β and ∝ is ∝=β/(1+β)=.2÷1.2=.16. The current gain is the ratio of the collector current and base current. The value of α is Ic÷IE."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of safety factor using the data: tc=12 msec, tq=6 msec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The latching current is the minimum anode current at which SCR starts conducting. Holding current is the anode below which SCR stops conduction. The latching current is 2-3 times more than the holding current."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "For successful commutation circuit turn-off time ______ device turn-off time.",
        "Options": [
            "a) <",
            "b) >",
            "c) =",
            "d) ~"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SCR is a current controlled device. It can be explained using a two transistor model. When the gate pulse is applied, then it will start conduction."
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "SCR is a  __________ device.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uncontrolled",
            "b) Semi-controlled",
            "c) Fully controlled",
            "d) Voltage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of the safety factor is the ratio of the circuit turn-off time and device turn-off time. S.F=tc÷tq=12÷6=2."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "Holding current of the SCR is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) > than latching current",
            "b) < than latching current",
            "c) = to latching current",
            "d) ≥ than latching current"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For successful commutation circuit turn-off time must be greater than the device turn-off time. The excess stored charged carriers should be removed from the gate junction in order to avoid false triggering."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "If holding current of an SCR is 6 mA then its latching current should be ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 mA",
            "b) 5 mA",
            "c) 12 mA",
            "d) 6 mA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The SCR is a semi-controlled device. Turn-on time can be controlled by using a gate pulse but commutation circuit is required to turn off the device."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "If latching current of an SCR is 10 mA then its holding current should be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 mA",
            "b) 7 mA",
            "c) 8 mA",
            "d) 4 mA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Holding current of the SCR is less than the latching current. The value of latching current is 2-3 times than holding current."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to protect SCR from overcurrent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat sink",
            "b) Fuse",
            "c) Snubber circuit",
            "d) Zener diode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If holding current of an SCR is 6 mA then its latching current should be 12 mA. The latching current is 2-3 times more than the holding current."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to protect SCR from thermal conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat sink",
            "b) Voltage clamping device",
            "c) Zener diode",
            "d) Snubber circuit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The latching current is 2-3 times more than the holding current. If a latching current of an SCR is 10 mA then its holding current should be 5 mA. Holding current=(latching current)÷2=10÷2=5 mA."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to protect SCR from d(i)/d(t) condition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inductor",
            "b) Capacitor",
            "c) Heat sink",
            "d) Fuse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fuse and circuit breakers are used to protect SCR from overcurrent. When current exceeds the certain limit they cut down the supply of current in the circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to protect SCR from d(v)/d(t) condition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Capacitor",
            "b) Fuse",
            "c) Snubber circuit",
            "d) Inductor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SCR is mounted on a heat sink. When temperature exceeded the rating of the SCR excess amount of heat is dissipated through the help of the heat sink."
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "A snubber circuit is used with thyristor in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parallel",
            "b) Series",
            "c) Anti-parallel",
            "d) Series or Parallel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Inductor is used to protect SCR from d(i)/d(t) condition. The inductor does not allow the sudden change in current."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "When maximum power loss occurs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rise time",
            "b) Delay time",
            "c) Spread time",
            "d) Rise time or Delay time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Snubber circuit is used to protect SCR from d(v)/d(t) condition. Snubber circuit consists of a Capacitor and resistor. The capacitor does not allow the sudden change in voltage and resistor resists the discharging of the capacitor."
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of Vpeak if crest factor=47 and Vr.m.s=6 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 282 V",
            "b) 300 V",
            "c) 290 V",
            "d) 286 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A snubber circuit is used with thyristor in parallel. Snubber circuit is used to protect SCR from d(v)/d(t) condition. Snubber circuit consists of a Capacitor and resistor."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "Which one of the following load is suitable for load commutation in Single phase Half-bridge inverter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R-L load",
            "b) R-L-C overdamped",
            "c) R-L-C underdamped",
            "d) L-load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: R-L-C underdamped are leading power factor loads. They do not require any forced commutation technique. Anti-Parallel diodes help in the commutation process."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "A step-down chopper has input voltage 40 V and output voltage 20 V. Calculate the value of the duty cycle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 0.2",
            "c) 0.3",
            "d) 0.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: R-L-C overdamped loads are generally lagging power factor loads. They require forced commutation. Anti-Parallel diodes do not help in the commutation process."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "Calculate the De-rating factor if the string efficiency is 20 %.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .8",
            "b) .4",
            "c) .5",
            "d) .6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The output voltage of the step-down chopper is Vo = Vin×(D). The value of the duty cycle is less than one which makes the Vo < Vin. The step-down chopper is used to step down the voltage. The value of the duty cycle is 20÷40 = .5."
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "Calculate the string efficiency if the de-rating factor is .48.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 48 %",
            "b) 52 %",
            "c) 50 %",
            "d) 60 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: De-rating factor is used to measure the reliability of a string. The value of the De-rating factor is 1-(string efficiency) = 1-.2 = .8."
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "400 V rated 5 SCRs are connected in series. The operation voltage of the string is 500. Calculate the string efficiency.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25 %",
            "b) 40 %",
            "c) 38 %",
            "d) 35 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The string efficiency is calculated for series and parallel connection of SCRs. The value of string efficiency is 1 – (De-rating factor) = 1-.48 = 52 %."
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "100 V rated 3 SCRs are connected in series. The operation voltage of the string is 200. Calculate the De-rating factor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .35",
            "b) .33",
            "c) .38",
            "d) .18"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The string efficiency can be calculated using the formula operation voltage÷(Number of SCRs×Rated voltage) = 500÷(400×5) = 25 %."
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "The range of turn-off time is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) .51-3 μsec",
            "b) 3-101 μsec",
            "c) 9-400 μsec",
            "d) 7-787 μsec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The string efficiency can be calculated using the formula operation voltage÷(Number of SCRs×Rated voltage) = 200÷(100×3) = .66. The De-rating factor value is 1-.66 = .33."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "The range of On-State voltage drop is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-1.6 V",
            "b) 0-1 V",
            "c) 1.6-2 V",
            "d) 2.4-3 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gate triggering is more reliable than any other triggering method. The risk of false triggering of SCR reduces in the case of gate triggering."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "Thyristors are used in series to complete ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High voltage demand",
            "b) High current demand",
            "c) Low voltage demand",
            "d) Low current demand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The range of turn-off time is 3-101 μsec. The time is very low as SCR takes low time to turn-off. Commutation time should be greater than circuit turn-off time to avoid false triggering."
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "Thyristors are used in parallel to complete ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High voltage demand",
            "b) High current demand",
            "c) Low current demand",
            "d) Low voltage demand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When SCR is in forwarding blocking mode it does not conduct. When the gate pulse is applied, it starts conducting. The On-state voltage drop is very low around 1-1.6 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "Calculate peak-peak voltage if Vmax=200 V and Vmin=190 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 V",
            "b) 10 V",
            "c) 60 V",
            "d) 80 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thyristors are used in series to complete high voltage demand. In series voltage across the components can be the same or different but the value of current remains the same."
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "Which harmonic is not present in 3-Φ fully controlled rectifier?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 27rd harmonic",
            "b) 15th harmonic",
            "c) 17th harmonic",
            "d) 12th harmonic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thyristors are used in parallel to complete high current demand. In parallel current in the components can be the same or different but the value of voltage remains the same."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "Third lowest order harmonic present in 3-Φ fully controlled rectifier is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11th",
            "b) 17th",
            "c) 13th",
            "d) 22nd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Peak-Peak voltage is equal to the difference between the maximum and minimum voltage. It is mathematically represented as Vp-p=Vmax-Vmin=200-190=10 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of output r.m.s voltage for Single phase Half-bridge inverter if the DC supply is 80 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 V",
            "b) 20 V",
            "c) 10 V",
            "d) 60 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The output voltage of a single phase half bridge inverter is a square wave with amplitude is equal to vD.C÷2. The r.m.s value of output voltage is vD.C÷2=80÷2=40 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "High d(i)÷d(t) causes _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Local hotspots",
            "b) Breakdown",
            "c) High cost",
            "d) Low cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: High d(i)÷d(t) causes local hotspots. Local hotspots are the small areas with high temperature due to overcrowdedness of charge generation. This cause high heat generation."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of output r.m.s voltage for Single phase Full-bridge inverter if the DC supply is 25 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 26 V",
            "b) 25 V",
            "c) 27 V",
            "d) 28 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The output voltage of a single phase full bridge inverter is a square wave with amplitude is equal to vD.C. The r.m.s value of output voltage is vD.C=25 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "High d(v)÷d(t) causes _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Local hotspots",
            "b) False triggering",
            "c) High cost",
            "d) High-speed operation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: High d(v)÷d(t) causes false triggering. The high value of d(v)÷d(t) causes the breakdown of the junction J2. The thyristor will trigger automatically."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "A step-down chopper has input voltage 12 V and output voltage 2 V. Calculate the value of the duty cycle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.26",
            "b) 0.16",
            "c) 0.33",
            "d) 0.41"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The output voltage of the step-down chopper is Vo = Vin×(D). The value of the duty cycle is less than one which makes the Vo < Vin. The step-down chopper is used to step down the voltage. The value of the duty cycle is 2÷12=.16."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "Calculate the De-rating factor if the string efficiency is 90 %.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .4",
            "b) .1",
            "c) .7",
            "d) .8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: De-rating factor is used to measure the reliability of a string. The value of the De-rating factor is 1-(string efficiency)=1-.9=.1."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "Calculate the string efficiency if the de-rating factor is .22.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 78 %",
            "b) 42 %",
            "c) 20 %",
            "d) 90 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The string efficiency is calculated for series and parallel connection of SCRs. The value of string efficiency is 1-(De-rating factor)=1-.22=78 %."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "25 V rated n SCRs are connected in series. The operation voltage of the string is 300 V and the string efficiency is 40 %. Calculate the value of n.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 27",
            "b) 30",
            "c) 34",
            "d) 36"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The string efficiency can be calculated using the formula operation voltage÷(Number of SCRs×Rated voltage). The value of n is 300÷(25×.4)=30."
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "What is the formula for thermal voltage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) K×e÷T",
            "b) K×T÷e",
            "c) K2×e÷T",
            "d) K×e2÷T"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gate triggering is more reliable than any other triggering method. The risk of false triggering of SCR reduces in the case of gate triggering."
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "Device with highest d(i)÷d(t) and d(v)÷d(t) capability is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) GTO",
            "b) BJT",
            "c) SCR",
            "d) SITH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The SCR is uni-directional, bipolar power electronics device. It is bipolar in nature because of its reverse and forward mode blocking capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "____________ is the switching frequency of SITH.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 55 KHz",
            "b) 100 KHz",
            "c) 91 KHz",
            "d) 105 KHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The formula for thermal voltage is K×e÷T where K is the Boltzmann constant, e is the charge on the electron, T is the absolute temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of Crest factor if Vpeak=1.5 V and Vr.m.s=2.5 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .4",
            "b) .6",
            "c) .5",
            "d) .7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: SITH stands for static induction thyristor. It has a buried gate structure in which the gate electrode is placed in the n-base region. They have high d(i)÷d(t) and d(v)÷d(t) capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "Calculate the output voltage of the Boost converter if the supply voltage is 1 V and duty cycle value is .9.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 V",
            "b) 20 V",
            "c) 40 V",
            "d) 60 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 100 KHz is the switching frequency of static induction thyristor. Static Induction Thyristor has a low frequency because of lower turn-off current gain."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "In Half-wave controlled rectifier calculate the average value of the voltage if the supply is 13sin(25t) and firing angle is 13°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.08 V",
            "b) 4.15 V",
            "c) 3.46 V",
            "d) 5.48 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Half-wave controlled rectifier, the average value of the voltage is Vm(1+cos(∝))÷2π=13(1+cos(13°))÷6.28=4.08 V. The thyristor will conduct from ∝ to π."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "Calculate the extinction angle in purely inductive load if the firing angle is 13°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 328°",
            "b) 347°",
            "c) 349°",
            "d) 315°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The extinction angle in the purely inductive load is 2π-∝=360°-13°=347°. The extinction angle is the angle at which current in the circuit becomes zero. The average value of the voltage in a purely inductive load is zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "Calculate the conduction angle in purely inductive load if the firing angle is 165°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 78°",
            "b) 55°",
            "c) 30°",
            "d) 19°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The conduction angle in the purely inductive load is β-α=2(π-∝)=2(180°-165°)=30°. The conduction angle is the angle for which the current exists in the circuit. The average value of the voltage in a purely inductive load is zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "In Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier calculate the average value of the voltage if the supply is 3sin(5t).",
        "Options": [
            "a) .95 V",
            "b) .92 V",
            "c) .93 V",
            "d) .94 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: R-L-C underdamped loads are generally leading power factor loads. They do not require forced commutation. Anti-Parallel diodes help in the commutation process."
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "In Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier calculate the r.m.s value of the voltage if the supply is 89sin(41t).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 91.5 V",
            "b) 44.5 V",
            "c) 25.1 V",
            "d) 15.1 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier, the average value of the voltage is Vm÷π=3÷π=.95 V. The diode will conduct only for the positive half cycle. The conduction period of the diode is π."
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "In Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier calculate the power dissipation across the 8 Ω resistor if the supply is 29sin(22t).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 26.2 W",
            "b) 24.2 W",
            "c) 26.1 W",
            "d) 29.1 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier, the r.m.s value of the voltage is Vm÷2=89÷2=44.5 V. The diode will conduct only for the positive half cycle. The conduction period of the diode is π."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "The conduction period of diode in Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier for resistive load is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) π",
            "b) 2π",
            "c) 3π",
            "d) 4π"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier, the r.m.s value of the voltage is Vm÷2=29÷2=14.5 V. The diode will conduct only for the positive half cycle. Power dissipation across the resistor is V2r.m.s÷R=14.52÷8=26.2 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "In Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier calculate the average value of the current for 3 Ω resistive load if the supply is 34sin(11t).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.6 A",
            "b) 2.6 A",
            "c) 2.5 A",
            "d) 3.1 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The conduction period of the diode in Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier for the resistive load is π. For the negative A.C supply diode will be reverse biased."
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "In Half-wave controlled rectifier calculate the average value of the current for 2.5 Ω resistive load if the supply is sin(5.2t) and firing angle is 26°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.8 V",
            "b) 0.15 V",
            "c) 0.12 V",
            "d) 0.21 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier, the average value of the current is Vm÷πR=34÷3π=3.6 A. The diode will conduct only for the positive half cycle. The conduction period of the diode is π."
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "Calculate the circuit turn-off time for Half-wave controlled rectifier for a ω=5 rad/sec for resistive load.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .62 sec",
            "b) .42 sec",
            "c) .58 sec",
            "d) .64 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Half-wave controlled rectifier, the average value of the current is Vm(1+cos(∝))÷2πR=(1+cos(26°))÷6.28×2.5=.12 V. The thyristor will conduct from ∝ to π."
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "Calculate the string efficiency if the de-rating factor is .429.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 48.1 %",
            "b) 57.1 %",
            "c) 47.8 %",
            "d) 46.5 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the circuit turn-off for Half-wave controlled rectifier for a ω=5 rad/sec for the resistive load is a π÷Ω=π÷5=.62 sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "Calculate the output frequency for the six-pulse converter if the supply frequency is 10 Hz.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 Hz",
            "b) 30 Hz",
            "c) 60 Hz",
            "d) 80 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The string efficiency is calculated for series and parallel connection of SCRs. The value of string efficiency is 1-(De-rating factor)=1-.429=57.1 %."
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "Calculate the pulse number if the supply frequency is 2π and the output frequency is π÷6.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 12",
            "c) 16",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The output of a six-pulse converter consists of six pulses in one cycle. The output frequency of the six pulse converter is 6×supply frequency=6×10=60 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the Input power factor for 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier if the firing angle value is 39°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .69",
            "b) .59",
            "c) .78",
            "d) .15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the input power factor for 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier is .9cos(67°)=.69. The input power factor is a product of distortion factor and displacement factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the fundamental displacement factor for 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier if the firing angle value is 38°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .22",
            "b) .78",
            "c) .33",
            "d) .44"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fundamental displacement factor is the cosine of angle difference between the fundamental voltage and fundamental current. D.F=cos(∝)=cos(38°)=0.78."
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the fundamental displacement factor for 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter if the firing angle value is 69°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .48",
            "b) .24",
            "c) .82",
            "d) .88"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fundamental displacement factor is the cosine of angle difference between the fundamental voltage and fundamental current. The fundamental displacement factor for 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter is cos(∝÷2)=cos(34.5°)=.82.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "Calculate the fundamental component of source current in 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier for load(Highly inductive) current=3.14 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.82 A",
            "b) 1.45 A",
            "c) 3.69 A",
            "d) 4.78 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fundamental component of source current in 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier is 2√2Io÷π. It is the r.m.s value of the fundamental component. Is1(r.m.s) = 2√2Io÷π=2√2=2.82 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "Calculate the circuit turn-off time for 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier for α=145°. Assume the value of ω=5 rad/sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 84.9 msec",
            "b) 94.5 msec",
            "c) 101.2 msec",
            "d) 87.2 msec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The circuit turn-off time for 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier is (π-α)÷ω. The value of circuit turn-off time is (π-145°)÷5=87.2 msec. "
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "Calculate the fundamental component of source current in 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier for the load(Highly inductive) current=78 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 78 A",
            "b) 45 A",
            "c) 69 A",
            "d) 13 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fundamental component of source current in 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier is Io. It is the r.m.s value of the source current. Is(r.m.s)=Io=78 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "Calculate the r.m.s value of source current in 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter for the load (Highly inductive) current=51.2 A and α=15°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10.53 A",
            "b) 14.52 A",
            "c) 44.92 A",
            "d) 49.02 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The r.m.s value of source current in 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter is Io√π-α÷π. It is the r.m.s value of the source current. I(r.m.s) = Io√π-α÷π = 51.2(√.916) = 49.02 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "Calculate the r.m.s value of thyristor current in 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter for the load (Highly inductive) current=2.2 A and α=155°. (Asymmetrical configuration)",
        "Options": [
            "a) .58 A",
            "b) .57 A",
            "c) .51 A",
            "d) .52 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The r.m.s value of source current in 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter is Io√π-α÷2π. It is the r.m.s value of the thyristor current. I(r.m.s) = Io√π-α÷2π=2.2(√.069)=.57 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "Calculate the r.m.s value of diode current in 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter for the load (Highly inductive) current=5.1 A and α=115°. (Asymmetrical configuration)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.21 A",
            "b) 4.61 A",
            "c) 4.71 A",
            "d) 4.52 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The r.m.s value of diode current in 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter is Io√π+α÷2π. It is the r.m.s value of the diode current. I(r.m.s) = Io√π+α÷π=5.1(√.819)=4.61 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "Calculate the average value of thyristor current in 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter for the load (Highly inductive) current=25.65 A and α=18°. (Asymmetrical configuration)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11.54 A",
            "b) 12.15 A",
            "c) 15.48 A",
            "d) 14.52 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The average value of thyristor current in 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter is Io(π-α÷2π). It is the average value of the thyristor current. Iavg = Io(π-α÷2π)=25.65(.45)=11.54 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "Calculate the average value of diode current in 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter for the load (Highly inductive) current=75.2 A and α=41°. (Asymmetrical configuration)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 46.16 A",
            "b) 42.15 A",
            "c) 41.78 A",
            "d) 41.18 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The average value of diode current in 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter is Io(π+α÷2π). It is the average value of the diode current. Iavg = Io(π+α÷2π)=75.2(.61)=46.16 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "Calculate the average value of diode current in 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter for the load (Highly inductive) current=5.2 A and α=11°. (F.D configuration)",
        "Options": [
            "a) .32 A",
            "b) .31 A",
            "c) .25 A",
            "d) .27 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The average value of diode current in 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter is Io(α÷π). It is the average value of the diode current. Iavg= Io(α÷π)=5.2(.061)=.31 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "Calculate the r.m.s value of diode current in 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter for the load (Highly inductive) current=.2 A and α=74°. (F.D configuration)",
        "Options": [
            "a) .154 A",
            "b) .248 A",
            "c) .128 A",
            "d) .587 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The r.m.s value of diode current in 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter is Io√(α÷π). It is the r.m.s value of the diode current. Ir.m.s = Io√(α÷π)=.2√(.41)=.128 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the conduction angle for R-L load if the value of β and α are 19° and 29°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10°",
            "b) 70°",
            "c) 30°",
            "d) 80°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The conduction angle for R-L load is β-α=29°-19°=10°. R-L load is a current stiff type of load. The current in the circuit only flows from α to β."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "Calculate the V0 avg for Single-phase Half Wave rectifier for R-L load using the data: Vm=24 V, ∝=30°, β=60°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.39 V",
            "b) 8.45 V",
            "c) 4.55 V",
            "d) 1.48 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Half-wave controlled rectifier, the average value of the voltage is Vm(cos(∝)-cos(β))÷2π=24(cos(30°)- cos(60°))÷6.28=1.39 V. The thyristor will conduct from ∝ to β."
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "Calculate the I0 avg for Single-phase Half Wave rectifier for R-L load using the data: Vm=56 V, ∝=15°, β=30°, R=2 Ω.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .56 A",
            "b) .44 A",
            "c) .26 A",
            "d) .89 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Half-wave controlled rectifier, the average value of the current is Vm(cos(∝)-cos(β))÷2πR=56(cos(15°)- cos(30°))÷12.56=.44 A. The thyristor will conduct from ∝ to β."
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "Calculate the I0 r.m.s for Single-phase Half Wave rectifier for R-L load (Highly inductive) using the data: Vm=110 V, ∝=16°, β=31°, R=1 Ω.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.56 A",
            "b) 1.82 A",
            "c) 4.81 A",
            "d) 9.15 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Half-wave controlled rectifier, the r.m.s value of the current is Vm(cos(∝) – cos(β))÷2πR=110(cos(16°) – cos(31°))÷6.28=1.82 A. The thyristor will conduct from ∝ to β."
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the fundamental displacement factor for 1-φ Full wave semi-converter if the firing angle value is 0o.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) .8",
            "c) .4",
            "d) .2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fundamental displacement factor is the cosine of angle difference between the fundamental voltage and fundamental current. The fundamental displacement factor for 1-φ Full wave semi-converter is cos(∝÷2)=cos(0o)=1."
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the Input power factor using the data: Fundamental displacement factor=.96, Distortion factor=.97.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .93",
            "b) .84",
            "c) .48",
            "d) .89"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For highly inductive load current remains continuous. Inductor opposes the change in the current. When current is about to extinct the next conducting cycle starts due to which currently remains constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "In single phase RLE load, calculate the voltage across the thyristor when current decays to zero using the data: (Vs)r.m.s=340 V, f=50 Hz, R=2 Ω, E=150 V, β=160°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45.89 V",
            "b) 74.45 V",
            "c) 54.85 V",
            "d) 84.48 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the input power factor is a product of the (Fundamental displacement factor)×(Distortion factor)=g×F.D.F=.97×.96=.93."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "In single phase RLE load, calculate the angle at which conduction starts using the data: (Vs)=14sin(Ωt), f=50 Hz, E=10 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45.58°",
            "b) 46.26°",
            "c) 47.26°",
            "d) 49.56°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Displacement factor depends upon the shape of the waveform. Displacement factor is the cosine of the angle between the fundamental voltage and fundamental current. It depends upon the type of load, converter type."
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "Full form of PIV.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peak inverse voltage",
            "b) Peak insert voltage",
            "c) Paas Inverse volatile",
            "d) Peak insert volatile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In single phase RLE load the voltage across the thyristor when current decays to zero VT=Vmsin(β)-E=340×√2sin(160°)-90=74.45 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "Calculate the PIV for the Full-wave bridge rectifier if the peak value of the supply voltage is 230.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 324.4 V",
            "b) 325.2 V",
            "c) 524.4 V",
            "d) 626.8 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The angle at which conduction starts when Vmsin(θ)=E. The conduction will remain from ϴ to π-θ. Θ=sin-(E÷Vm)=sin-(.71)=45.58°."
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "In single phase RLE load, calculate the Peak inverse voltage using the data: (Vs)r.m.s=89 V, f=50 Hz,  E=440 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 521.2 V",
            "b) 527.8 V",
            "c) 597 V",
            "d) 529 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PIV stands for Peak inverse voltage. It is the maximum negative voltage after which thyristor will breakdown."
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "Full form of DAC is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Digital to Analog converter",
            "b) Discrete to Analog converter",
            "c) Digital to AC converter",
            "d) Discrete to Avalanche converter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The peak inverse voltage for the Full-wave bridge rectifier is Vm=√2×230=325.2 V. The peak inverse is the maximum negative voltage across the thyristor."
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "Full form of ADC is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Analog to Digital converter",
            "b) Discrete to Analog converter",
            "c) Analog to Digital converter",
            "d) Discrete to Avalanche converter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In a single phase, RLE load the peak inverse voltage across the thyristor VT=Vm+E=529 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "Calculate the voltage across the freewheeling diode when the output voltage is 24 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) -15 V",
            "b) -24 V",
            "c) 28 V",
            "d) 39 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The freewheeling diode is used to provide a freewheeling path. It is connected in the anti-parallel direction of the load. The voltage across the diode is -Vo=-24 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the conduction angle for SCR for R-L load with a freewheeling diode if the value of β and α are 65° and 12°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 168°",
            "b) 170°",
            "c) 130°",
            "d) 180°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The conduction angle for SCR for R-L load with a freewheeling diode is π-α=180°-12°=168°. R-L load is a current stiff type of load. The current in the SCR only flows from α to π."
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the conduction angle for diode for R-L load with a freewheeling diode if the value of α is 45°. (Continous conduction mode)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 220°",
            "b) 225°",
            "c) 230°",
            "d) 280°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The conduction angle for diode for R-L load with a freewheeling diode is π+α=180°+45°=225°. R-L load is a current stiff type of load."
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the conduction angle for diode for R-L load with a freewheeling diode if the value of β is 226°. (Discontinuous conduction mode)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40°",
            "b) 45°",
            "c) 50°",
            "d) 46°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The conduction angle for diode for R-L load with a freewheeling diode is β-π=226°-180°=45°. R-L load is a current stiff type of load."
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the conduction angle for R-L load if the value of β and α are 56° and 18°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 48°",
            "b) 38°",
            "c) 57°",
            "d) 15°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The conduction angle for R-L load is β-α=56°-18°=38°. R-L load is a current stiff type of load. The current in the circuit only flows from α to β."
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the fundamental displacement factor for 1-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier if the firing α=17°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .98",
            "b) .19",
            "c) .56",
            "d) .95"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fundamental displacement factor is the cosine of angle difference between the fundamental voltage and fundamental current. D.F=cos(∝)=cos(17°)=0.95."
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the fundamental displacement factor for 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter if the firing angle value is 95o.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .60",
            "b) .68",
            "c) .62",
            "d) .67"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fundamental displacement factor is the cosine of angle difference between the fundamental voltage and fundamental current. The fundamental displacement factor for 1-Φ Full wave semi-converter is cos(∝÷2)=cos(47.5o)=.67."
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "Which one of the following load is suitable for lagging power factor load in Single phase Half-bridge inverter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) C load",
            "b) R-L-C overdamped",
            "c) R-L-C underdamped",
            "d) L-C load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: R-L-C overdamped loads are generally lagging power factor loads. They require forced commutation. Anti-Parallel diodes do not help in the commutation process."
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "Which one of the following load is suitable for leading power factor load in Single phase Half-bridge inverter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) C load",
            "b) R-L-C overdamped",
            "c) R-L-C underdamped",
            "d) L-C load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: R-L-C underdamped are leading power factor loads. They do not require any forced commutation technique. Anti-Parallel diodes help in the commutation process."
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "A step-down chopper has input voltage .1 V and output voltage .01 V. Calculate the value of the duty cycle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1",
            "b) 0.2",
            "c) 0.3",
            "d) 0.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The output voltage of the step-down chopper is Vo = Vin×(D). The value of the duty cycle is less than one which makes the Vo < Vin. The step-down chopper is used to step down the voltage. The value of the duty cycle is .01÷.1=.1."
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "Calculate the De-rating factor if the string efficiency is 98%.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .04",
            "b) .02",
            "c) .05",
            "d) .03"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: De-rating factor is used to measure the reliability of a string. The value of the De-rating factor is 1-(string efficiency)=1-.98=.02."
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "Calculate the string efficiency if the de-rating factor is .50.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 28 %",
            "b) 42 %",
            "c) 80 %",
            "d) 50 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The string efficiency is calculated for series and parallel connection of SCRs. The value of string efficiency is 1-(De-rating factor)=1-.50=50 %."
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "70 V rated 6 SCRs are connected in series. The operation voltage of the string is 130. Calculate the De-rating factor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .70",
            "b) .73",
            "c) .78",
            "d) .74"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The string efficiency can be calculated using the formula operation voltage÷(Number of SCRs×Rated voltage)=130÷(70×6)=.30. The De-rating factor value is 1-.30=.70."
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "Calculate the output voltage of the Buck converter if the supply voltage is 13 V and duty cycle value is .16.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.08 V",
            "b) 2.24 V",
            "c) 2.58 V",
            "d) 2.54 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gate triggering is more reliable than any other triggering method. The risk of false triggering of SCR increases in the case of the d(v)÷d(t) triggering."
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "Calculate the Vo(avg) for the 3-Φ phase Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier if the supply value is 440 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 297.25 V",
            "b) 298.15 V",
            "c) 298.11 V",
            "d) 300.15 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Vo(avg) for the 3-Φ phase Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier is 3Vml÷2π. The value of output voltage is 3Vml÷2π=3×√2×440÷6.28=297.25 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "Calculate the pulse number if the supply frequency is 2π and the output frequency is 2π÷3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The pulse number can be calculated using the ratio of input frequency to the output frequency. The value of pulse number (P) is 2π÷(2π÷3)=3. It is a three-pulse converter or 3-Φ phase Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier."
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "Calculate the average value of current for the 3-Φ phase Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier if the supply value is 400 V and resistive load value is 5 Ω.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 54.04 A",
            "b) 57.26 A",
            "c) 51.64 A",
            "d) 58.15 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Io(avg) for the 3-Φ phase Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier is 3Vml÷2πR. The value of output voltage is 3Vml÷2πR=3×√2×440÷6.28×5=54.04 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "In 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier calculate the average value of the voltage if the supply is 400 V and firing angle is 45°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 381.15 V",
            "b) 382.16 V",
            "c) 383.19 V",
            "d) 384.25 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier, the average value of the voltage is   3Vml(cos(∝))÷π=3×400×√2(cos(45°))÷3.14=382.16 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "Calculate the Vo(r.m.s) (Highly inductive load) for the 3-Φ phase Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier if the supply value is 441 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 297.25 V",
            "b) 298.15 V",
            "c) 298.11 V",
            "d) 300.15 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Vo(r.m.s) for the 3-Φ phase Half-wave uncontrolled rectifier is 3Vml÷2π. The value of output voltage is 3Vml÷2π=3×√2×441÷6.28=297.25 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "Calculate the Vo(avg) for the 3-Φ phase Half-wave controlled rectifier if the supply value is 364 V and the value of firing angle is 2°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 247.62 V",
            "b) 245.76 V",
            "c) 214.26 V",
            "d) 233.26 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Vo(avg) for the 3-Φ phase Half-wave controlled rectifier is 3Vmlcos(α)÷2π. The value of output voltage is 3Vmlcos(α)÷2π=3×√2×364×(.99)÷6.28=245.76 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the Input power factor for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier if the firing angle value is 16°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .96",
            "b) .91",
            "c) .93",
            "d) .94"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of the input power factor for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier is .95cos(16°)=.91. The input power factor is a product of distortion factor and displacement factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "In 3-Φ Semi-controlled rectifier calculate the average value of the voltage if the supply is 299 V and firing angle is 56.15°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 311.26 V",
            "b) 304.26 V",
            "c) 314.51 V",
            "d) 312.45 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In 3-Φ Semi-controlled rectifier, the average value of the voltage is 3Vml(1+cos(∝))÷2π=3×299×√2(1+cos(56.15°))÷6.28=314.51 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "Calculate the circuit turn-off time for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier if the firing angle is 13° and supply frequency is 49.5 Hz.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 730.2 msec",
            "b) 740.8 msec",
            "c) 754.5 msec",
            "d) 755.1 msec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The circuit turn-off time for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier is (240°-α)÷ω. The value of circuit turn-off time for ∝ < 60° is (240°-13°)÷6.28×49.5=730.2 msec."
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "Calculate the circuit turn-off time for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier if the firing angle is 170° and supply frequency is 50.5 Hz.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 32.4 msec",
            "b) 35.2 msec",
            "c) 39.3 msec",
            "d) 31.5 msec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The circuit turn-off time for 3-Φ Fully controlled rectifier is (180°-α)÷Ω. The value of circuit turn-off time for ∝ ≥ 60° is (180°-170°)÷6.28×50.5=31.5 msec."
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "Calculate the form factor if V(r.m.s)=45 V, V(avg)=15 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The form factor is defined as the ratio of the Vr.m.s÷Vavg=45÷15=3. The r.m.s value is three times of average value Vavg."
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "Calculate the Vo(avg) for the 3-Φ phase Half-wave controlled rectifier if the supply value is 480 V and the value of firing angle is 92°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 264.02 V",
            "b) 487.26 V",
            "c) 858.26 V",
            "d) 248.25 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Vo(r.m.s) for the 3-Φ phase Half-wave controlled rectifier is 3Vm(1+cos(α))÷2π. The value of output voltage is 3Vm(1+cos(α+30))÷2π=3×480×√3×√2(1+cos(92))÷2π=264.02 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "Full form of SCR is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silicon controlled rectifier",
            "b) State-controlled rectifier",
            "c) State cover rectifier",
            "d) State-controlled reset"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SCR stands for silicon controlled rectifier. It is a semi-controlled, bipolar, uni-directional switch. It is a high power rating than other power electronic devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "Full form of TRIAC is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triode for Alternating current",
            "b) Tri for Alternating current",
            "c) Triode for Alternating counter",
            "d) Tri for Alternating counters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: TRIAC stands for Triode for Alternating current. It is a bipolar, bidirectional switch. It is used in fan regulators to control the speed of fans."
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "What is the formula for output voltage for 3-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier for R-L load?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3Vml(cos(∝))÷2π",
            "b) 3Vml(cos(∝))÷π",
            "c) 2Vml(cos(∝))÷π",
            "d) 6Vml(cos(∝))÷π"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The output voltage of 3-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier is 3Vml(cos(∝))÷π. For α > 90° the output voltage becomes negative. The power flows from DC to the AC side."
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": "What is the formula for output voltage for 3-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier for R load for α < 60°?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2Vml(cos(∝))÷π",
            "b) 3Vml(cos(∝))÷2π",
            "c) 3Vml(cos(∝))÷π",
            "d) 6Vml(cos(∝))÷π"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The output voltage of 3-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier for R-L load is 3Vml(cos(∝))÷π. The net area of the output voltage for R-L load remains zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": "____________ is the boundary for C.C.M and D.C.M mode in 3-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier for R load.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60°",
            "b) 10°",
            "c) 80°",
            "d) 50°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The output voltage of 3-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier is 3Vml(cos(∝))÷π. The output voltage of 3-Φ Half wave rectifier is 3Vml(cos(∝))÷2π."
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "What is the formula for output voltage for 3-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier for R load for α > 60°?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2Vml(1+cos(∝+60°))÷π",
            "b) 3Vml(1+cos(60°+∝))÷2π",
            "c) 3Vml(1+cos(60°+∝))÷π",
            "d) 6Vml(cos(∝))÷π"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The output voltage of 3-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier for R load is 3Vml(cos(∝))÷π for α < 60°. Conduction will only remain from 60°+α to 120°+α."
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": "Calculate the r.m.s value of thyristor current in 3-Φ Full wave converter for the load current=4 A and α=12°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.3 A",
            "b) 2.5 A",
            "c) 2.7 A",
            "d) 2.9 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 60° is the boundary for C.C.M and D.C.M mode in 3-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier for R load. Conduction will only remain from 60°+α to 120°+α."
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": "Calculate the average value of thyristor current in 3-Φ Full wave converter for the load current=9 A and α=26°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 A",
            "b) 5 A",
            "c) 7 A",
            "d) 3 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The output voltage of 3-Φ Full wave bridge rectifier for R load is 3Vml(1+cos(60°+∝))÷π for α > 60°. Conduction will only remain from 60°+α to 180°."
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "Calculate the De-rating factor if the string efficiency is 16 %.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .84",
            "b) .44",
            "c) .5",
            "d) .6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The r.m.s value of thyristor current in 3-Φ Full wave converter is Io√1÷3. It is the r.m.s value of the thyristor current. I(r.m.s) = Io√1÷3 = 2.3 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "Full form of MOSFET is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metal oxide silicon field effect transistor",
            "b) Metal oxide semiconductor field effect transistor",
            "c) Metal oxide settle field effect transistor",
            "d) Metal oriented silicon field effect transistor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The average value of thyristor current in 3-Φ Full wave converter is Io÷3. It is the average value of the thyristor current. I(r.m.s) = Io÷3 = 3 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 728,
        "Question": "Full form of FET is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Field effect transistor",
            "b) Field engage transistor",
            "c) Field effect terminal",
            "d) Fire engage transistor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: De-rating factor is used to measure the reliability of a string. The value of the De-rating factor is 1-(string efficiency)=1-.16=.84."
    },
    {
        "id": 729,
        "Question": "Calculate the compensator rating required for sin(Φ)=.13.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.45 P.U",
            "b) 0.12 P.U",
            "c) 0.13 P.U",
            "d) 0.82 P.U"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MOSFET stands for Metal oxide semiconductor field effect transistor. It is a three terminal device consists of source, drain, gate. It is a high switching device."
    },
    {
        "id": 730,
        "Question": "Full form of DIAC is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Digital Alternating current",
            "b) Discrete Alternating current",
            "c) Diode for Alternating current",
            "d) Digital Alternating counter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: FET stands for Field effect transistor. It is a transistor that depends upon the electric field to control the conductivity of the channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 731,
        "Question": "Which harmonic is not present in 3-Φ fully controlled rectifier?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 81st harmonic",
            "b) 15th harmonic",
            "c) 17th harmonic",
            "d) 11th harmonic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The compensator rating can be calculated using the relation QP.U=√1-cos2(∅)=sin(∅)=.13. This per unit value VAR compensator is required to improve the power factor of the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 732,
        "Question": "Fifth lowest order harmonic present in 3-Φ fully controlled rectifier is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15th",
            "b) 17th",
            "c) 13th",
            "d) 12th"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: DIAC stands for Diode Alternating current. It is a bipolar switch. It will conduct when the voltage across it becomes greater than the breakover voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 733,
        "Question": "Which one of the following device is uncontrolled?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SCR",
            "b) MOSFET",
            "c) Diode",
            "d) TRIAC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Choppers are used to control the DC voltage level. They can increase, decrease or both the input DC voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 734,
        "Question": "What is the formula for output voltage for Buck converter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8D×Vin",
            "b) 5D×Vin",
            "c) 2D×Vin",
            "d) D×Vin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Diode is uncontrolled, unidirectional power electronic device. When the voltage across the diode becomes positive it starts conduction otherwise remains off."
    },
    {
        "id": 735,
        "Question": "What is the formula for output voltage for Buck-Boost converter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) D×Vin",
            "b) Vin ÷ (1-D)",
            "c) D×Vin ÷ (1-D)",
            "d) D×Vin ÷ (1+D)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cuk-converter is better than Buck converter in terms of the output voltage. The filter is present at the output and input side of the Cuk-converter whereas in Buck there is no filter circuit present at the input side."
    },
    {
        "id": 736,
        "Question": "What is the formula for output voltage for Boost converter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8D×Vin",
            "b) 5D×Vin",
            "c) 2D×Vin",
            "d) D×Vin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The output voltage of the buck converter is Vo = D×Vin. The value of the duty cycle is less than one which makes the Vo < Vin. The buck converter is used to step down voltage. Vin is a fixed voltage and Vo is a variable voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 737,
        "Question": "____________ is the boundary for C.C.M and D.C.M mode in 3-Φ Half wave bridge rectifier for R load.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60°",
            "b) 10°",
            "c) 80°",
            "d) 30°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The output voltage of the buck-boost converter is Vo = D×Vin ÷ (1-D). It can step up and step down the voltage depending upon the value of the duty cycle. If the value of the duty cycle is less than .5 it will work as a buck converter and for duty cycle greater than .5 it will work as a boost converter."
    },
    {
        "id": 738,
        "Question": "Buck-Boost acts as Buck converter for duty cycle is equal to  _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) .9",
            "b) .7",
            "c) .6",
            "d) .4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The output voltage of the boost converter is Vo = Vin ÷ (1-D). The value of the duty cycle is less than one which makes the Vo > Vin. The boost converter is used to step up the voltage. Vin is a fixed voltage and Vo is a variable voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 739,
        "Question": "Buck-Boost acts as Boost converter for duty cycle is equal to  _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) .8",
            "b) .1",
            "c) .2",
            "d) .4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 30° is the boundary for C.C.M and D.C.M mode in 3-Φ Half wave bridge rectifier for R load. Conduction will only remain from 30°+α to 150°+α."
    },
    {
        "id": 740,
        "Question": "Inductor and Capacitor in Buck converter are used to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase the cost",
            "b) Decrease the cost",
            "c) Filter out the harmonics",
            "d) Increase the harmonics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The output voltage of the buck-boost converter is Vo = D×Vin ÷ (1-D). It can step up and step down the voltage depending upon the value of the duty cycle. If the value of the duty cycle is less than .5 it will work as a buck converter. The answer is .4."
    },
    {
        "id": 741,
        "Question": "Calculate peak-peak voltage if Vmax=1 V and Vmin=-1 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 V",
            "b) 2 V",
            "c) 3 V",
            "d) 1 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The output voltage of the buck-boost converter is Vo = D×Vin ÷ (1-D). It can step up and step down the voltage depending upon the value of the duty cycle. If the value of the duty cycle is more than .5 it will work as a boost converter. The answer is .8."
    },
    {
        "id": 742,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of Crest factor if Vpeak=0 V and Vr.m.s=24 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Inductor and capacitor in Buck converter are used to filter out the harmonics. They remove the ripple from the output voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 743,
        "Question": "Calculate the output voltage of the Buck converter if the supply voltage is 789 V and duty cycle value is .9.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 711.1 V",
            "b) 710.1 V",
            "c) 722.2 V",
            "d) 713.2 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Peak-Peak voltage is equal to the difference between the maximum and minimum voltage. It is mathematically represented as Vp-p=Vmax-Vmin=1+1=2 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 744,
        "Question": "Calculate the average value of thyristor current in 3-Φ Full wave converter for the load current=27 A and α=6°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9 A",
            "b) 4 A",
            "c) 5 A",
            "d) 9 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the crest factor is Vpeak÷Vr.m.s=0÷24=0 V. It signifies the peak value is 0 times than the r.m.s value."
    },
    {
        "id": 745,
        "Question": "Calculate the output voltage of the Boost converter if the supply voltage is 156 V and duty cycle value is .4.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 260 V",
            "b) 264 V",
            "c) 261 V",
            "d) 268 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The output voltage of the buck converter is Vo = Vin×(D)=789×.9=710.1 V. The value of the duty cycle is less than one which makes the Vo < Vin. The buck converter is used to step down the voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 746,
        "Question": "Switches used in VSI are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unipolar & Unidirectional",
            "b) Bipolar & Bidirectional",
            "c) Unipolar & Bidirectional",
            "d) Unidirectional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Inverters are used to convert DC power into variable AC power. The variable AC power means variable frequency and variable voltage level."
    },
    {
        "id": 747,
        "Question": "Switches used in CSI are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bipolar & Unidirectional",
            "b) Bipolar & Bidirectional",
            "c) Unipolar & Unidirectional",
            "d) Bidirectional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Short-circuit problem is severe in case of voltage source inverter. The output voltage of VSI is fixed but the output current depends upon the load. When Z=0, I=V÷Z=∞."
    },
    {
        "id": 748,
        "Question": "Full form of VSI is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Voltage source inverter",
            "b) Volume source inverter",
            "c) Voltage severe inverter",
            "d) Voltage source inserter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Switches used in VSI are unipolar and bidirectional in nature. MOSFET, BJT are the examples of switches used in VSI. The output voltage of VSI is fixed but the output current depends upon the load."
    },
    {
        "id": 749,
        "Question": "Full form of CSI is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Counter source inverter",
            "b) Counter severe inverter",
            "c) Current source inverter",
            "d) Current severe inverter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Switches used in CSI are bipolar and unidirectional in nature. GTO, thyristors are the examples of switches used in CSI. The output voltage of CSI is variable but the output current is fixed."
    },
    {
        "id": 750,
        "Question": "Number of switches turned on in 3-phase 180° VSI at a single time are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: VSI stands for Voltage source inverter. The output voltage of VSI is fixed but the output current depends upon the load. Switches used in VSI are unipolar and bidirectional in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 751,
        "Question": "Number of switches turned on in 3-phase 120° VSI at a single time are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: CSI stands for Current source inverter. The output voltage of CSI is variable but the output current is fixed."
    },
    {
        "id": 752,
        "Question": "Calculate the phase voltage for 3-∅ 180° VSI if the value of DC supply is 20 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9.40 V",
            "b) 9.42 V",
            "c) 9.18 V",
            "d) 9.78 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In 3-phase 180° VSI each phase conducts for 180° and only two switches from different phases conduct at a single time."
    },
    {
        "id": 753,
        "Question": "Calculate the line voltage for 3-∅ 180° VSI if the value of DC supply is 22 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18.52 V",
            "b) 18.12 V",
            "c) 17.96 V",
            "d) 15.48 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In 3-phase 120° VSI each phase conducts for 120° and only three switches from different phases conduct at a single time."
    },
    {
        "id": 754,
        "Question": "Calculate the line voltage for 3-∅ 120° VSI if the value of DC supply is 24 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 16.52 V",
            "b) 16.97 V",
            "c) 12.96 V",
            "d) 12.48 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The phase voltage for 3-∅ 180° VSI is (√2÷3)×VDC=.471×20=9.42 V. In 3-phase 180° VSI each phase conducts for 180° and only two switches from different phases conduct at a single time."
    },
    {
        "id": 755,
        "Question": "Calculate the phase voltage for 3-∅ 120° VSI if the value of DC supply is 26 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10.52 V",
            "b) 10.97 V",
            "c) 10.96 V",
            "d) 10.61 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The line voltage for 3-∅ 180° VSI is (√2÷√3)×VDC=.81×22=17.96 V. In 3-phase 180° VSI each phase conducts for 180° and only two switches from different phases conduct at a single time."
    },
    {
        "id": 756,
        "Question": "Calculate power absorbed by 5 Ω load in 3-∅ 120° VSI if the value of DC supply is 16 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 17.06 W",
            "b) 15.15 W",
            "c) 18.25 W",
            "d) 19.26 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The line voltage for 3-∅ 120° VSI is (VDC÷√2)=.707×24=16.97 V. In 3-phase 120° VSI each phase conducts for 120° and only three switches from different phases conduct at a single time."
    },
    {
        "id": 757,
        "Question": "Calculate power absorbed by 10 Ω load in 3-∅ 180° VSI if the value of DC supply is 36 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20.6 W",
            "b) 24.5 W",
            "c) 26.4 W",
            "d) 28.8 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The line voltage for 3-∅ 120° VSI is (VDC÷√6)=10.61 V. In 3-phase 120° VSI each phase conducts for 120° and only three switches from different phases conduct at a single time."
    },
    {
        "id": 758,
        "Question": "T.H.D value for 3-∅ 180° VSI is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 36 %",
            "b) 31 %",
            "c) 39 %",
            "d) 46 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The power absorbed by 5 Ω load in 3-∅ 120° VSI if the value of DC supply is 16 V is Vph2÷R=(16÷√3)2÷5=17.06 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 759,
        "Question": "Full form of KERS is  ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The kinetic energy recovery system",
            "b) The kinetic ever recovery system",
            "c) Kin ever recovery system",
            "d) The kinetic energy recovery store"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Inverters are used to convert DC power into variable AC power. The variable AC power means variable frequency and variable voltage level."
    },
    {
        "id": 760,
        "Question": "Full form of IGBT is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Insulated gate bipolar transistor",
            "b) Insulated gate bipolar transducer",
            "c) Insulator gate bidirectional transducer",
            "d) Insulated gate bidirectional transistor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Short-circuit problem is severe in case of voltage source inverter. The output voltage of VSI is fixed but the output current depends upon the load. When Z=0, I=V÷Z=∞."
    },
    {
        "id": 761,
        "Question": "Flywheel is analogous to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical battery",
            "b) Mechanical battery",
            "c) Nuclear battery",
            "d) Electrostatic battery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Full form of KERS is the Kinetic energy recovery system. The systems recover the kinetic energy from the heat generated by the car’s braking."
    },
    {
        "id": 762,
        "Question": "Energy is stored in Flywheel in the form of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kinetic energy",
            "b) Electrical energy",
            "c) Solar energy",
            "d) Wind energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Full form of IGBT is Insulated gate bipolar transistor. It is a 3-terminal device, bipolar in nature. It can be used as a switch."
    },
    {
        "id": 763,
        "Question": "Calculate the coefficient of fluctuation of speed using the data: Vmax(Fluctuation)=25 m/sec, Vmean=12 m/sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.08",
            "b) 2.16",
            "c) 2.34",
            "d) 2.74"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A flywheel is a heavy wheel that stores a high amount of rotational kinetic energy. It requires a lot of force to spin the wheel."
    },
    {
        "id": 764,
        "Question": "Calculate the maximum fluctuation of speed using the data: Vmax=23 m/sec, Vmin=13 m/sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 14",
            "d) 15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Energy is stored in Flywheel in the form of kinetic energy. It stores the rotational kinetic energy. "
    },
    {
        "id": 765,
        "Question": "Calculate Kinetic energy of the object of mass = 7 Kg moving in a straight line with a velocity of 12 m/s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 504 J",
            "b) 502 J",
            "c) 503 J",
            "d) 509 J"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The coefficient of fluctuation of speed is the ratio of the maximum fluctuation speed and mean speed. C.F = Vmax(Fluctuation) ÷ Vmean = 25÷12 = 2.08."
    },
    {
        "id": 766,
        "Question": "Calculate the rotational kinetic energy of the object using the data: I=5 Kg-m2, ω=25 rad/sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.46 KJ",
            "b) 1.56 KJ",
            "c) 2.58 KJ",
            "d) 3.15 KJ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum fluctuation of speed is the difference between the maximum speed and minimum speed. Maximum fluctuation of speed= Vmax – Vmin = 23 – 13 = 10."
    },
    {
        "id": 767,
        "Question": "Calculate the line voltage for 3-∅ 120° VSI if the value of DC supply is 96 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 68.25 V",
            "b) 67.87 V",
            "c) 66.25 V",
            "d) 62.14 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Kinetic energy of the object of mass = 7 Kg moving in a straight line with a velocity of 12 m/s is .5×m×v2 = .5×7×12×12 = 504 J."
    },
    {
        "id": 768,
        "Question": "Calculate the phase voltage for 3-∅ 120° VSI if the value of DC supply is 78 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30.45 V",
            "b) 15.18 V",
            "c) 31.84 V",
            "d) 48.15 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Kinetic energy of the object having a moment of inertia=5 kg-m2 rotating with an angular velocity equals to 25 rad/sec is .5×I×ω2 = .5×5×25×25 = 1.56 KJ."
    },
    {
        "id": 769,
        "Question": "Calculate the r.m.s value of thyristor current in 3-Φ Full wave converter for the load current=2 A and α=59°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.15 A",
            "b) 2.55 A",
            "c) 2.07 A",
            "d) 2.89 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The line voltage for 3-∅ 120° VSI is (VDC÷√2)=.707×96=67.87 V. In 3-phase 120° VSI each phase conducts for 120° and only three switches from different phases conduct at a single time."
    },
    {
        "id": 770,
        "Question": "Calculate the average value of thyristor current in 3-Φ Full wave converter for the load current=729 A and α=3°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 254 A",
            "b) 285 A",
            "c) 247 A",
            "d) 243 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The line voltage for 3-∅ 120° VSI is (VDC÷√6)=31.84 V. In 3-phase 120° VSI each phase conducts for 120° and only three switches from different phases conduct at a single time."
    },
    {
        "id": 771,
        "Question": "1600 V rated 8 SCRs are connected in series. The operation voltage of the string is 4400. Calculate the string efficiency.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 34.37 %",
            "b) 30.15 %",
            "c) 38.48 %",
            "d) 35.84 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The r.m.s value of thyristor current in 3-Φ Full wave converter is Io√1÷3. It is the r.m.s value of the thyristor current. I(r.m.s) = Io√1÷3=1.15 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 772,
        "Question": "Which one of the element is used to make R load commutating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inductor",
            "b) Capacitor",
            "c) Resistor",
            "d) Coil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The inductor in CSI is used to make the source current constant. The input current of CSI should be constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 773,
        "Question": "Calculate the minimum time period for ASCI using the data: R=12 kΩ, C=45 μF.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.58 sec",
            "b) 2.16 sec",
            "c) 2.23 sec",
            "d) 2.48 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The output voltage of CSI depends upon the load. The output current of CSI is fixed as the input source current is fixed."
    },
    {
        "id": 774,
        "Question": "Full form of ASCI is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Auto sequential commutated inverter",
            "b) Auto starter commutated inverter",
            "c) Auto sequential current inverter",
            "d) Auto sequential current inserter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Capacitor is used to make the R load commutating. It is used in parallel with the resistive load."
    },
    {
        "id": 775,
        "Question": "Calculate the maximum frequency for ASCI using the data: R=15 kΩ, C=5 μF.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.51 Hz",
            "b) 3.69 Hz",
            "c) 3.33 Hz",
            "d) 3.98 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum time period for ASCI is a 4×R×C = 4×12×45×.001 = 2.16 sec. The total time is the sum of charging and discharging time."
    },
    {
        "id": 776,
        "Question": "The output current waveform for R load in CSI is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Square",
            "b) Triangular",
            "c) Constant",
            "d) Vertical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ASCI stands for Auto sequential commutated inverter. No external forced commutation is required for ASCI. The capacitor itself works as a load commutated inverter."
    },
    {
        "id": 777,
        "Question": "T.H.D value for CSI is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 48.43 %",
            "b) 41.15 %",
            "c) 39.15 %",
            "d) 46.48 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum frequency for ASCI is a 1÷(4×R×C) = 1÷(4×15×5×.001) = 3.33 Hz. The total frequency is the sum of charging and discharging frequency."
    },
    {
        "id": 778,
        "Question": "What is the distortion factor value in CSI?",
        "Options": [
            "a) .85",
            "b) .90",
            "c) .95",
            "d) .88"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The output current of CSI for R load is square in nature. The amplitude of the output current varies from I to -I."
    },
    {
        "id": 779,
        "Question": "Number of switches turned on in CSI at a single time are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: T.H.D value for VSI is 48.43 %. Triplen harmonics are present in CSI due to which harmonic content increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 780,
        "Question": "Calculate the r.m.s value of the output current having an amplitude of 2 A for CSI.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 A",
            "b) 4 A",
            "c) 2 A",
            "d) 1 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The distortion value in CSI is .90. The r.m.s value of the fundamental current is 2√2I÷π and r.m.s value of the output current is I. The distortion factor is (2√2I÷π)÷I = .90."
    },
    {
        "id": 781,
        "Question": "Calculate the r.m.s value of the fundamental component of the output current having an amplitude of 3 A for CSI.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.80 A",
            "b) 2.70 A",
            "c) 2.54 A",
            "d) 3.48 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In CSI two switches conduct at a single time. The common switch used in CSI is thyristor. Thyristors are unidirectional, bipolar in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 782,
        "Question": "Calculate the string efficiency if the de-rating factor is .76.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24 %",
            "b) 25 %",
            "c) 26 %",
            "d) 27 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The r.m.s value of the output current having an amplitude of 2 A for CSI is 2A. The waveform for output current is a square wave. The r.m.s value of the square wave is its amplitude."
    },
    {
        "id": 783,
        "Question": "20 V rated 8 SCRs are connected in series. The operation voltage of the string is 50. Calculate the De-rating factor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .67",
            "b) .68",
            "c) .69",
            "d) .70"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The r.m.s value of the fundamental component of the output current is 2√2I÷π=8.48÷3.14=2.70 A. The r.m.s value of the output current is I. "
    },
    {
        "id": 784,
        "Question": "Forced commutated CSI require _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diode",
            "b) Resistor",
            "c) Inductor",
            "d) Capacitor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The string efficiency is calculated for series and parallel connection of SCRs. The value of string efficiency is 1-(De-rating factor)=1-.76=24 %."
    },
    {
        "id": 785,
        "Question": "A solar cell converts light energy into __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrical energy",
            "b) Thermal energy",
            "c) Sound energy",
            "d) Heat energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A solar cell converts light energy into electrical energy. The light energy excites the electron of the solar cell which further flows in the circuit and constitutes the electric current."
    },
    {
        "id": 786,
        "Question": "Series and parallel combination of the solar cell is known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solar array",
            "b) Solar light",
            "c) Solar sight",
            "d) Solar eye"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are three types of solar cells. Single crystal, polycrystal, and amorphous silicon cells are the major types of solar cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 787,
        "Question": "Full form of FF in the solar field is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Form factor",
            "b) Fill factor",
            "c) Face factor",
            "d) Fire factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Series and parallel combination of the solar cell is known as Solar array. Shunt diodes are used to avoid the circulating current."
    },
    {
        "id": 788,
        "Question": "Calculate Fill factor using the data: Pmax=15 W, Voc=18 V, Isc=4 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .65",
            "b) .59",
            "c) .20",
            "d) .98"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: FF stands for Fill factor. It is the ratio of the maximum obtainable power to the product of the open-circuit voltage and short circuit current."
    },
    {
        "id": 789,
        "Question": "Calculate the line voltage in star connection when phase voltage=311 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 548.29 V",
            "b) 538.66 V",
            "c) 587.28 V",
            "d) 185.58 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fill factor is the ratio of the maximum obtainable power to the product of the open-circuit voltage and short circuit current. F.F=Pmax÷(Voc×Isc)=15/72=.20."
    },
    {
        "id": 790,
        "Question": "The slope of the V-I curve of a solar cell is 66.1°. Calculate the value of resistance. Assume the relationship between voltage and current is a straight line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.5 Ω",
            "b) 2.2 Ω",
            "c) 2.5 Ω",
            "d) 2.9 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Permanent magnet DC motor is more expensive than an Induction motor because of the magnetic used in it. Magnets are made up of ferromagnetic material which results in high cost."
    },
    {
        "id": 791,
        "Question": "SCIM has a  _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shorter life",
            "b) Medium life",
            "c) Longer life",
            "d) Infinite life"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The line voltage in case of star connection is 1.73 times of phase voltage. It leads the phase voltage by an angle of 30°. VL-L = 1.73×311 = 538.66 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 792,
        "Question": "The power factor of a SCIM generally is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) .1-.2",
            "b) .6-.8",
            "c) .3-.4",
            "d) .5-.7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The slope of the V-I curve of a solar cell is resistance. The slope given is 66.1° so R=tan(66.1°)=2.2 Ω. The slope of the I-V curve is reciprocal of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 793,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 11710 H inductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8245 W",
            "b) 1781 W",
            "c) 0 W",
            "d) 1964 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: SCIM stands for squirrel cage induction motor. It has high efficiency, maintenance-free operation, and long life because of rigidness nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 794,
        "Question": "Calculate the frequency of the waveform i(t) = sin(πt+π÷4)+sin(πt+π÷74).",
        "Options": [
            "a) .5 Hz",
            "b) .8 Hz",
            "c) .1 Hz",
            "d) .9 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At light loads, the current drawn is largely a magnetizing current due to the air gap and hence the power factor is low. The power factor of a SCIM generally is .6-.8."
    },
    {
        "id": 795,
        "Question": "Full form of CEL is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Central Electronics Limited",
            "b) Central Electrical Limited",
            "c) Circle Electronics Limited",
            "d) Circle Electrical Limited"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90° = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 796,
        "Question": "Full form of BEL is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Busy Electronics Limited",
            "b) Burden Electrical Limited",
            "c) Bharat Electronics Limited",
            "d) Brahma Electrical Limited"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fundamental time period of the sine wave is 2π. The time period of i(t) is L.C.M {2,2}=2 sec. The frequency of the waveform is 1/2 = .5 Hz. The time period is independent of phase shifting and time-shifting."
    },
    {
        "id": 797,
        "Question": "Material used for making solar cell is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silicon",
            "b) Carbon",
            "c) Sodium",
            "d) Magnesium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The full form of CEL is Central Electronics Limited. It is a Government of India enterprise founded in 1974. It is a publicly listed company."
    },
    {
        "id": 798,
        "Question": "The output power of the centrifugal pump is proportional to the _________ of the speed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Square",
            "b) Cube",
            "c) Square-root",
            "d) Cube-root"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The output power of the centrifugal pump is proportional to the cube of the speed. They require a small torque to start."
    },
    {
        "id": 799,
        "Question": "Which of the relationship is correct in Permanent magnet DC motor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) T ∝ (Ia)2",
            "b) T ∝ (Ia)0",
            "c) T ∝ Ia",
            "d) T2 ∝ Ia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are two types of Water pumps. Centrifugal and reciprocating are the major types of water pumps."
    },
    {
        "id": 800,
        "Question": "Calculate Fill factor using the data: Pmax=5 W, Voc=5 V, Isc=1 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The output of the solar panel is DC. Inverters are used at the output terminals of the solar panel in order to convert DC into AC."
    },
    {
        "id": 801,
        "Question": "Full form of ICE is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal Combustion Engine",
            "b) International Combustion Engine",
            "c) Iterative Combustion Engine",
            "d) Iterative Commercial Engine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of flux remains constant in Permanent magnet DC motor. The torque in the PMMC motor is directly proportional to the armature current."
    },
    {
        "id": 802,
        "Question": "Which of the relationship is correct in Permanent magnet DC motor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) E ∝ (N)2",
            "b) E ∝ (N)0",
            "c) E ∝ N",
            "d) E2 ∝ N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fill factor is the ratio of the maximum obtainable power to the product of the open-circuit voltage and short circuit current. F.F=Pmax÷(Voc×Isc)=5/5=1."
    },
    {
        "id": 803,
        "Question": "Full form of SSS is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saur Sujala Yojana",
            "b) Saur Solar Yojana",
            "c) Solar Sun Yojana",
            "d) Sun Sujala Yojana"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Full form of ICE is International Combustion Engine. It consists of pistons inside the closed chamber in order to drive the machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 804,
        "Question": "Who made the first solar cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gerald Pearson",
            "b) Tim Bell",
            "c) Tim Cook",
            "d) Nicola Tesla"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of flux remains constant in Permanent magnet DC motor. The back e.m.f in the PMMC motor is directly proportional to the speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 805,
        "Question": "When was the first solar cell invented?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1950",
            "b) 1954",
            "c) 1965",
            "d) 1952"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Full form of SSS is Saur Sujala Yojana. It is an initiative by the Government of India to encourage people to use solar energy as an energy source."
    },
    {
        "id": 806,
        "Question": "Who invented the first Solar car?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ian Bell",
            "b) Trent Boult",
            "c) Jon Woakes",
            "d) William G. Cobb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first solar cell was made by Gerald Pearson in 1954 in Bell laboratories. It was a lithium-silicon photovoltaic cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 807,
        "Question": "The power factor of a WRIM generally is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) .1-.2",
            "b) .6-.8",
            "c) .3-.4",
            "d) .5-.7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first solar cell was made by Gerald Pearson in 1954 in Bell laboratories. It was a lithium-silicon photovoltaic cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 808,
        "Question": "Full form of BHEL is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bharat Heavy Electronics Limited",
            "b) Bharat Heavy Electrical Limited",
            "c) Bharat Hero Electronics Limited",
            "d) Busy Hero Electrical Limited"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The first solar car was invented by William G. Cobb in 1955. It was a 15-inch vehicle. It was made by General Motors."
    },
    {
        "id": 809,
        "Question": "Calculate peak-peak voltage if Vmax=0 V and Vmin=9 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) -5 V",
            "b) -6 V",
            "c) -9 V",
            "d) -10 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: At light loads, the current drawn is largely a magnetizing current due to the air gap and hence the power factor is low. The power factor of a WRIM generally is .5-.7."
    },
    {
        "id": 810,
        "Question": "Calculate the De-rating factor if the string efficiency is 5 %.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .95",
            "b) .55",
            "c) .65",
            "d) .85"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Full form of BHEL is Bharat Heavy Electrical Limited. It is a Government of India enterprise founded in 1964. It is a publicly listed company."
    },
    {
        "id": 811,
        "Question": "When was the first electric car invented?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1830",
            "b) 1985",
            "c) 1832",
            "d) 1945"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first electric car was developed by Robert Anderson in 1832. It was the first crude electric vehicle. Electric cars are the future of the automobile industry."
    },
    {
        "id": 812,
        "Question": "The moving coil instrument measures the ___________ of the signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average value",
            "b) R.M.S value",
            "c) Zero value",
            "d) Half value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The moving coil instrument measures the R.M.S value of the signal. The moving coil instrument can be used to measure the DC value."
    },
    {
        "id": 813,
        "Question": "Which of the relationship is correct in Ferromagnetic motor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) T ∝ (Ia)2",
            "b) T ∝ (Ia)0",
            "c) T ∝ Ia",
            "d) T2 ∝ Ia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Permanent magnetic moving coil instrument measures the average value of the signal. It is not suitable for AC measurement as pointer fluctuates in case of AC measurement."
    },
    {
        "id": 814,
        "Question": "Calculate Fill factor using the data: Pmax=5 W, Voc=0 V, Isc=1 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ∞",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of flux remains constant in Ferromagnetic motor. The torque in the Ferromagnetic motor is directly proportional to the armature current."
    },
    {
        "id": 815,
        "Question": "Electric Vehicles are generally powered by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminum batteries",
            "b) Lead-acid batteries",
            "c) Sodium batteries",
            "d) Magnesium batteries"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fill factor is the ratio of the maximum obtainable power to the product of the open-circuit voltage and short circuit current. F.F = Pmax ÷ (Voc×Isc) = 5/0 = ∞."
    },
    {
        "id": 816,
        "Question": "Calculate the line voltage in star connection when phase voltage=315 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 545.5 V",
            "b) 548.6 V",
            "c) 547.8 V",
            "d) 585.8 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electric vehicles are generally powered by Lead-acid batteries. They consist of lead electrodes with H2SO4 as an electrolyte."
    },
    {
        "id": 817,
        "Question": "Who coined the term battery?",
        "Options": [
            "a) George Franklin",
            "b) Benjamin Fernandes",
            "c) Benjamin Franklin",
            "d) George Bush"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The line voltage in the case of star connection is 1.73 times of phase voltage. It leads the phase voltage by an angle of 30°. VL-L=1.73×315=545.5 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 818,
        "Question": "Who invented the battery?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alessandro Volta",
            "b) Alexander Bell",
            "c) Alessandro Bell",
            "d) Tim Southee"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Benjamin Franklin was the first who coined the term battery. Batteries were the main source of electrical energy before the invention of generators."
    },
    {
        "id": 819,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in a 315 F capacitor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45 W",
            "b) 81 W",
            "c) 0 W",
            "d) 64 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A battery converts the chemical energy into electrical energy. Alessandro Volta invented the battery in 1800. He was an Italian scientist."
    },
    {
        "id": 820,
        "Question": "Calculate the frequency of the waveform v(t) = sin(πt+π÷4) + sin(πt+π÷74) + sin(πt+π÷56).",
        "Options": [
            "a) .1 Hz",
            "b) .8 Hz",
            "c) .5 Hz",
            "d) .2 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A battery is a combination of cells connected in parallel and series. It converts chemical energy into electrical energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 821,
        "Question": "Full form of EV is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Energy voltage",
            "b) Electric vehicles",
            "c) Electric voltage",
            "d) Energy vehicles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The capacitor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the capacitor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90° = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 822,
        "Question": "Full form of ICV is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal combustion vehicles",
            "b) Internet combustion vehicles",
            "c) Internally combined vehicles",
            "d) Internet combined vehicles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The fundamental time period of the sine wave is 2π. The time period of i(t) is L.C.M {2,2,2}=2 sec. The frequency of the waveform is 1/2=.5 Hz. The time period is independent of phase shifting and time-shifting."
    },
    {
        "id": 823,
        "Question": "The shape of pantograph collector is _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Square",
            "b) Pentagon",
            "c) Circle",
            "d) Hexagon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mainline trains and suburban trains are the two types of trains. They run on fixed rails. They are powered by electricity."
    },
    {
        "id": 824,
        "Question": "Full form of EMU is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electronics Multiple Unit",
            "b) Electrical Multiple Unit",
            "c) Electrical Multiple Usage",
            "d) Electrical Multiple User"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The shape of the pantograph collector is a pentagon. It has a conducting strip which is pressed against contact wire with the help of springs."
    },
    {
        "id": 825,
        "Question": "Who is known as the Father of Indian Railways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lord Dalhousie",
            "b) Lord Ripon",
            "c) Lord Boult",
            "d) Lord Hero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Open frame, faiveley, crossed arm are typically three types of the pantograph. The function of the pantograph is to maintain pressure and prevent vertical vibrations."
    },
    {
        "id": 826,
        "Question": "Who built the first train?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Richardson",
            "b) Rampa",
            "c) Richard Trevithick",
            "d) John Carry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Full form of EMU is Electrical Multiple Unit. The trains having motor coaches and trailer coaches are known as EMU trains. They provide flexibility."
    },
    {
        "id": 827,
        "Question": "Who built the first bullet train?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hideo Rampa",
            "b) Hideo Shima",
            "c) Hideo Carry",
            "d) Hideo Stokes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lord Dalhousie is known as the father of the Indian Railways. The first railway line connecting Bombay with Thane was laid in 1853."
    },
    {
        "id": 828,
        "Question": "The supply conductor in electric trains is also known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contact Wire",
            "b) Contact Distance",
            "c) Contact Direction",
            "d) Supply Wire"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Richard Trevithick built the first train in 1804. It was a steam locomotive train that used to carry 10 tonnes of iron from one place to another."
    },
    {
        "id": 829,
        "Question": "Calculate the value measured by PMMC when a sinusoidal voltage signal is applied to it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15 V",
            "b) 0 V",
            "c) 16 V",
            "d) 18 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hideo Shima built the first bullet train. He was a Japenese engineer. He was born in 1901 and died in 1998. He was the man behind the concept of a bullet train."
    },
    {
        "id": 830,
        "Question": "Calculate the value measured by Moving Iron when a sinusoidal voltage signal V(t)=20sin(ωt) is applied to it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 14.14 V",
            "b) 20.15 V",
            "c) 16.18 V",
            "d) 22.18 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The supply conductor in electric trains is also known as Contact wire. Driving motor and power modulators are housed in the locomotive."
    },
    {
        "id": 831,
        "Question": "Full form of PMMC is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Permanent Magnet Moving Coil",
            "b) Premature Magnet Moving Coil",
            "c) Permanent Magnet Motion Coil",
            "d) Peterson Magnet Motion Coil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: PMMC instrument measures the average of the input signal. The sinusoidal voltage signal is symmetric about the origin. The average value measured by PMMC is zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 832,
        "Question": "Fuel used in the train is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diesel",
            "b) Kerosene",
            "c) Petrol",
            "d) Ice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Moving iron instrument measures the r.m.s value of the input signal. The r.m.s value of the sinusoidal signal is 20÷√2=14.14 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 833,
        "Question": "How much fuel does a train use per Km?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7.85 L/Km",
            "b) 7.97 L/Km",
            "c) 6.59 L/Km",
            "d) 7.15 L/Km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Full form of PMMC is Permanent Magnet Moving Coil. It measures the average value of the applied input signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 834,
        "Question": "Which motor is used in the Electric train?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DC shunt motor",
            "b) DC series motor",
            "c) Synchronous motor",
            "d) Stepper motor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fuel used in the train is Diesel. Diesel fuel in trains provides more efficiency and more economy. It is more economical than air travel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 835,
        "Question": "Calculate the minimum time period for ASCI using the data: R=1 kΩ, C=1 μF.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 msec",
            "b) 8 msec",
            "c) 5 msec",
            "d) 3 msec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The average fuel consumed by a train is 7.97 L/Km. Consumption is the same for passenger and cargo trains. "
    },
    {
        "id": 836,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the coefficient of friction using the data: F=24 N, Normal force=12 N.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 8",
            "d) 9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are two types of friction. Internal and external friction are types of friction. Coefficient of friction is independent of the force of friction."
    },
    {
        "id": 837,
        "Question": "If the friction force value is doubled, calculate the new value of the coefficient of friction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 times of the original value",
            "b) 2 times of the original value",
            "c) 7 times of the original value",
            "d) Remains the same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Coefficient of friction is the ratio of the friction force and normal force. It is dependent on the smoothness of the surface area. μ=24÷12=2."
    },
    {
        "id": 838,
        "Question": "The frictional force always acts in the _________ direction of motion of the body.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Opposite",
            "b) Same",
            "c) Perpendicular",
            "d) Vertical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of the coefficient of friction will not change if the friction force is doubled. It only depends upon the nature of the surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 839,
        "Question": "Calculate the coefficient of friction if the angle of inclination is 60°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.73",
            "b) 1.73",
            "c) 2.48",
            "d) 1.41"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The friction of force always acts in the opposite direction of the motion of the body. It is a non-conservative force. It helps in the motion of the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 840,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is the correct relationship?",
        "Options": [
            "a) F=μR",
            "b) F=4μR",
            "c) F=3μR",
            "d) F=2μR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The coefficient of friction is the tangent of the angle of the inclined plane. The value of μ is the tan(60°)=1.73. The coefficient of friction depends on the nature of the surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 841,
        "Question": "Calculate the velocity of the bottom point of the wheel for perfect rolling using the data: r=20 cm, ω=100 rad/sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 m/sec",
            "b) 40 m/sec",
            "c) 60 m/sec",
            "d) 80 m/sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the friction force is the product of the coefficient of friction and normal reaction. The correct value is F=μR."
    },
    {
        "id": 842,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the coefficient of adhesion for dusty rails if the value of the coefficient of adhesion for dry rails is .55.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.65",
            "b) 0.89",
            "c) 0.97",
            "d) 0.48"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The velocity of the bottom point of the wheel for perfect rolling is the product of the radius and angular velocity. It is expressed in terms of m/sec. V = r×ω = .2×100=20 m/sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 843,
        "Question": "Calculate the value measured by Moving Iron when a sinusoidal voltage signal V(t) = √2sin(3ωt) is applied to it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 V",
            "b) 1 V",
            "c) 3 V",
            "d) 4 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The coefficient of adhesion is maximum when rails are dry. The coefficient of adhesion depends on the nature of the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 844,
        "Question": "The value of area under a velocity-time graph is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acceleration",
            "b) Displacement",
            "c) Force",
            "d) Momentum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of the coefficient of adhesion for dusty rails is .48. The value of the coefficient of adhesion for dry rails is maximum."
    },
    {
        "id": 845,
        "Question": "The value of area under acceleration-time graph is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Velocity",
            "b) Displacement",
            "c) Force",
            "d) Impulse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Moving iron instrument measures the r.m.s value of the input signal. The r.m.s value of the sinusoidal signal is √2÷√2 = 1 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 846,
        "Question": "The value of area under force-time graph is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reaction",
            "b) Change in momentum",
            "c) Force",
            "d) Torque"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of the area under a velocity-time graph is displacement. The velocity is the ratio of displacement and time."
    },
    {
        "id": 847,
        "Question": "Full form of HVDC is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High Voltage Direct Current",
            "b) High Voltage Distribution Combination",
            "c) High-Value Direct Current",
            "d) High-Value Distribution Combination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the area under an acceleration-time graph is velocity. The acceleration is the ratio of velocity and time."
    },
    {
        "id": 848,
        "Question": "Full form of HVAC is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High Voltage Alternative Current",
            "b) High Voltage Alternating Current",
            "c) High-Value Alternating Combination",
            "d) High-Value Alternative Counter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of the area under a force-time graph is a change in momentum. The force is the ratio of change in momentum with respect to time."
    },
    {
        "id": 849,
        "Question": "Full form of SVC is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Static Var Compensator",
            "b) Static Variable Counter",
            "c) State Value Counter",
            "d) Static Value Compensator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The full form of SVC is Static Var Compensator. It is a FACTS controller used for reactive power compensation. It maintains the voltage profile."
    },
    {
        "id": 850,
        "Question": "Full form of STATCOM is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Static Synchronous Counter",
            "b) Static Synchronous Compensator",
            "c) State Synchronized Compensator",
            "d) State System Counter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The full form of STATCOM is a Static synchronous compensator. It is a voltage source converter. It maintains the voltage profile of the system. It is a FACTS controller."
    },
    {
        "id": 851,
        "Question": "The circuit which operates signals is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Track circuit",
            "b) Fellow circuit",
            "c) Ground circuit",
            "d) Unit circuit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The circuit which operates signals is called track circuit. Its supply consists of low AC or DC voltage supply. Running rail is used as the return line for the track circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 852,
        "Question": "SVC is used to maintain the power factor above __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) .2",
            "b) .5",
            "c) .8",
            "d) .6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: SVC stands for static var compensator. It is the FACTS controller used for reducing the harmonics from the system. It is used for reactive power compensation."
    },
    {
        "id": 853,
        "Question": "Which is the most severe type of fault?",
        "Options": [
            "a) LL",
            "b) LLG",
            "c) LLL",
            "d) LLLG"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: LLLG fault is the most severe type of fault. The order of severity is maximum for LLLG fault. LG fault is more severe at the generator terminals."
    },
    {
        "id": 854,
        "Question": "If induction motor air gap power is 11 KW and mechanically developed power is 2 KW, then rotor ohmic loss will be _________ KW.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 9",
            "d) 11"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Skin effect increases with the increase in frequency. The value of skin depth decreases with the increase in frequency."
    },
    {
        "id": 855,
        "Question": "If induction motor rotor power is 26 KW and gross developed power is 21 KW, then rotor ohmic loss will be _________ KW.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 7",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rotor ohmic losses are due to the resistance of armature windings. Net input power to the rotor is equal to the sum of rotor ohmic losses and mechanically developed power. Rotor ohmic losses = Air gap power – Mechanical developed power = 11-2 = 9 KW."
    },
    {
        "id": 856,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in 14 μH inductors if the THD value is 58.1%.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 W",
            "b) 9 W",
            "c) 4 W",
            "d) 0 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rotor ohmic losses are due to the resistance of armature windings. Net input power to the rotor is equal to the sum of rotor ohmic losses and mechanically developed power. Rotor ohmic losses=Air gap power-Mechanical developed power=26-21=5 KW."
    },
    {
        "id": 857,
        "Question": "Calculate the power factor using the data: P=15 W, S=25 VA.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 0.9",
            "c) 0.4",
            "d) 0.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The inductor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the inductor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90° = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 858,
        "Question": "Calculate the active power in 56 μF capacitor if the VRF value is 5.1%.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 W",
            "b) 0 W",
            "c) 9 W",
            "d) 2 W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The power factor is the ratio of active power and apparent power. The value of the power factor is P÷S=15÷25=.6."
    },
    {
        "id": 859,
        "Question": "Calculate the apparent power using the data: P=3 W, Q=4 VAR.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 VA",
            "b) 6 VA",
            "c) 9 VA",
            "d) 2 VA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The capacitor is a linear element. It only absorbs reactive power and stores it in the form of oscillating energy. The voltage and current are 90° in phase in case of the capacitor so the angle between V & I is 90°. P = VIcos90° = 0 W."
    },
    {
        "id": 860,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of impedance using the data: R=2 Ω, XL=4 Ω.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.5 Ω",
            "b) 5.4 Ω",
            "c) 2.5 Ω",
            "d) 4.4 Ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The apparent power is the product of the voltage and current conjugate phasor. The value of apparent power is (9+16).5 = 5 VA."
    },
    {
        "id": 861,
        "Question": "Which type of grounding is used to suppress the capacitive effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid grounding",
            "b) Reactance grounding",
            "c) Resistance grounding",
            "d) Peterson coil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of impedance is {(R)2+(XL)2).5 = (4+16).5 = 4.4 Ω. It is total impedance offered by an AC circuit. It is expressed in Ω."
    },
    {
        "id": 862,
        "Question": "Calculate the minimum anode current required to turn off SCR if the latching current value is 2 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 A",
            "b) 3 A",
            "c) 4 A",
            "d) 5 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum anode current required to turn off the SCR is the latching current. The value of the latching current is 2 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 863,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the coefficient of static friction using the data: F=4 N, Normal force=16 N.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .24",
            "b) .25",
            "c) .15",
            "d) .14"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Coefficient of friction is the ratio of the friction force and normal force. It is dependent on the smoothness of the surface area. μ = 4÷16 = .25."
    },
    {
        "id": 864,
        "Question": "Full form of TVS is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transient voltage suppression",
            "b) Transient voltage surge",
            "c) Total voltage surge",
            "d) True voltage surge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The full form of TVS is Transient voltage suppression. It is one of the types of light surge suppressors. It is used to suppress transient voltages."
    },
    {
        "id": 865,
        "Question": "Calculate the coefficient of friction if the angle of inclination is 0°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The friction of force always acts in the opposite direction of the motion of the body. It is a non-conservative force. It helps in the motion of the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 866,
        "Question": "When was the first train built?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1804",
            "b) 1810",
            "c) 1814",
            "d) 1820"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The coefficient of friction is the tangent of the angle of the inclined plane. The value of μ is the tan(0°) = 0. The coefficient of friction depends on the nature of the surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 867,
        "Question": "Who invented the first circuit breaker?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Albert Einstein",
            "b) Thomas Edison",
            "c) Nicola Tesla",
            "d) Trent Boult"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Richard Trevithick built the first train in 1804. It was a steam locomotive train that used to carry 10 tonnes of iron from one place to another."
    },
    {
        "id": 868,
        "Question": "Full form of LSS is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Line Surge Suppressors",
            "b) Local Surge System",
            "c) Local Surge Suppressors",
            "d) Line Surge  System"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thomas Edison was the inventor of the circuit breaker. It was designed in 1879. It was an early form of the circuit breaker."
    },
    {
        "id": 869,
        "Question": "Calculate the value measured by PMMC when a sinusoidal voltage signal V(t)=20sin(ωt) is applied to it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 V",
            "b) 2 V",
            "c) 6 V",
            "d) 0 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The supply conductor in electric trains is also known as Contact wire. Driving motor and power modulators are housed in the locomotive."
    },
    {
        "id": 870,
        "Question": "Full form of MCC is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Motor control center",
            "b) Motor counter center",
            "c) Machine control center",
            "d) Motor coil counter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Full form of LSS is Line surge suppressors. They are used to protect the semiconductor converter against voltage spikes produced in line."
    },
    {
        "id": 871,
        "Question": "Full form of PCC is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Producer control center",
            "b) Poor counter center",
            "c) Power control center",
            "d) Power coil counter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Permanent magnet moving coil instrument measures the average value of the input signal. The average value of the sinusoidal signal is 0 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 872,
        "Question": "Current Chopping is most severe in which one of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air Blast Circuit Breaker",
            "b) Oil Circuit Breaker",
            "c) Air Break Circuit Breaker",
            "d) Vacuum Circuit Breaker"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The full form of MCC is Motor control center. It controls the power to system drives. There can many MCCs exist in an area."
    },
    {
        "id": 873,
        "Question": "Oil circuit breaker is mainly used in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Synchronous machine",
            "b) Induction machine",
            "c) DC machine",
            "d) Transformer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The full form of PCC is Power control center. They receive power from the main power distribution center."
    },
    {
        "id": 874,
        "Question": "Full form of PLC is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Programmable Logic Controller",
            "b) Programmable Language Controller",
            "c) Peterson Language Counter",
            "d) Programmable Logic Counter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Current chopping is most severe in the case of Air blast circuit breaker. Resistance switching is used to avoid the problem of current chopping."
    },
    {
        "id": 875,
        "Question": "Full form of LED is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Light Emitting Diode",
            "b) Light Emission Digital",
            "c) Light Energy Diode",
            "d) Light Energy Digital"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Relay is an electromechanical switch. It uses electrical signals as input and mechanical operation as an output."
    },
    {
        "id": 876,
        "Question": "Inter turn fault can be detected by using __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oil circuit breaker",
            "b) Split phase relay",
            "c) SF6 circuit breaker",
            "d) Vertical breaker"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mho relay is an inherent directional relay. It is used in the long transmission line. It is less affected by power surges."
    },
    {
        "id": 877,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of the fault impedance if the fault voltage is 2 V and fault current is 4 A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) .5 ohm",
            "b) .2 ohm",
            "c) .4 ohm",
            "d) .6 ohm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The full form of LED is a light-emitting diode. It converts light energy into electrical energy. It works in the reverse bias region."
    },
    {
        "id": 878,
        "Question": "Reactance relay is used in _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Medium line",
            "b) Short transmission line",
            "c) Lossless line",
            "d) Long transmission line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Inter turn fault mainly occurs in the winding of the rotor side of the alternator. They can be detected by using the split-phase relaying technique."
    },
    {
        "id": 879,
        "Question": "Load interrupter operated at ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) No-load",
            "b) Full load",
            "c) Half of the full load",
            "d) One-fourth of the full load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the fault impedance is the ratio of fault voltage and fault current. It is expressed in ohms. Z=V/I=2/4=.5 ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 880,
        "Question": "Calculate the maximum frequency for ASCI using the data: R=1 kΩ, C=1 μF.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 250 Hz",
            "b) 280 Hz",
            "c) 300 Hz",
            "d) 320 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reactance relay is used in a short transmission line. Reactance relay is independent of the resistance value. It protects the short transmission line from any fault."
    },
    {
        "id": 881,
        "Question": "Calculate the PIV for the Full-wave bridge rectifier if the peak value of the supply voltage is 50.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 72.5 V",
            "b) 72.8 V",
            "c) 70.7 V",
            "d) 76.1 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Load interrupter is used to avoid overloading conditions. It separates the under-stressed area from the line. It operates at full load."
    },
    {
        "id": 882,
        "Question": "In single-phase, RLE load, calculate the Peak inverse voltage using the data: (Vs)r.m.s = 9 V, f = 50 Hz,  E = 40 V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 52.2 V",
            "b) 52.7 V",
            "c) 59.7 V",
            "d) 52.9 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum time period for ASCI is a 4×R×C=4×1×1×.001=4 msec. The total time is the sum of charging and discharging time. The maximum frequency is 1÷f=250 Hz."
    }
]